<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en" xml:id="ojs-131">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Debates Were to be Held in the Parliament, but it Proved Impossible</title>
            <title>The Federal Assembly and the Velvet Revolution in Czechoslovakia in
                    1989</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Adéla</forename>
                  <surname>Gjuričová</surname>
               </name>
               <roleName>researcher</roleName>
               <roleName>PhD</roleName>
               <affiliation>Institute of Contemporary History of the Czech Academy of
                        Sciences</affiliation>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Puškinovo náměstí 9</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Prague 6</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>16000</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Czech Republic</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>tzahradnicek@seznam.cz</email>
            </author>
            <funder>This paper was written as part of a research project on the “Czechoslovak
                    dissent as a spiritual, cultural and political phenomenon at the times of
                    normalization, revolution and transformation (1969-2000)” that has been
                    supported by a grant from the Czech Science Foundation (GACR,
                    GA15-16256S).</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2015-12-03</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
               <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
               </address>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/131</pubPlace>
            <date>2015</date>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
            </availability>
             <idno type="sistory" corresp="#ojs-131 #ojs-131-search #ojs-131-izvlecek #ojs-131-abstract #ojs-131-article #ojs-131-bibliogr #ojs-131-summary">36120</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
            <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
            <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
            <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
            <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
            <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="sl"/>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Czechoslovakia 1989</term>
               <term>Parliamentarism</term>
               <term>The Federal Assembly</term>
               <term>The Communist Party of Czechoslovakia</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords xml:lang="sl">
               <term> Češkoslovaška 1989</term>
               <term>parlamentarizem</term>
               <term>zvezni parlament</term>
               <term>komunistična partija Češkoslovaške</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change>
               <date>2015-12-03T19:27:59Z</date>
               <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
               <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
            </change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="article" n="Articles">
      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>Debates Were to be Held in the Parliament, but it Proved
                        Impossible</titlePart>
               <titlePart>The Federal Assembly and the Velvet Revolution in Czechoslovakia in
                        1989</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
             <docAuthor>Tomáš Zahradníček</docAuthor>
             <docImprint>
                 <idno type="cobissType">1.01</idno>
                 <idno type="UDC">328(437):323.27"1989"</idno>
             </docImprint>
         </titlePage>
         <divGen type="search" xml:id="ojs-131-search">
            <head>Search</head>
         </divGen>
         <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl" xml:id="ojs-131-izvlecek">
            <head xml:id="ojs.131-head-3">Izvleček</head>
            <head rend="subtitle" xml:id="ojs.131-head-4">V parlamentu naj bi potekale razprave, vendar se je to
                    izkazalo za nemogoče: Zvezni parlament in žametna revolucija na Češkoslovaškem
                    leta 1989</head>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-6">Leta 1989, ko se je zrušil komunistični režim, se je na Češkoslovaškem pogosto
                    ponavljala zahteva, da bi bilo treba pomembno politično razpravo o usmeritvi
                    države voditi zlasti v parlamentu. Vendar se je parlament vse leto izmikal
                    bistvenim političnim razpravam. Zakonodajno telo ni postalo politični oder in
                    forum za pomembne razprave ali prizorišče merjenja moči nasprotnikov. Članek
                    opisuje poskuse pooblastitve parlamenta in analizira razloge za njihov neuspeh.
                    Osredotoča se zlasti na nekaj tednov po padcu berlinskega zidu, ki so na
                    Češkoslovaškem dosegli vrhunec z izvolitvijo Václava Havla in Aleksandra Dubčka
                    na vrhovni ustavni funkciji predsednika in predsednika zveznega parlamenta. </p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-7">Ključne besede: Češkoslovaška 1989, parlamentarizem, zvezni parlament,
                    komunistična partija Češkoslovaške</p>
         </div>
         <div type="abstract" xml:id="ojs-131-abstract">
            <head xml:id="ojs.131-head-5">Abstract</head>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-8">During 1989, the year of the collapse of the Communist regime, a claim was often
                    repeated in Czechoslovakia that substantive political debate about the direction
                    of the country ought to be held particularly in the parliament. Yet the key
                    political debates shun away from the parliament for the entire year. The
                    legislature did not become the stage for politics, a forum for substantive
                    debates or the arena for competing forces. The article maps the attempts to
                    empower the parliament and analyses the reasons for their failure. Particular
                    focus is given to the few weeks after the fall of the Berlin Wall that
                    culminated in Czechoslovakia with the election of Václav Havel and Alexander
                    Dubček to the supreme constitutional posts of the President and Chairman of the
                    Federal Assembly.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-9">Keywords: Czechoslovakia 1989, Parliamentarism, The Federal Assembly, The
                    Communist Party of Czechoslovakia</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="chapter" xml:id="ojs-131-article">
            <head xml:id="ojs.131-head-6">Debates Were to be Held in the Parliament, but it Proved Impossible: The
                    Federal Assembly and the Velvet Revolution in Czechoslovakia in 1989<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn2" n="1">This paper was written as part of a
                        research project on the “Czechoslovak dissent as a spiritual, cultural and
                        political phenomenon at the times of normalization, revolution and
                        transformation (1969-2000)” that has been supported by a grant from the
                        Czech Science Foundation (GACR, GA15-16256S).</note>
            </head>
            <docAuthor xml:id="ojs.131-docAuthor-2">Tomáš Zahradníček<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn1" n="*">researcher, PhD, Institute of Contemporary History of the Czech Academy of
                        Sciences, Puškinovo náměstí 9, Prague 6, 16000, Czech Republic, <ref target="mailto:tzahradnicek@seznam.cz">tzahradnicek@seznam.cz</ref>
               </note>
            </docAuthor>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-10">During the breakthrough year of 1989 a claim was often repeated in Czechoslovakia
                    that substantive political debate about the direction of the country ought to be
                    held particularly in the parliament. Yet the key political debates shun away
                    from the parliament for the entire year. The legislature did not become the
                    stage for politics, a forum for substantive debates or the arena for competing
                    forces. This study maps the attempts to empower the parliament and their
                    failure. Particular focus is given to the few weeks after the fall of the Berlin
                    Wall that culminated in Czechoslovakia with the rise of Václav Havel and
                    Alexander Dubček to the supreme constitutional posts of the President and
                    Chairman of the Federal Assembly.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn3" n="2">The best summary publications about the Czechoslovak November and December
                        1989: James Krapfl, <hi rend="italic">Revolution with a Human Face:
                            Politics, Culture, and Community in Czechoslovakia, 1989-1992</hi>
                        (Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 2013). Jiří Suk, <hi rend="italic">Labyrintem revoluce. Aktéři, zápletky a křižovatky jedné politické
                            krize (od listopadu 1989 do června 1990)</hi> [Through the Labyrinth of
                        the Revolution. Actors, Plots and Crossroads of A Political Crisis (from
                        November 1989 to June 1990)] (Praha: Prostor, 2003).</note>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-11">The Berlin Wall fell on 11 November 1989. On 17 November police in Prague
                    intervened against student demonstration in a manner that triggered mass
                    demonstrations in the coming days in Czechoslovakia as well. Most gatherings
                    took place just a few metres from the Czechoslovak federal parliament – the
                    Federal Assembly, which, however did not merit their attention. During the first
                    street protests the massive flow of protesters repeatedly headed towards the
                    parliament. Yet that was not their destination: the crowd passed the building
                    without major interest and continued a few steps further to the headquarters of
                    the Czechoslovak Radio to demand true information about the developments in
                    Prague. The initial ignorance of the federal parliament building by the
                    protesters shows their realistic assessment of the role of the legislature and
                    its crew in the power gear.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-12">To enhance the role of representative assemblies during socialism was one of the
                    slogans of Mikhail Gorbachevʼs reforms. They had been also translated, quoted
                    and repeated in Czechoslovakia. The parliament was to enhance its autonomy and
                    become “a powerful agent of socialist democracy.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn4" n="3">Gorbachev speaks of “Soviets” that were known as
                        the “National Committees” in Czechoslovak terminology, whilst the three
                        supreme assemblies were called differently: The Czech National Council, the
                        Slovak National Council (the supreme soviets in the republics), and the
                        Federal Assembly. In his criticism of the existing situation Gorbachev used
                        to say: “... the role of the Soviets was weakened. What emerged was what we
                        call the replacement of the roles and activities of the state and
                        administrative bodies by the party organs. (...) In brief, there was a
                        specific deformation of the entire activity of the democratic body which
                        owes its existence to our socialist revolution. Thus the major task that
                        arose in front of us during the reconstruction: to fully renew the role of
                        the Soviets, as the bodies of political power, as bearers and powerful
                        carriers of socialist democracy”. ̶ Michail Sergejevič Gorbačov, <hi rend="italic">Přestavba a nové myšlení pro naši zemi a pro celý svět
                        </hi>[Perestroika and New Thinking for Our Country and the Whole World]
                        (Praha: Svoboda, 1987), 96-97.</note> Possible outcome was only tested by
                    individuals in Prague before the Autumn of 1989. Among them was Evžen Erban,
                    retired high official of the Communist Party. As the first and only more
                    noteworthy politician he invited Václav Havel for a meeting in the Summer of
                    1989. At one point of his long political monologue he told Havel: “I might be
                    arrested in the afternoon ...” to add: “They cannot! They cannot! I have
                    parliamentary immunity!” and pulled out his parliamentary ID card.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn5" n="4">Václav Havel seemed so captivated
                        by that moment that he has not forgotten about it when, from the distance of
                        a few weeks, he recounted the unique encounter of 15 November to Irena
                        Gerová. Irena Gerová, <hi rend="italic">Vyhrabávačky: Deníkové zápisy a
                            rozhovory z let 1988 a 1989</hi> [Digs: Diary Notes and Interviews from
                        1888 and 1989] (Praha, Litomyšl: Paseka, 2009), 137. For additional
                        testimonies about Erbanʼs activities see Zdislav Šulc, <hi rend="italic">Z
                            jeviště i zákulisí české politiky a ekonomiky</hi> [From the Stage and
                        Backstage of Czech Politics and Economics] (Brno: Doplněk, 2011),
                        197.</note> The scene offers a glimpse on some significance attached to
                    parliamentary immunity when deciding about the degree of political courage
                    vis-à-vis political breakthroughs. Yet there is only limited evidence of the
                    kind in Czechoslovakia.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-13">When testing the limits of how far one could have gone in using the federal
                    parliament and uncensored rostrum, Lubomír Štrougal went farthest. Another of
                    the political veterans, having served the top power posts for thirty years,
                    Štrougal withdrew to seclusion probably in hope that he would be invited back.
                    In the Summer of 1989 he reminded the Party leadership of their guilt for the
                    failure of the earlier reform attempts. He skilfully used a language different
                    from that prescribed by the Party leadership. Instead of reconstruction he spoke
                    of “radical reform” and criticised the abandonment of economic policies of the
                    Prague Spring.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn6" n="5">“Politics is the
                        art of the possible, whilst the possible was affected not only by internal,
                        but also international context. (...) The abandonment of the economic reform
                        in the early 1970s was a grave mistake,” stated Štrougal. ̶ <hi rend="italic">Společná česko-slovenská digitální parlamentní
                            knihovna</hi> [Common Digital Czecho-Slovak Parliamentary Library],
                        Federal Assembly 1986-1990, Joint Sessions of the House of People and the
                        House of Nations, Stenographic records, 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                        session, 20. 6. 1989, accessed October 30, 2015,<ref target="http://www.psp.cz/eknih/1986fs/slsn/stenprot/014schuz/s014017.htm">http://www.psp.cz/eknih/1986fs/slsn/stenprot/014schuz/s014017.htm</ref>.
                        Cf. Jaromír Sedlák, <hi rend="italic">Muž nad stolem, aneb Byl jsem
                            Štrougalovým poradcem</hi> [A Man Over The Table or I Was Štrougalʼs
                        Adviser] (Praha: BVD, 2010), 131.</note> His address on 20 June 1989 to the
                    plenary session of the Federal Assembly met with silence among the MPs and the
                    media.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-14">Another attempt was made a few months later by Štrougalʼs successor in the post
                    of the federal Prime Minister, Ladislav Adamec. As constitutional official the
                    Prime Minister was answerable to the federal parliament. At the same time, as
                    member of the Communist Party, he was bound to conformity with the Party
                    leadership. In the Autumn of 1989 Adamec tried to weaken the dependence on the
                    Party leadership by transferring the hitherto internal discussion from the Party
                    grounds to the parliament. Yet the report he had drafted was not approved by his
                    superior Party bodies. Hence on 11 November 1989 the Prime Minister, bound with
                    discipline, had to read to the Federal Assembly statements that included some
                    points that were in contradiction to what he had wanted to say. Nonetheless, he
                    did not give in and spoke later in the debate together with other MPs. With a
                    slight delay he presented his own version of the thesis about the need for
                    political reform. Those passages were, however, later censored by the media upon
                    intervention from the Party headquarters. Such was the infamous fate of the key
                    attempt to transfer political debate from Party corridors to the
                        parliament.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn7" n="6">Miloš Hájek, <hi rend="italic">Paměť české levice</hi> [The Memory of the Czech Left]
                        (Praha: Ústav pro soudobé dějiny AV ČR, 2011), 295.</note>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-15">The attempt by Adamec did not become publicly known and has not entered history:
                    in the days that followed it was outshone by new, more far reaching events. The
                    Civic Forum was established as a wide coalition of those outraged by police
                    brutality against the demonstration in Prague on 17 November 1989. After a few
                    days of mass rallies it became apparent that the retiring power structures were
                    giving up their power quite willingly. Guided by the logic of the existing power
                    system, the attention focused on the development within the Communist Party of
                    Czechoslovakia. The parliament and other political institutions respected the
                    hierarchy.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-16">Personnel changes in the presidium of the Central Committee of the Communist
                    Party of Czechoslovakia were bound to signal a major power shift. The Central
                    Committee was a federal body: two thirds out of the hundred and fifty full
                    members were Czechs. The assembly of the actual power holders convened on 24 and
                    25 November.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn8" n="7">Recordings of both
                        session, after which the leadership was altogether replaced: <hi rend="italic">Poslední hurá. Stenografický záznam z mimořádných zasedání
                            ÚV KSČ 24. a 26. listopadu 1989</hi> [The Final Hooray: Stenographic
                        Record from Extraordinary Sessions of the Central Committee of the Communist
                        Party of Czechoslovakia on 24 and 26 November 1989] (Praha: Agentura Cesty,
                        1992).</note> A few candidates for political leadership spoke actively,
                    including the two aforementioned speakers from the parliament – Lubomír Štrougal
                    and Ladislav Adamec. Yet none of them was given a mandate. A dramatic clash of
                    long warring factions gave rise to the Communist Party leadership to neutral,
                    feeble candidates. The choice meant actual and virtually immediate extinction of
                    the influence of the Party headquarters.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-17">The disintegration of the old institutional centre opened space for activities at
                    other platforms. The first in line to benefit from this for some time was the
                    federal Prime Minister Ladislav Adamec. He held operational power and entered,
                    on his own, into talks about further developments with the Civic Forum. The
                    demands by the Civic Forum headed towards transformation of the political
                    system: a revision of the Constitution, preparation of elections, changes in
                    state posts. All that called for the involvement of the parliament.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-18">As the events evolved, the significance of the parliament rose notably. Yet there
                    was a glitch: mandates were required in order to move political debates to the
                    parliament. Nevertheless, none of the new members of the temporarily governing
                    group surrounding Prime Minister Adamec had them. Adamec himself was not member
                    of the parliament. Naturally, the Civic Forum did not have any parliamentary
                    representatives. Meeting in the federal government building, only one of the
                    seventeen people who gathered on 28 November as part of the delegations of the
                    federal government and the Civic Forum to plan the future of their country, held
                    parliamentary mandate: Bohuslav Kučera, the Chairman of the Czechoslovak
                    Socialist Party.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-19">Who then actually was represented in the parliament? Who were the people who
                    held, at the moment of political change, the 350 mandates? The national key
                    served as the basis of parliamentary mathematics at the Federal Assembly. At the
                    core of the entire complex structure of the institution was representation of
                    deputies from both parts of the federation in the two Houses of the Federal
                    Assembly. The representation in one of them, the House of Nations, was equal.
                    Moreover, the deputies from the Czech Republic and from Slovakia voted
                    separately on Constitutional changes and other major issues subject to debate on
                    which the Constitution stipulated “a ban on majorisation”. Hence the need for
                    identical consensus by both Czech and Slovak majority. In the other chamber, the
                    House of People, the twice more populous Czech Republic had the corresponding
                    majority of mandates.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-20">Additional crucial parliamentary mathematics was based on power control through
                    the privileged and disciplined Communist Party. The thoroughness that gave the
                    Party members priority rights and leading posts was, in the case of the
                    parliament, brought to perfection. Following the elections in 1986, 69 percent
                    of MPs came from the Communist Party of Czechoslovakia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn9" n="8">For the list of MPs elected in 1986 with their
                        political identification and other characteristics see <hi rend="italic">Československo dnes: Zastupitelské sbory, vlády, diplomatické styky,
                            školství, zdravotnictví, ekonomika, kraje ČSSR</hi> [Czechoslovakia
                        Today: Representative Assemblies, Government, Diplomatic Relations, Schools,
                        Healthcare, Economics, and Regions in CSSR] (Praha: Pressfoto, 1987),
                        20-56.</note> The second most numerous group was the “non-partisan” members,
                    representing 18.3 percent. It was an atomised crowd of women and men
                    organisationally linked to the apparatus of the Communist Party.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn10" n="9">The easiest way to describe this
                        is an atomised team of reliable friends of the Party in power, representing
                        some features prescribed by the doctrine of socialist parliamentarism that
                        detailed all qualities and their proportion as ought to be present in the
                        assemblies.</note> The only four individual organisations with some degree
                    of autonomy were represented far more scarcely. The two Czech political parties,
                    the Czechoslovak Socialist Party and the Czechoslovak Peopleʼs Party held
                    identical 5.5 percent of mandates in the Federal Assembly. Each of the two
                    Slovak parties, the Freedom Party and the Party of Slovak Revival held only 1.1
                    percent.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-21">A simple look at the data that were undisclosed at the time in the raw form,
                    shows quite clearly the developmental options for the Federal Assembly: the
                    fundamental question was what would the total of 87 percent of MPs representing
                    the Communist A-team (the faction of the Communist MPs) and the associate B-team
                    (non-partisan MPs), the hitherto pillars of power do. What would they do in the
                    uncertain times when their power centre was falling apart?</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-22">The first joint session in the revolutionary weeks was called for Thursday 29
                    November. The main points in the agenda arose from the government talks with the
                    Civic Forum. The deputy Prime Minister in the Adamec cabinet was to address
                    them. On their way to the parliament the MPs had to pass by instructions from
                    the revolutionary street, saying: “Deputies, vote for your voters, not for
                        yourselves!”<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn11" n="10">“Poslanci,
                        hlasujte za své voliče, ne za sebe!,” <hi rend="italic">Svobodné slovo</hi>,
                        November 30, 1989, 1.</note> The joint session of the two Houses opened
                    after lunch in somewhat chaotic atmosphere. “Quite an unrest reigned in the
                    building of the Federal Assembly during the lunch break,” recalled MP Karel Löbl
                    later. “We did not have any information about the agenda of the joint session.
                    It seemed that an unusual number of guests were present. One could hear the echo
                    of the protesters chanting outside by the statue of St. Wenceslas. (...) When
                    the hitherto Chairman Indra stepped down, Slovak Communist Janík, lacking
                    relevant experience, took over chairing the session. Moreover, the atmosphere in
                    the Federal Assembly building echoed responses to the morning closed session of
                    the Communist faction where the Minister of Defence General Václavík was
                    allegedly in a warring mood when reporting on the readiness of the military to
                    intervene. Being non-Communist, I was not there. The non-Communist MPs were,
                    however, disturbed by that the Communist MPs had already available in advance
                    some printouts of the agenda of the afternoon session.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn12" n="11">Karel Löbl, <hi rend="italic">Naděje a omyly.
                            Vzpomínky na onu dobu</hi> [Hopes and Errors. Memoirs of An Era] (Praha:
                        Academia, 2012), 641-2.</note>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-23">At their joint session, the two Houses of the Federal Assembly quickly met all
                    fundamental demands by the Civic Forum, yet by means most advantageous for the
                    parliamentarians. Within a few hours the discredited veteran Alois Indra
                    disappeared as the leader of the Federal Assembly, as did the passages in the
                    Constitution about the leading role of the Communist Party of Czechoslovakia and
                    of Marxism-Leninism. A commission for the oversight over the investigation of
                    the intervention on 17 November was set up. All that happened broadcasted live
                    by the Czechoslovak Television and the Czechoslovak Radio.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-24">Yet the parliament also adopted its own resolution on the political situation.
                    Speakers from different political currents represented in the parliament agreed
                    in that the political decision-making finally got to the parliament from the
                    Party bureaus, as well as from the streets and squares. It belonged there and
                    was to remain there. The resolution adopted by both chambers of the Federal
                    Assembly as “the representative of the people of Czechoslovakia” subscribed to
                    all “progressive demands that lead to further development of socialist societal
                    relations, to the improvement of socialist democracy and living conditions of
                    the people.” It reminded that a number of reform laws have reached an advanced
                    stage of draft and were to be adopted within “a few days”, whilst MPs were
                    drafting additional ones. At the same time they explicitly mentioned the need to
                    adopt new regulations for the press, association, and the right to petition and
                    defence law. Furthermore, “at the same time we deem it of prime duty to promptly
                    complete the work on the new Constitution.” The parliament further emphasised
                    both steps that preceded the adoption of resolutions and meant satisfaction of
                    the main demands of those on strike. That meant setting up the parliamentary
                    commission and abolition of the Constitutional article about the leading role of
                    the Communist Party of Czechoslovakia. Constitutionally speaking – and
                    altogether in contrast with the vision of the revolutionary forces – the Federal
                    Assembly became the sovereign. Whilst its declaration did not explicitly
                    emphasise that and only hinted at it by praising the government for “the
                    dialogue with the representatives of civic initiatives”, by expressing support
                    to the planned changes in the government and also with a few formulations
                    attempting to define the government powers: “The Federal Assembly commits the
                    government of the Czechoslovak Socialist Republic to carry out dialogue whilst
                    being aware of responsibility for the socialist future of our nations and ethnic
                    groups. At the same time it commits it to systematically continue in following
                    the foreign policy line contained in its manifesto adopted in November 1989 at
                    the joint session of the Federal Assembly.” Finally, the Federal Assembly
                    stated: “We assure the people of our republic that we shall continue to do our
                    utmost to secure content life of the peoples in our socialist republic in line
                    with the principle: 'All power in the Czechoslovak Socialist Republic belongs to
                    the working people.'”<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn13" n="12">“K
                        současné vnitropolitické situaci. Prohlášení FS ČSSR“ [On the current
                        political situation. Declaration by the Federal Assembly of CSSR], <hi rend="italic">Svobodné slovo</hi>, November 30, 1989, 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-25">The parliamentary attempt to take over activity as an indispensable institution
                    was, in the hours that followed after the end of the televised broadcast,
                    commented upon far less than was the audience experience of it. The breakthrough
                    events were increasingly broadcast by the state television and radio. The first
                    televised live broadcasts from Wenceslas Square were aired on 22 November, a
                    week prior to the broadcast from the Federal Assembly. Ever longer broadcasts
                    and transmissions followed, all of which were less and less tailored to satisfy
                    the needs of the leadership of the Communist Party of Czechoslovakia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn14" n="13">The director general of
                        Czechoslovak Television Libor Bartla announced on the news on 23 November
                        that the television was directly run by the federal government; i.e. it was
                        the government instead of the hitherto unlawful direct control by the
                        apparatus of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of Czechoslovakia.
                        Mirka Spáčilová, “Televize v rukou vlády?” [Television in the Hands of the
                        Government?], <hi rend="italic">Mladá fronta</hi>, November 24, 1989, 5. Cf.
                        Milan Šmíd, “Česká média a jejich role v procesu politické změny roku 1989”
                        [Czech Media and Their Role in the Process of Political Change in 1989],
                        accessed May 15, 2013, <ref target="http://www.louc.cz/pril01/listopad.pdf">http://www.louc.cz/pril01/listopad.pdf</ref>.</note> The highlight of
                    the development came as soon as Saturday 25 November when the first federal
                    channel showed alternatively live broadcasts of thanksgiving mass for the
                    canonisation of Agnes of Bohemia with Cardinal František Tomášek serving at St.
                    Vitus Cathedral; from press conference on the extraordinary session of the
                    Central Committee of the Communist Party of Czechoslovakia; and from the biggest
                    of mass demonstrations in Prague, which was alternated with a concurrent
                    conference of the Prague branch of the Communist Party of Czechoslovakia held in
                    the Palace of Culture. In the evening after the extended main news, the
                    television repeated twice a special televised address by the new secretary
                    general of the Communist Party of Czechoslovakia Karel Urbánek. In between,
                    within an improvised 45-minute bloc of interviews “On Current Issues”, Václav
                    Havel spoke for the first time more continuously on cameras.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-26">The programme deserves recognition for the speed, quality and representative
                    nature of political debate on television and its broadcasts, that was achieved
                    as early as during the weekend of 25 and 26 November. Apart from the television,
                    other media, radio and daily press tried hard as well. It ought to be noted in
                    order to understand the preserved scope of – largely disenchanted – responses to
                    the first live broadcast from the Federal Assembly in the afternoon of Wednesday
                    29 November. From the perspective of television viewers, the session of the
                    legislative body was to be yet another part in the series on the revolution. The
                    core roles that otherwise were to be played by the parliament, had been already
                    well served by other fora, as had been also noted by MPs. Compared to the
                    televised platforms, some representatives had been missing altogether whilst
                    others were superfluous. The final impression was thus somewhat skewed and
                    incoherent with the ongoing debates in Prague and Bratislava.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-27">Those characteristics come out most clearly in the case of Anton Blažej who
                    became, for three weeks, the leading figure of the emancipation effort at the
                    Federal Assembly. Rector of the Technical University in Bratislava since 1969,
                    Blažej appeared in front of the cameras on 29 December as spokesman of the
                    Communists in the parliament. He gave a major political address about the
                    emergent situation. On behalf of the Communist majority he recognised and
                    welcomed the de facto completed régime change: “We, the Communist MPs, have to
                    primarily state in public that those were our own faults and mistakes, as well
                    as the mistakes of the Party, our erroneous interpretation of socialism, our
                    flawed understanding of the leading role of the Communist Party ...” He
                    explained to the viewers that the federal parliament was being transformed along
                    with the wider changes, and was gaining stronger position. He criticised the
                    previous policy, welcomed constitutional changes and talks with the Opposition,
                    and stated that the Communists would try to succeed in the coming elections:
                    “Communist MPs support most actively the democratic elections and the emergence
                    of the coalition government. If we wish to genuinely unite on the principles of
                    building modern, democratic, human, and industrially advanced socialist
                    Czechoslovakia, I think we have every capacity to find a common
                    ground.”According to Blažej, within the coming hours the Federal Assembly was to
                    meet all student demands it was able to satisfy, and the youth would then be
                    free to part and return to their studies.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn15" n="14">
                  <hi rend="italic">Společná česko-slovenská
                            digitální parlamentní knihovna</hi> [Common Digital Czecho-Slovak
                        Parliamentary Library], Federal Assembly 1986-1990, Joint Sessions of the
                        House of People and the House of Nations, Stenographic records, 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> session, 29. 11. 1989, accessed October 30,
                        2015, <ref target="http://www.psp.cz/eknih/1986fs/slsn/stenprot/016schuz/s016001.htm">http://www.psp.cz/eknih/1986fs/slsn/stenprot/016schuz/s016001.htm</ref>.</note>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-28">It would have been a fine address and perhaps even effective, had it not been
                    given by an unknown man in his sixties and without Miloš Jakeš and other
                    infamous faces of the old leadership seated to his left. They evidently
                    considered it their duty not to be missing in their seats at the presidium. Even
                    though they no longer had any influence on the content of Blažejʼs speech or on
                    anything else what was going on that day in the Federal Assembly, with their
                    mere visual presence they set the background to the effort of most speakers.
                    They sat without responding to Blažej or the others who were escalating the
                    general condemnation of the previous decades and the criticism of particulars.
                    Yet, according to the rules of procedure, as members of the presidium they were
                    entitled to priority intervention in the debate. From among the Czech
                    politicians representing real power, only the Minister of Defence General Milan
                    Václavík was to speak. He was invited directly by the deputy chairman of the
                    Czechoslovak Socialist Party Karel Löbl to tell the plenary whether there were
                    any grounds for concern about military intervention. The Minister, dressed in
                    uniform as was customary, indignantly rejected the concern.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn16" n="15">Karel Löbl, <hi rend="italic">Naděje a omyly.
                            Vzpomínky na onu dobu</hi> [Hopes and Errors. Memoirs of An Era] (Praha:
                        Academia, 2012), 641. Address by Löbl and Václavík: <hi rend="italic">Společná česko-slovenská digitální parlamentní knihovna</hi> [Common
                        Digital Czecho-Slovak Parliamentary Library], Federal Assembly 1986-1990,
                        Joint Sessions of the House of People and the House of Nations, Stenographic
                        records, 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> session, 29. 11. 1989, accessed
                        October 30, 2015, <ref target="http://www.psp.cz/eknih/1986fs/slsn/stenprot/016schuz/s016004.htm">http://www.psp.cz/eknih/1986fs/slsn/stenprot/016schuz/s016004.htm</ref>.</note>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-29">On behalf of the Czech part of the Communist Party of Czechoslovakia, two common
                    MPs spoke up: Jana Pekařová and Hana Návratová. It was their address that, in
                    the coming days, triggered major debate within the Czech context. One might
                    rightly assume that theirs were to be complementary speeches to that given by
                    Blažej. The Czech women-mothers spoke after a man, an academic with his rational
                    arguments. The division was common in similar arrangements and the two MPs
                    introduced themselves to the viewers and listeners accordingly. After the
                    conflict in the Communist faction at noon, it was unlikely to be an
                    authoritatively drafted script for the debate, but somewhat an intuitive
                    balancing and repetition of morning debates in front of the television cameras.
                    According to the testimony by Ms Návratová, MP, the Communist MPs no longer had
                    any firm leadership that day after the noon meeting of the faction, and their
                    presentations came out in an improvised manner.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-30">In case of the Czech female MPs on television the impression was not given that
                    much by their message, but their looks and presentation. In a concentrated form
                    the addresses contained vast amount of patterns and canonical formulations by
                    lower rank officials who reproduced the official propaganda with least
                    investment in thought or language, yet with high personal commitment. That
                    immediately triggered allergic reactions among a part of audience in spite of
                    the fact that the addresses by the two MPs were de facto quite forthcoming. Both
                    were plainly supportive of the Adamec cabinet against possible attacks by the
                    Party apparatus. Yet most audiences had been unable to decode this. Not only
                    were they accustomed to “switch off” when listening to official speeches. The
                    speeches suggesting emancipation of Communist MPs from the leadership by the
                    Party apparatus that were in part pursuing the pre-November institutional
                    attempts and intraparty struggles, were unintelligible to the uninitiated
                    audience. Within the context of the new discourse and situation they came across
                    as inappropriate and out of sync with the debate on the squares.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-31">The Adamec cabinet had an opportunity on the day to test its ability as the new
                    centre of power to mobilise the majority in both Houses. The test brought
                    relatively positive results: except for a handful of succinct commentaries, its
                    opponents from the Communist Party were silent in the plenary. Support to the
                    federal government and to the Prime Minister personally came out from most
                    speakers. For instance, Slovak independent MP Gejza Mede appealed: “We, the
                    parliament, have already shown that we are at the level that we can criticise
                    the government when appropriate and in the interest of the society, of our
                    voters. Yet has this parliament reached the level that it can help the
                    government when help is needed?”<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn17" n="16">
                  <hi rend="italic"> Společná česko-slovenská digitální parlamentní
                            knihovna</hi> [Common Digital Czecho-Slovak Parliamentary Library],
                        Federal Assembly 1986-1990, Joint Sessions of the House of People and the
                        House of Nations, Stenographic records, 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                        session, 29. 11. 1989, accessed October 30, 2015, <ref target="http://www.psp.cz/eknih/1986fs/slsn/stenprot/016schuz/s016002.htm">http://www.psp.cz/eknih/1986fs/slsn/stenprot/016schuz/s016002.htm</ref>.</note>
                    Prime Minister Adamec and his team followed the debate on television and were
                    responding to some statements by telephone. “Adamec followed my address on
                    television and immediately phoned my secretariat,” recalls Karel Löbl who has
                    known Adamec well for the nearly two decades of their service to the Czech
                    government. “His secretary Dáša only got hold of me the next day when the Prime
                    Minister thanked me for support and critical suggestions, and expressed belief
                    in positive developments. I acquired an impression from the debate that he was
                    not fighting as much the emerging Civic Forum, but some people in his own
                        Party.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn18" n="17">Löbl, <hi rend="italic">Naděje a omyly</hi>, 643.</note>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-32">The first debate evidenced fairly advanced split in the Czech and Slovak
                    politics, different role of debates in the two national communities at the
                    Federal Assembly, as well as the different position and perspective of the
                    Communist Parties in Czech and Slovak politics. Though the Communist faction
                    formally presented all Constitutional changes, a number of disparate groups were
                    within the brand, all standing on historical crossroads where they split into a
                    number of groups. Anton Blažej was given space in front of the cameras. As the
                    subsequent debate and events over the coming weeks and months showed, the rector
                    from Bratislava used, in an improvised manner, his perspective and rhetorical
                    skills. Yet de facto he did not represent any significant faction within the
                    disintegrating Party. The moments that were deciding their fate occurred
                    elsewhere, mainly in the central apparatuses in Prague and Bratislava and within
                    the executive.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-33">The other components of the parliament to draw attention by their activity during
                    the first televised debate were the smaller Czech and Slovak political parties.
                    The Czech Socialists, who emerged strong with a team of five well prepared
                    speakers during the debate over the first point on the agenda, were gradually
                    joined by others. Thus during the evening tuning of the parliamentary
                    declaration in the plenary, each particular matter was discussed by a Czech and
                    Slovak Communist MP along with MPs from the Czechoslovak Peopleʼs Party, the
                    Party of Slovak Renewal, and the Freedom Party. The common problem of all these
                    voices lay in the proportion between their quantity and representativeness.
                    Unlike the readers of this text, television viewers were not warned in advance
                    about the weight of individual organisations. Thus the debate might have led
                    them to a false conclusion about the political weight of individual
                    addresses.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-34">The assessment of the four legal political parties differed substantially in the
                    Czech and Slovak society, ranging from quite benign ideas about the prospective
                    role of these parties as the nuclei of pluralistic political life (what was the
                    evident long-term aim of, for instance, their newspapers), to bitter
                    condemnations of the operetta mini-parties led by police agents and frightened
                    corrupted officials whose activity created smokescreen for democratic
                    socialism.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-35">The particular status of these parties within the political system emerged as an
                    improvisation in an effort to retain, in the newly seized countries in the
                    Soviet bloc, some ornamental differences related to local customs.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn19" n="18">Non-Communist parties as part of
                        the state-socialist governments worked in East Germany (4), Czechoslovakia
                        (2+2), Poland (2) and Bulgaria (1), as well as in Vietnam (2 destroyed in
                        1988) and China (8). In Hungary, Romania, Yugoslavia and other countries of
                        the Soviet bloc non-Communist parties were altogether suppressed.</note> It
                    was similar to the Moscow decision to retain Presidency in Czechoslovakia, a
                    post that was functionally superfluous and inexistent in the Soviet model. The
                    Soviet political reforms at the end of 1980s led to democratisation of internal
                    life of the Communist Party. They did not offer any example for the leaders of
                    non-Communist parties in the Soviet satellites. Not that the leaders of those
                    parties did not know what could be expected of them. Visions of equality and
                    greater share in the government were a natural part of their existence.
                    Throughout the forty years all such efforts ended where they began. Other
                    organisations were not allowed to take part in the decision-making. They were
                    merely permitted to elaborate or provide for the adopted decision. It was the
                    Communist Party that had the patent to govern. The situation at the end of the
                    1980s seemed to a part of the lower rank officials of both larger Czech
                    satellite parties, the Peopleʼs and Socialist, as untenable. Pressure on the
                    leadership was rising and the activities in both parties were called a “reviving
                    current.”</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-36">The idea that they would significantly increase their influence in the future was
                    largely based on analogies with Czechoslovakia’s interwar politics. Similarly to
                    other areas, such as the economy or culture, there was a widespread belief in
                    the Czech society that the future development would return to the developmental
                    trends suppressed or eliminated by the Communist rule. Other future was hardly
                    conceivable.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-37">Hence the quite widespread belief that the Socialists and Populars represented,
                    albeit in a distorted form, traditional mass political currents identified with
                    by a substantial part of the population, and that some sort of restoration of
                    influence was about to come. Václav Havel thought along the same lines. In the
                    middle of the Summer of 1989, he grasped an accidental informal opportunity to
                    send, faced by a number of witnesses, a flirty message to the central secretary
                    of the Czechoslovak Socialist Party, Jan Škoda, addressing his former schoolmate
                    and fellow scout with an old nickname: “Dear Nosák [Nosey], I hope we meet soon
                    at some roundtable. Václav Havel.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn20" n="19">Gerová, <hi rend="italic">Vyhrabávačky, </hi>51.</note>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-38">The Czechoslovak Socialist party was the first to join the newly formed coalition
                    as soon as in the first hours of the demonstrations against the police
                    intervention on 17 November. When Škoda, directly invited by Havel, came to the
                    founding meeting of the Civic Forum, he was listed among the representatives of
                    the dissident groups and strike committees. In the tumultuous events of the
                    coming days the Czech Socialists were present and accepted everywhere, and,
                    given their mediation skills, they were also liked to be seen in the old
                    government institutions and in the headquarters of the Civic Forum. The chairman
                    of the party, Kučera, ceremoniously used his many posts in the political system
                    to involve the Civic Forum in the game and in the removal of the Communist Party
                    headquarters. The star day came during the parliamentary debate in front of the
                    television cameras on 29 November.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-39">Whatever was said above about the party of Czechoslovak Socialists also held true
                    with some variations for the Czechoslovak Peopleʼs Party. The first major
                    difference was the threefold membership base: there were about fifteen thousand
                    socialists and some forty thousand Populars.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn21" n="20">Löbl, <hi rend="italic">Naděje a omyly</hi>,
                        583.</note> The other distinction was such a cautious party leadership that,
                    apart from pacifying its own fellow party members, throughout 1989 it did not
                    exert any noteworthy activity. In order for the Peopleʼs Party to join the main
                    stream of political events, the leadership had to be replaced, which happened on
                    Monday 27 November.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn22" n="21">Břetislav
                        Daněk, <hi rend="italic">Československá strana lidová – její krize a obroda
                        </hi>[Czechoslovak Peopleʼ Party – Its Crisis and Restoration] (Praha:
                        Vyšehrad, 1990), 130.</note> With the new leadership, the Czechoslovak
                    Peopleʼs Party joined the Czech Socialists. Richard Sacher attended with Jan
                    Škoda as an ally leadership meetings about further action at the Civic Forum.
                    The new party chairman, Josef Bartončík, showed himself in live televised
                    broadcast as skilled speaker and strategist.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-40">None of that could be said of any of the Slovak parties. Their status was a
                    magnitude weaker, although some symmetry in the political system concealed the
                    reality. The deputy chairmen of the Federal Assembly included Josef Šimúth, the
                    chairman of the Party of Slovak Renewal (renamed Democratic Party from 1
                    December) as well as Ján Pampúch, deputy chairman of the Freedom Party. Yet each
                    had only four MPs in both chambers of the Federal Assembly, including their own
                    mandates. The nature of the groupings that were not exceeding fourteen hundred
                    members across Slovakia in the Autumn of 1989<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn23" n="22">Lubomír Lipták, <hi rend="italic">Politické
                            strany na Slovensku, 1860–1989</hi> [Political Parties in Slovakia
                        1860–1989] (Bratislava: Archa, 1992), 293-300.</note> and their sparse
                    representation in the executive institutions caused that, in Bratislava, they
                    did not play any visible role similar to that assumed by the Socialists and
                    Populars in the Czech Republic during the fall of the old régime. On 29 November
                    in front of the television cameras at the Federal Assembly they tried as best as
                    they could, yet their diligence added the deliberations blindingly grotesque
                    features. In the silence of the parliamentary constitutional majority, Josef
                    Šimúth managed, throughout the day, to deliver to the cameras three major
                    speeches. That made him the busiest speaker of the day.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn24" n="23">Bohuslav Kučera, the chairman of the Czech
                        Socialists, was the only one to be at the microphone more often than Šimút.
                        Yet the former only five times glossed the procedure or specified some
                        situations as one who attended the earlier talks between Adamec and Havel.
                        He managed to deliver two of his own speeches on that.</note> He touched
                    upon a number of substantial political and economic issues. As the first MP in
                    the plenary of the Federal Assembly he also managed to criticise the planned
                    Constitutional changes and to demand a better role for Slovakia.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-41">When exploring the response to the first televised broadcast from the federal
                    parliament, the sources unveil a few discrete scenes. Joining the winning
                    revolution, the media aired in devastating condemnations in the coming days.
                    “The live broadcast from the parliament beats the worst of expectations. I am in
                    no mood for this farce,” Václav Bartuška, one of the leaders of the student
                    committees in Prague, noted in his diary. He did not endure watching the
                    broadcast, at the end of which he was elected by the parliament for the
                    parliamentary commission for the oversight over the investigation of the police
                    intervention on 17 November. <hi rend="italic">Mladá fronta</hi>, the daily of
                    the Socialist Youth Union, reported with the same air of disdain. To describe
                    the broadcast, it used the most emotional statements by the most radical
                    segments of the society, the leaders of the student strike committees at the
                    Prague schools. After a week of reign over public spaces in the centre of the
                    capital city, they only had condemnation and ironic comments for the sticking
                    and dashed spectacle from the parliament: “There is no life to it. It is a
                    typical example of speaking in the supreme institutions. (...) The winter
                    hibernation that breaths from the parliament is truly striking.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn25" n="24">Zdeněk John and Petr Šabata,
                        “Studenti poslancům: Budíček” [Students to the Deputies: Wake Up Call], <hi rend="italic">Mladá fronta</hi>, November 30, 1989, 1-2.</note> The
                    comment by one of the revolutionaries applied here to the debate, its
                    proceedings and aesthetic. Yet it altogether missed the point that the live
                    broadcast was just showing the key postulates by the student rebellion being
                    met.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-42">Those most vocal voices, however, were by far not the only feedback to confront
                    the MPs after the television première of the live broadcast from the Federal
                    Assembly in the days to come. The abolition of the postulate of the rule of the
                    Communist Party transformed the holders of the federal mandates into a choir
                    without which no further step was possible, as all actors were quick to realise.
                    The federal executive was leaving and the preparations for the early elections,
                    which no one doubted anymore, would not do without a number of legislative
                    measures.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-43">When the Federal Assembly reconvened to address these issues two weeks later, it
                    offered an altogether different picture: most of the legislature came back to
                    life. The familiar faces of the old régime left their visible seats and joined
                    the MPs down below. The new spokesmen of the Communists led by Anton Blažej
                    revelled with confidence and latching activity. The altogether worst proposal
                    for the Civic Forum that came out from the televised session on 13 December 1989
                    was Blažejʼs suggestion that the new President was not to be elected by the
                    Federal Assembly but the people in a referendum. That dramatically lowered
                    Havelʼs chances and raise the hopes of the members of the then establishment
                    (such as Adamec) or the figures of 1968 (Alexander Dubček or someone else). From
                    the perspective of the revolutionaries, the very fact that the parliamentary
                    soil came to life as the key playground without the Civic Forum having control
                    over it, was bad enough news. The student siege of the building and pressure on
                    the MPs in their constituencies, both applied already for a number of weeks,
                    were instruments with limited effect.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-44">Following the resignation of the hitherto officials, Blažej was elected chairman
                    of the House of Nations on 12 December. He gave a programmatic address about the
                    new role of the parliament as an active and autonomous institution with its own
                    specialist base that “will not only be considering government proposals, but
                    will also be presenting its own initiatives,” whilst “starting to execute a
                    genuine control over the government” and becoming “the conscience of the work of
                    the government.” The Federal Assembly would thus earn “respect and gain
                    authority prior to the elections” which, as Blažej rightly predicted, would be
                    held in about six months. It was to be used in order “not to lose continuity and
                    to create real conditions for the functioning of the parliamentary system within
                    the context of legal democratic state.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn26" n="25">
                  <hi rend="italic">Společná česko-slovenská digitální parlamentní
                            knihovna</hi> [Common Digital Czecho-Slovak Parliamentary Library],
                        Federal Assembly 1986-1990, The House of Nations, Stenographic records, 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> session, 12. 12. 1989, accessed October 30,
                        2015, <ref target="http://www.psp.cz/eknih/1986fs/sn/stenprot/006schuz/s006001.htm">http://www.psp.cz/eknih/1986fs/sn/stenprot/006schuz/s006001.htm</ref>.</note>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-45">The next two weeks had shown that the development was to follow a different path.
                    The Civic Forum established itself as the new power hub. A part of the elderly
                    political establishment of the old régime was withdrawing to privacy and the
                    youths were offering themselves to serve the new régime. Its fundamental
                    institution became “the government of national unity” which was the name for the
                    reshuffled federal cabinet with multiple representation with former dissidents
                    complementing the ranks of relatively unknown bureaucrats.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn27" n="26">Government posts in the previous régime were
                        not held by the actual rulers who were based at the superior Party
                        apparatus; federal ministers were hardly present in the media, their names
                        and faces were hardly discernible even by political professionals. Václav
                        Havel, as can be seen in the recordings of meetings within the Civic Forum,
                        took a while to remember the name of Marián Čalfa, Adamecʼs successor in the
                        post of the federal Prime Minister. Čalfa was in the government since 1987
                        and was deputy to Adamec in the last year.</note> The government emerged
                    outside the parliament and without participation by MPs: none of the ministers
                    were members of the Federal Assembly. The government was named on 10 December by
                    President Gustav Husák who abdicated immediately afterwards to free his
                    Presidential post.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-46">Blažejʼs vision that the parliament would oversee the new executive proved to be
                    an illusion. In a few days everything was the other way round. It was Václav
                    Havel and his colleagues from the leadership at the Civic Forum to design the
                    progress of the key moments of the next sessions as a staged production. They
                    discussed in detail individual roles with relevant actors or sought willing
                    executors among MPs.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn28" n="27">Meeting of
                        representatives of the Civic Forum Coordination Centre and the Coordination
                        Committee of the Public Against Violence on co-optations of deputies to the
                        Federal Assembly and on the election of its chairman and presidium, 22
                        December 1989. ̶ Jiří Suk, <hi rend="italic">Občanské fórum,
                            listopad-prosinec 1989, 2. díl – dokumenty</hi> [Civic Forum,
                        November–December 1992, volume 2: Documents] (Praha-Brno: Doplněk, 1998),
                        261.</note> Except for those who retreated to seclusion and Blažej, all
                    officials within the Federal Assembly came forward. Already a favourite in the
                    Presidential elections to be held in a few days by the federal parliament
                    following the desires of the Civic Forum, Havel explained to his less initiated
                    colleagues: “Everything has been agreed with the people, they all know it and
                    are prepared for the arrangement (...) Apart from Mr Blažej. The arrangement has
                    not been agreed with him.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn29" n="28">Suk,
                            <hi rend="italic">Občanské forum</hi>, 262-3.</note>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-47">The concept of “national unity” in Czechoslovakia at the break of 1989 and 1990
                    went without the autonomously acting institutions. Blažej was removed from his
                    post on 28 December having led the Federal Assembly for three weeks. The new
                    leadership of the Communist Party that arose from the extraordinary Congress on
                    20 and 21 December 1989 agreed with the reshuffle in the leadership of the House
                    of Nations. Blažej was replaced by Jozef Stank, another Slovak with Communist
                    membership. Although, at the time of the election, he identified with the agenda
                    of his predecessor, in practical politics of the coming months he became a
                    willing executor of the will of the new President and of “the government of
                    national understanding.”</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-48">The parliament soon returned to the dependence on the executive. Blažejʼs failed
                    attempt for the more independent parliamentary politics was among many failures,
                    albeit the most visible and interesting. Overall statistics lay beneath: none of
                    the 350 holders of the federal mandates as of 17 November 1989 served a year
                    later in any significant post; only a handful were given further federal mandate
                    in the next elections but none have appeared in the governments. Such degree of
                    discontinuity was not a norm but an absolute exception in Czechoslovak political
                    institutions where, for example, Marián Čalfa, the former deputy of Adamec, was
                    the federal Prime Minister until the summer of 1992.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-49">The main reason is called co-optations: the replacement of a part of deputies. It
                    was created by agreement between the old and new political forces at a
                    roundtable and was part of conciliatory accord about the occupation of
                    governmental posts, the office of the President and early elections. The present
                    power apparatuses – the leadership of the Civic Forum and its Slovak
                    counterpart, the new leadership of the Communist Party of Czechoslovakia and the
                    four non-Communist political parties – agreed that, within the framework of the
                    politics of “national understanding”, they would bring to the Federal Assembly
                    MPs from the Civic Forum; at the same time, the individual parties could replace
                    their MPs at their own discretion.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn30" n="29">For details of the genesis and the process see the study by Petr
                        Roubal in this issue.</note> The new political élites thus gained the
                    missing political representation and, from Spring 1990, the role of the
                    parliament has indeed increased. Only it did not happen through the rising
                    authority of MPs, but by their replacement for political officials who gained
                    their de facto power before and elsewhere. They moved their political debates to
                    the parliament, having taken over parliamentary seats by the means of
                    revolution. The list of their names shows that they were renowned dissidents,
                    skilled leaders of local rebellions of November 1989 in the regional centres or
                    political talents of the Communist Party grabbing high posts in the rejuvenating
                    apparatus. Whilst it holds true that none of the three hundred and fifty holders
                    of the federal mandates as of 17 November 1989, none of the deputies became any
                    significant political or public figure in the coming years, the opposite holds
                    true for the one hundred and fifty co-opted deputies:<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-131-ftn31" n="30">For a list of co-opted MPs see Petr Roubal,
                            <hi rend="italic">Starý pes, nové kousky. Kooptace do Federálního
                            shromáždění a vytváření polistopadové politické kultury</hi> [Old Dog,
                        New Tricks: Co-optations in the Federal Assembly and the Development of the
                        post-November Political Culture] (Praha: Ústav pro soudobé dějiny Akademie
                        věd České republiky, 2013), 94-102.</note> among them were two future
                    Presidents, a number of Ministers, Constitutional Judges as well as a range of
                    other leading figures in the coming two decades of Czechoslovakia and, after
                    1992, in the Czech Republic and the Slovak Republic.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="bibliogr" xml:id="ojs-131-bibliogr">
            <head xml:id="ojs.131-head-7">Sources and references</head>
            <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-131-bibliogr-sub01">
               <head xml:id="ojs.131-head-8">Literature</head>
               <listBibl xml:id="ojs.131-listBibl-1">
                  <bibl>
                     <hi rend="italic">Československo dnes: Zastupitelské sbory, vlády,
                                diplomatické styky, školství, zdravotnictví, ekonomika, kraje
                                ČSSR</hi> [Czechoslovakia Today: Representative Assemblies,
                            Government, Diplomatic Relations, Schools, Healthcare, Economics, and
                            Regions in CSSR]. Praha: Pressfoto, 1987.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Daněk, Břetislav. <hi rend="italic">Československá strana lidová –
                                její krize a obroda</hi> [Czechoslovak Peopleʼ Party – Its Crisis
                            and Restoration]. Praha: Vyšehrad, 1990. </bibl>
                  <bibl>Gerová, Irena. <hi rend="italic">Vyhrabávačky: Deníkové zápisy a
                                rozhovory z let 1988 a 1989</hi> [Digs: Diary Notes and Interviews
                            from 1888 and 1989]. Praha, Litomyšl: Paseka, 2009. </bibl>
                  <bibl>Gorbačov, Michail Sergejevič. <hi rend="italic">Přestavba a nové
                                myšlení pro naši zemi a pro celý svět</hi> [Perestroika and New
                            Thinking for Our Country and the Whole World]. Praha: Svoboda,
                            1987.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Hájek, Miloš. <hi rend="italic">Paměť české levice</hi> [The Memory of
                            the Czech Left]. Praha: Ústav pro soudobé dějiny AV ČR, 2011.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Krapfl, James. <hi rend="italic">Revolution with a Human Face:
                                Politics, Culture, and Community in Czechoslovakia, 1989-1992.</hi>
                            Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 2013.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Lipták, Lubomír.<hi rend="italic"> Politické strany na Slovensku,
                                1860–1989</hi> [Political Parties in Slovakia 1860–1989].
                            Bratislava: Archa, 1992.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Löbl Karel, <hi rend="italic">Naděje a omyly. Vzpomínky na onu
                                dobu</hi> [Hopes and Errors. Memoirs of An Era]. Praha: Academia,
                            2012.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi rend="italic">Poslední hurá. Stenografický záznam z mimořádných
                                zasedání ÚV KSČ 24. a 26. listopadu 1989</hi> [The Final Hooray:
                            Stenographic Record from Extraordinary Sessions of the Central Committee
                            of the Communist Party of Czechoslovakia on 24 and 26 November 1989].
                            Praha: Agentura Cesty, 1992. </bibl>
                  <bibl>Roubal, Petr. <hi rend="italic">Starý pes, nové kousky. Kooptace do
                                Federálního shromáždění a vytváření polistopadové politické
                                kultury</hi> [Old Dog, New Tricks: Co-optations in the Federal
                            Assembly and the Development of the post-November Political Culture].
                            Praha: Ústav pro soudobé dějiny Akademie věd České republiky,
                            2013.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Sedlák, Jaromír.<hi rend="italic"> Muž nad stolem, aneb Byl jsem
                                Štrougalovým poradcem</hi> [A Man Over The Table or I Was Štrougalʼs
                            Adviser]. Praha: BVD, 2010.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Šmíd, Milan. “Česká média a jejich role v procesu politické změny roku
                            1989” [Czech Media and Their Role in the Process of Political Change in
                            1989]. Accessed May 15, 2013, <ref target="http://www.louc.cz/pril01/listopad.pdf">http://www.louc.cz/pril01/listopad.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi rend="italic">Společná česko-slovenská digitální parlamentní
                                knihovna</hi> [Common Digital Czecho-Slovak Parliamentary Library],
                            Federal Assembly 1986-1990. Accessed October 30, 2015. <ref target="http://www.psp.cz/eknih/1986fs/index.htm">http://www.psp.cz/eknih/1986fs/index.htm</ref>.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Suk, Jiří. <hi rend="italic">Labyrintem revoluce. Aktéři, zápletky a
                                křižovatky jedné politické krize (od listopadu 1989 do června
                                1990)</hi> [Through the Labyrinth of the Revolution. Actors, Plots
                            and Crossroads of A Political Crisis (from November 1989 to June 1990)].
                            Praha: Prostor, 2003.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Suk, Jiří. <hi rend="italic">Občanské fórum, listopad-prosinec 1989,
                                2. díl – dokumenty</hi> [Civic Forum, November–December 1992, volume
                            2: Documents]. Praha, Brno: Doplněk, 1998. </bibl>
                  <bibl>Šulc, Zdislav. <hi rend="italic">Z jeviště i zákulisí české politiky a
                                ekonomiky</hi> [From the Stage and Backstage of Czech Politics and
                            Economics]. Brno: Doplněk, 2011.</bibl>
               </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-131-bibliogr-sub02">
               <head xml:id="ojs.131-head-9">Newspaper sources</head>
               <listBibl xml:id="ojs.131-listBibl-2">
                  <bibl>John, Zdeněk and Petr Šabata. “Studenti poslancům: Budíček” [Students
                            to the Deputies: Wake Up Call]. <hi rend="italic">Mladá fronta</hi>,
                            November 30, 1989, 1-2.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Spáčilová, Mirka. “Televize v rukou vlády?” [Television in the Hands
                            of the Government?]. <hi rend="italic">Mladá fronta</hi>, November 24,
                            1989, 5. </bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi rend="italic">Svobodné slovo.</hi> “K současné vnitropolitické
                            situaci. Prohlášení FS ČSSR“ [On the current political situation.
                            Declaration by the Federal Assembly of CSSR]. November 30, 1989,
                            3.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi rend="italic">Svobodné slovo</hi>. “Poslanci, hlasujte za své
                            voliče, ne za sebe!,” November 30, 1989, 1.</bibl>
               </listBibl>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl" xml:id="ojs-131-summary">
            <head xml:id="ojs.131-head-10">Povzetek</head>
            <head rend="subtitle" xml:id="ojs.131-head-11">V parlamentu naj bi potekale razprave, vendar se je to
                    izkazalo za nemogoče: Zvezni parlament in žametna revolucija na Češkoslovaškem
                    leta 1989</head>
            <docAuthor xml:id="ojs.131-docAuthor-3">Tomáš Zahradníček</docAuthor>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-50">Študija je osredotočena na vlogo češkoslovaškega zveznega parlamenta v političnem
                    prevratu leta 1989. Na podlagi institucionalne perspektive predstavlja novo
                    analizo prelomnih tednov. Z vidika parlamenta so bile spremembe nenavadno hitre.
                    V nekaj tednih od padca berlinskega zidu do konca leta 1989 je državi uspelo
                    zamenjati izvršilno oblast (zlasti predsedstvo – Václav Havel je nadomestil
                    Gustáva Husáka), pri čemer parlament ni odigral pomembne vloge.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-51">Predhodna vlada in vodje Državljanskega foruma so sklenili dogovor, ki je
                    vključeval tudi naloge, ki bi jih moral izpolnjevati parlament, tako da je bila
                    odločitev formalno ustrezna. Ključna pogajanja se sploh niso približala
                    parlamentarnemu odru.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-52">Medtem so si številni tedanji poslanci, izvoljeni leta 1986, pa tudi parlament
                    kot institucija, razlagali zlom predhodne strukture moči kot priložnost za
                    neodvisnost, zato so se poskušali vključiti v pogajanja, vendar brez uspeha.
                    Slovaški poslanec Anton Blažej, ki se je javno zavzemal, da bi neodvisni
                    parlament postal »vest vlade«, je na čelu zveznega parlamenta preživel samo tri
                    tedne, preden ga je odslovila nova izvršilna oblast z novoizvoljenim
                    predsednikom Havlom.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs.131-p-53">Istočasno so v parlament začeli vstopati predstavniki nove oblasti in zasedli
                    prazne sedeže poslancev, ki so odstopili ali bili razrešeni. Po skoraj dveh
                    mesecih improviziranja se je parlament spet vključil v politiko. To se ni
                    zgodilo zaradi njegove neodvisnosti ali splošnih volitev. Formalnopraven prihod
                    predstavnikov nove oblasti na vodilne položaje je bil resnično revolucionarno
                    dejanje. Institucionalna perspektiva nam omogoča, da precej jasno prepoznamo
                    tovrstno naravo te politične spremembe.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
