<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en" xml:id="ojs-132">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Complex Parliaments in Transition: Central European Federations Facing Regime Change</title>
            <title level="a">International Workshop, Ljubljana, 16 October 2015</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Jurij</forename>
                  <surname>Hadalin</surname>
               </name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2015-11-24</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
               <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
               </address>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/132</pubPlace>
            <date>2015</date>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="PID">sistory.36121</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
            <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
            <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
            <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
            <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
            <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change>
               <date>2015-12-03</date>
               <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
               <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
            </change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="article" n="Reviews and Reports">
      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>Complex Parliaments in Transition: Central European Federations Facing Regime Change</titlePart>
               <titlePart>International Workshop, Ljubljana, 16 October 2015</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <docAuthor>Jurij Hadalin</docAuthor>
         </titlePage>
         <divGen type="search" xml:id="ojs-132-search">
            <head>Search</head>
         </divGen>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="chapter" xml:id="ojs-132-article">
            <head xml:id="ojs-132-head-1">Complex Parliaments in Transition: Central European Federations Facing Regime Change</head>
            <head rend="subtitle" xml:id="ojs-132-head-2">International Workshop, Ljubljana, 16 October 2015</head>
            <docAuthor xml:id="ojs-132-docAuthor-2">Jurij Hadalin</docAuthor>
            <p xml:id="ojs-132-p-6">The year 1990 represented a turning point in many aspects. Also in the Eastern
                    European Assemblies, which carried out their role in the transition processes in
                    different manners. Federations were falling apart, new states were forming,
                    efficient ways of carrying out the transition from the socialist to the
                    democratic system were being sought, and the majority of the population found
                    itself in an unknown and treacherous terrain... Even the former dissidents and
                    new leaders. Meanwhile, compliance with the law and democratic decision‑making
                    in the Parliaments, whatever they were like, was a vital part of the process
                    that ensured the legitimacy of the transition. As we were able to hear at the
                    conference, Vaclav Havel faced such an obstacle as well, and according to the
                    opinion at the time he carried out one of the most elegant political
                    transitions. On the other hand, fortunately the Romanian scenario was unique.
                    Nevertheless, the unexpected course of events in the Soviet Union contributed to
                    these events as well, besides a large number of other factors. Ephraim Kishon
                    described this moment in his own way: <hi rend="italic">"Frankly, such a
                        development of events was not certain. It was a true miracle. I am only
                        trying to describe how such an impossible revolution was possible at all.
                        And I am not doing it as one of those experts in the Soviet Union who
                        disgraced themselves, but because I was a witness to the events. So, those
                        who expect any new prophecies from me should stay away from this book. Not
                        even the Delphic oracle could predict with any certainty whether Gorbachev
                        will go down in history as a messiah the saviour or a confused wizard's
                        apprentice. Even now everybody is saying that during the time of Brezhnev
                        one had to stand in line for carrots a quarter of an hour less... As far as
                        I am concerned, Mikhail Gorbachev is nevertheless an impressive person,
                        whether the Russian market runs out of carrots completely or not. His
                        revolution that shook the world is a special kind of a one‑man show, which
                        he has carried out himself. Moses had a brother, Aaron; Marx had a friend,
                        Engels; and Gorbachev has nothing but worries. Still, at this moment I am as
                        confused as anyone else. Was it all just a nightmare, a cheap horror movie?
                        Were all those generals, faceless fossils with countless shiny medals, truly
                        the masters of the universe? Did the bloodthirsty Count Dracula truly exist
                        in Romania? Was that average insurance agent Erich Honecker truly a tyrant
                        whom everyone was afraid of? Was all of this just a bad joke? Therefore my
                        book will only describe the events that already belong to history, and which
                        can no longer be changed by anyone. Except for the Soviet historians, of
                        course."</hi>
               <note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-132-ftn1" n="1">Ephraim Kishon<hi rend="italic">, Pomozi sirotu na svoju sramotu</hi>. (Zagreb: Znanje,
                        1992), 7-8.</note> Thus the question of transition was dealt with by a
                    Hungarian emigrant, as he looked into the past.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs-132-p-7">However, at that moment it was far more important to look into the future. The
                    participants of the workshop in Ljubljana focused on the question of the role of
                    Assemblies in the former socialist federal countries. As it was stated in the
                    presentation of the workshop, the federal states, based on the construction of
                    the socialist relations, started to lose their primary meaning. As we could see
                    in the cases of Yugoslavia and Czechoslovakia, the deputies/delegates in the
                    federal structures started focusing on their national issues, and instead of the
                    community the individual national units gradually became more important, which
                    ultimately resulted in the dissolution of both federations. In the Czechoslovak
                    case the Federal Assembly, which had not played a very important political role
                    before, nevertheless managed to complete the transition from the socialist
                    system to a democratic regime before its term came to an end, while the Yugoslav
                    Federal Assembly was quite an unimportant factor in this process and the
                    Republican Assemblies played a tremendous role. The presentation of the East
                    German example represented an interesting addition to the majority of the
                    contributions that focused on the aforementioned countries. As it happened,
                    after the first free elections the East German Volkskammer merely paved the way
                    towards the legal and formal unification with West Germany. This also involved a
                    renewed federalisation, as East Germany had no longer been divided into states
                    since the late 1950s. However, the fact that the parliamentary transition in
                    Germany was thus not yet concluded was pointed out by the analysis of the
                    changed circumstances, in which the today's German Federal State Parliaments can
                    take an active part in the European Parliament without answering to the federal
                    authorities.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs-132-p-8">The consultation took place at the Institute of Contemporary History in
                    Ljubljana, where Jure Gašparič and the Director of the Institute Damijan Guštin
                    greeted the participants in the name of the Slovenian hosts.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs-132-p-9">Accompanied by the photos from the former Czechoslovak Parliament, the
                    introductory paper was presented by Dr. Adéla Gjuričovà, who has ample
                    experience of her own with this Czech parliament. She presented the role of the
                    Federal Parliament, which had, until the Velvet Revolution, been a less
                    important institution from the political viewpoint, and where decisions were
                    merely adopted and not created all that often. During the turmoil of the Velvet
                    Revolution this Parliament continued working and remained unresponsive to the
                    external influences, even though it was clearly evident from its immediate
                    surroundings that the environment had changed radically. The revolutionary
                    leadership did not hold the reins of the Parliament, but it quickly established
                    that without the Parliament it would not be possible to implement the changes
                    legally. Namely, the problems implied by the structure of the Parliament – which
                    did not guarantee that any decisions adopted at various round tables in those
                    days would also be processed or adopted – dictated changes in the structure of
                    the delegates. Tomaš Zahradniček explained more about the solution, which
                    represented a compromise between the departing old authorities and the
                    revolutionary movement, and thus provided the missing details. As it happened,
                    elections for the Federal Assembly were not deemed as a sufficiently swift and
                    efficient solution, and therefore approximately one third of new delegates were
                    co‑opted into the Assembly. Despite the legality of this procedure, which
                    enabled an active cooperation between the executive and legislative authorities,
                    the move started undermining the legitimacy of the Assembly itself, as its
                    co‑opted members started undermining the Assembly's previous political
                    consistency as well as its regional proportionality. The majority of the new
                    members came from large cities, and the essential differences in perception
                    between the Czech and Slovak parts of the state were evident as well. Censorship
                    and the consequent political turmoil were significantly less prominent in
                    Slovakia, and soon after the introduction of the most important changes the
                    Assembly deputies started acting more in line with the expectations of the
                    individual parts of the state. Then Petr Roubal presented an in‑depth analysis
                    of the subsequent parliamentary discord and the origins of the problems of
                    Czechoslovak federalism, which was the only political remainder of the Prague
                    Spring (perhaps also because of the Slovak role in its conclusion; author's
                    comment). Thus Roubal supplemented the introductory lecture with regard to the
                    final but consenting breakup after the consolidation of the two national
                    leaders, Vaclav Havel and Vladimir Mečiar. At this point we should also
                    underline the discussion about how easily this breakup was actually accepted by
                    the Czech public and politics, which saw the West through rose‑tinted glasses at
                    the time but disregarded the East.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs-132-p-10">From the today's perception of the established democratic parliamentary
                    practices, the East German example of transitional parliament is actually
                    closest to us. The first and last free elections in the German Democratic
                    Republic took place in May 1990, and the Parliament operated successfully until
                    2 October of the same year, that is, until the day before the German
                    reunification. Its mandate was clear, despite the organisationally unchanged
                    structure: to pave the way for the reunification. Unlike other transitional
                    states, where the political parties had yet to be established, the last East
                    German Parliament enjoyed a strong support in the traditional political parties
                    from the Federal Republic of Germany. If we disregard the SED (Sozialistiche
                    Einheitspartei Deutschland), the former East German party that came in third,
                    most of the parties worth mentioning were actually copies of the existing West
                    German parties. Bettina Tuffers presented the influence of the Bonn parties on
                    the political developments in the Berlin Parliament, as its delegates also
                    followed the events from the balcony. The inexperienced new Members of
                    Parliament had yet to learn about the significance of parliamentary procedures
                    and basics of political appearances from the veteran West German politicians.
                    Further elaboration was provided by Aron Buzogany, who focused on the somewhat
                    more recent issues. With the example of the German Federal State Parliaments he
                    demonstrated that these independent bodies have – apart from the Upper Chambers
                    of the National Parliaments – the possibility of successfully influencing the
                    adoption or rejection of legislation in the European Parliament. While this
                    calls for enormous organisational efforts, it has born results in at least two
                    cases. Therefore the weakened national and regional parliaments have retained or
                    enhanced their significance in the process of the "European federalisation".</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs-132-p-11">The comparisons between the various constitutional and legal systems and the role
                    of parliamentary institutions in these systems usually turn out to be very
                    significant for the presentation of the last stage of the Yugoslav system, the
                    so‑called "mature self‑management". The convoluted language that accompanied
                    this system can also be seen in the foreword to the collected works of the
                    Yugoslav President of the Government Milka Planinc: <hi rend="italic">"The
                        current stage of the Yugoslav socialist revolution involves the struggle for
                        the development of socialist self‑management as an integral social
                        relationship and principle of the construction of the society, struggle for
                        the construction of the associated labour society or the rule of the working
                        class with regard to income, social reproduction and social decision‑making.
                        The everyday constancy of this struggle results in the totality of the
                        revolutionary practices and attests to human creativity on the path towards
                        the further liberation of work, the working class and the masses, led by the
                        League of Communists of Yugoslavia as the leading ideological‑political
                        force."</hi>
               <note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-132-ftn2" n="2">Milka Planinc, <hi rend="italic">Savez komunista Jugoslavije u socialističkom
                            samoupravljanju</hi> (Zagreb: Centar za kulturnu djelatnost, 1982),
                        2.</note>This totality and creativity resulted in the fact that formally
                    almost everyone could take part in the political decision‑making at the various
                    levels, which Jure Gašparič demonstrated schematically in his introduction to
                    the explanation of the transition in the Slovenian Assembly. Gašparič brought
                    the attention to the fact that in this process the Federal Assembly became
                    increasingly irrelevant, while the fundamental political discussions started
                    coming to the forefront in the Slovenian Socialist Assembly. The Socialist
                    Assembly and the subsequent first democratically‑elected Assembly, still based
                    on the old organisational principles, were seen as exceedingly positive by the
                    Slovenian public. This is also apparent from the results of the public opinion
                    polls, which was one of Slovenian peculiarities, as this research has gone on
                    continuously since as early as 1967. However, public opinion polls can
                    occasionally be wrong, especially when it comes to election results. On the
                    basis of public opinion patterns and election results, Simona Kustec Lipicer
                    showed the trends of the changes in the Slovenian political space, where the
                    already established parties keep losing their positions, while the newly‑formed
                    parties (sometimes actually established during the official election campaign)
                    keep making their way into the parliamentary life with each new elections and
                    have enjoyed very large percentages for the past few years. The lecturer is also
                    the president of a parliamentary group of one of these parties. Therefore she
                    could bring together her practical and research experience, while the workshop
                    participants were able to observe the everyday parliamentary life in the
                    Slovenian Parliament.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs-132-p-12">The constructive debates following each individual contribution and the provided
                    comparative dimension set excellent foundations for the future research
                    challenges. These results will not only remain limited to the participants, as
                    they are freely accessible to anyone: the workshop was recorded, and the
                    recordings are published at the History of Slovenia – SIstory portal (<ref target="http://www.sistory.si">www.sistory.si</ref>).</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
