<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ojs-118">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">In Search of Compromise</title>
            <title level="a">Janez Cvirn: Dunajski državni zbor in Slovenci (1848-1918) [Vienna
                    National Assembly and Slovenians (1848-1918)]. Zgodovinsko društvo Celje,
                    Znanstvena založba Filozofske fakultete Ljubljana. Celje, Ljubljana 2015,
                    280 pages</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Filip</forename>
                  <surname>Čuček</surname>
               </name>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2015-11-04</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
               <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
               </address>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/118</pubPlace>
            <date>2015</date>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="PID">sistory.36123</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
            <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
            <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
            <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
            <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
            <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change>
               <date>2015-11-04</date>
               <name>Andrej Pančur</name>
               <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
            </change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="article" n="Reviews and Reports">
      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>In Search of Compromise</titlePart>
               <titlePart>Janez Cvirn: Dunajski državni zbor in Slovenci (1848-1918) [Vienna
                        National Assembly and Slovenians (1848-1918)]. Zgodovinsko društvo Celje,
                        Znanstvena založba Filozofske fakultete Ljubljana. Celje, Ljubljana 2015,
                        280 pages</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <docAuthor>Filip Čuček</docAuthor>
         </titlePage>
         <divGen type="search" xml:id="ojs-118-search">
            <head>Search</head>
         </divGen>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="chapter" xml:id="ojs-118-article">
            <head xml:id="ojs-118-head-1">In Search of Compromise</head>
            <head rend="subtitle" xml:id="ojs-118-head-2">Janez Cvirn: Dunajski državni zbor in Slovenci (1848-1918) [Vienna National
                    Assembly and Slovenians (1848-1918)]. Zgodovinsko društvo Celje, Znanstvena
                    založba Filozofske fakultete Ljubljana. Celje, Ljubljana 2015, 280 pages</head>
            <docAuthor xml:id="ojs-118-docAuthor-2">Filip Čuček</docAuthor>
            <p xml:id="ojs-118-p-6">Based on several years of research into the issue of parliamentarism in the
                    Austrian Monarchy, the late Prof. Dr. Janez Cvirn (1960–2013) published a
                    university textbook entitled Razvoj ustavnosti in parlamentarizma v habsburški
                    monarhiji (dunajski državni zbor in Slovenci 1848 – 1918) [Development of
                    Constitutionality and Parliamentarism in the Habsburg Monarchy: Vienna National
                    Assembly and Slovenians (1848-1918)]. This textbook was far more than what its
                    name suggested and indicated that the author was about to realise even more
                    ambitious plans regarding this subject. Those of us who were close to him knew
                    that he was also planning a book edition, i.e. a thorough and comprehensive
                    history of Austrian parliamentarism (and the Slovenian experience within its
                    context). However, he was not able to realise this project (the book was
                    supposed to be published by another publisher a few years ago but,
                    unfortunately, was not). It was finally co-published posthumously by the
                    Historical Society of Celje and the Faculty of Arts of Ljubljana (also in
                    cooperation with the Institute of Contemporary History – the book was edited by
                    Dr. Jure Gašparič). Cvirn’s book is an essential source for studying the
                    political history of the second half of the 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                    century and, as such, finally available in Slovenian libraries and bookstores as
                    the last, fifteenth book of the collection Zgodovini.ce, based on Cvirn’s idea
                    (with this book the Celje book collection is therefore completed). Regrettably,
                    Cvirn will not be able to read, evaluate or in any way assess this book, but I
                    am convinced that he would certainly approve of it, as it is.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs-118-p-7">Cvirn has profoundly marked Slovenian historiography with his work and is
                    considered the leading Slovenian expert in the history of the 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century. In his final work, which is a result of
                    systematic research, he presented the crucial turning points in the
                    constitutional history of Austria – from the first steps toward
                    constitutionalism in 1848 until the end of the Monarchy in 1918. Apart from
                    that, the book is an exhaustive political-historical overview, as the author
                    analysed the relationships between the governments and the parliament and thus
                    described the role of the Austrian National Assembly in the political life of
                    the state. The book also contains a detailed presentation of the activities of
                    the Slovenian deputies (who had always been forced to resort to opportunistic
                    politics because of their limited numbers) in the National Assembly between 1848
                    and 1918, which is particularly valuable.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs-118-p-8">Let us take a quick glance at the book. The early constitutionalism, established
                    especially by certain (south) German states in the pre-March period, was very
                    slow to penetrate the conservative Austria on the eve of the March revolution.
                    Only the revolution encouraged the Court to rely on the new societal model.
                    However, the April (Pillersdorf) Constitution which, as the author convincingly
                    demonstrates, followed constitutionalism only as far as to clearly enforce the
                    separation of powers (judicial, executive and legislative), still conferred many
                    powers on the emperor. The author then presents the initiative of the Provincial
                    (Estate) Assemblies which joined the reform movement. The National Assembly
                    elections in June 1848, establishing the first Austrian Parliament, were even
                    more important. Cvirn analyses the elections in detail and notes, among other
                    things, that the national component is indisputably a result of the political
                    development of the later period.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs-118-p-9">With the imposed constitution the young Emperor Franz Joseph demonstrated that
                    concessions to the revolution had come to an end. The author skilfully guides us
                    through the developments which led to the neo-absolutist regime through the New
                    Year’s Eve Patents, thus ending the early constitutional period in Austria. A
                    ten-year period of resumed "silence", personified by the Minister of the
                    Interior Bach, was followed by the restoration of the constitutional life in
                    1860/61, when the period of oppression and censorship had, in a moral and
                    material sense, come to an end. However, the creator of the new political course
                    Anton Schmerling added a "German character" to the Austrian parliamentarism with
                    his electoral structure, which also favoured the wealthier strata on the basis
                    of a tax and intelligence census. The author thus offers a sound and coherent
                    description of the development of political thought until the introduction of
                    dualism in 1867, when Cisleithania was forced to re-establish the state-legal
                    foundations of the Austrian half of the Monarchy and provide for the further
                    (political) modernisation of the state with the December Constitution. The
                    author then meticulously highlights individual issues concerning the
                    directly-elected Vienna National Assembly (from 1873 on) and presents them
                    through a perspective related to the functioning of governments and each
                    convening of the Parliament. Cvirn does not conclude his work before World War
                    I, as it would be expected, but follows the Austrian parliamentary life until
                    the fall of the Monarchy.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs-118-p-10">One of the basic findings of Cvirn’s book is that the dissolution of the Monarchy
                    was not a consequence of a belated and insufficient political democratisation.
                    As it was, the liberal December Constitution of 1867 transformed Cisleithania
                    into a relatively modern constitutional monarchy, which, as far as democracy was
                    concerned, did not exhibit a significant lag in comparison with most European
                    countries. With a set of electoral reforms the Monarchy advanced towards
                    enforcing the universal manhood suffrage and also achieved it in 1907. The
                    reasons for the Monarchy's tragic end lied primarily in the fatal lack of basic
                    consensus on the matter of how the state should be organised. The latter was
                    becoming increasingly evident in the Austrian parliamentary practice. Namely,
                    since the end of the 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century the parliament had
                    become the place of severe national conflicts with no room for an agreement.</p>
            <p xml:id="ojs-118-p-11">The present book is Cvirn’s final and most comprehensive work on the history of
                    parliamentarism. The editor manly followed Cvirn's university textbook and
                    strived to refrain from interfering with the text as much as possible. The
                    author concludes the book with World War I. However, the editor completed
                    Cvirn’s structure of the book by ending it with a few additional chapters
                    written by the author (on the electoral reforms of the National Assembly,
                    women’s suffrage, rules of procedure, language of proceedings, immunity of
                    deputies, and deputies’ wages), which complement and clarify the primary text as
                    well as underline the magnitude of the history of parliamentarism.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
