<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en" xml:id="ojs-133">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a">Complex Parliaments in Transition</title>
                <title level="a">Central European Federations Facing Regime Change</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Jure</forename>
                        <surname>Gašparič</surname>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Adéla</forename>
                        <surname>Gjuričová</surname>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2015-12-08</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/133</pubPlace>
                <date>2015</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="PID">sistory.36114</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2015-12-08</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en" type="article" n="Editorial">
        <front>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart>Complex Parliaments in Transition</titlePart>
                    <titlePart>Central European Federations Facing Regime Change</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <docAuthor>Jure Gašparič</docAuthor>
                <docAuthor>Adéla Gjuričová</docAuthor>
            </titlePage>
            <divGen type="search" xml:id="ojs133-search">
                <head>Search</head>
            </divGen>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="chapter" xml:id="ojs133-article">
                <head xml:id="ojs133-head1">Complex Parliaments in Transition</head>
                <head xml:id="ojs133-head2" rend="subtitle">Central European Federations Facing Regime Change</head>
                <docAuthor>Jure Gašparič</docAuthor>
                <docAuthor>Adéla Gjuričová</docAuthor>
                <p xml:id="ojs133-p-1">"What is a socialist parliament?" This is a question that
                    many political historians may see as redundant or pointless. Parliaments in the
                    one-party socialist states in the Eastern Europe after World War II are
                    frequently shrugged off with an effortless explanation that they were merely
                    façades of the socialist regimes. Although this cannot be completely refuted,
                    questions nevertheless arise in the modern political historiography, calling for
                    answers stemming from the "neo-institutionalist" paradigm. What were the
                    socialist parliaments like? How were they organised? What was their outward
                    appearance, who were their members, how did they operate, what sorts of
                    mechanisms guided the socialist parliamentarism, and so on? At least a few
                    members of the European Information and Research Network on Parliamentary
                    History (EuParl.net), which brings together research organisations focusing on
                    the history of parliamentarism, deal with this phenomenon systematically. These
                    efforts resulted in the idea to organise a workshop where these researchers
                    could exchange their outlooks on socialist parliaments in their terminal stages,
                    when they were already undergoing a transformation into modern European
                    parliaments. </p>
                <p xml:id="ojs133-p-2">The workshop was organised by the Institute of Contemporary
                    History in Ljubljana in cooperation with the Czech Institute for Contemporary
                    History (Ústav pro soudobé dějiny AV ČR) from Prague and the Commission for the
                    History of Parliamentarianism and Political Parties (Kommission für Geschichte
                    des Parlamentarismus und der politischen Parteien) from Berlin. It took place on
                    16 October 2015 in Ljubljana at the Institute of Contemporary History, in the
                    building where in the past – until 1959 – the Socialist Parliament of the
                    Republic of Slovenia had held its sessions.</p>
                <p xml:id="ojs133-p-3">The main idea and purpose of the gathering was to illustrate
                    the transformation of the parliaments and parliamentary systems in the late
                    1980s and early 1990s. We did not want to define any detailed programme points –
                    deliberately, because we wanted the academic space for our workshop to remain as
                    open as possible.</p>
                <p xml:id="ojs133-p-4">In the introduction only a few common points were defined:
                    The collapse of the socialist regimes in 1989-1990 set off multifaceted
                    processes of democratic reforms as well as social and economic transformations.
                    In some of the East-Central European countries, these transformations were even
                    more complex due to their federal structure. Originally, the Yugoslav and
                    Czechoslovak federal systems had been intended to "engineer" a socialist
                    equality of the member nations. However, following the changes in the late
                    1980s, this basic precondition ceased to exist and the various parts of the
                    federations began to express interests, use powers, build party systems and
                    create ethnic publics.</p>
                <p xml:id="ojs133-p-5">The workshop explored some of these examples in detail, by
                    comparing the transformations of the parliamentary systems in three federal
                    countries in the early 1990s – in Czechoslovakia, Yugoslavia and Germany. In
                    Czechoslovakia, the strong legal continuity between the socialist, revolutionary
                    and post-socialist era created fascinating blends of the three images of
                    parliament. The German case is described through the colonisation metaphor,
                    which is interesting to test on the example of the East German Volkskammer. In
                    Yugoslavia, where the already loose federal system kept getting looser, the
                    individual federal republics with their own socialist parliaments eventually
                    became the only truly important political actors in the process of system and
                    state disintegration.</p>
                <ab type="milestone" style="text-align:center" xml:id="ojs133-ab-1">* * *</ab>
                <p xml:id="ojs133-p-6">Already during the preparations for the workshop one of the
                    ambitions of the organisers was to collect some of the contributions and
                    discussions as well as the results of the research projects and publish them in
                    a special topical issue of our scholarly journal, thus making them available for
                    the scrutiny or challenge of the scholarly and general public. The ambition
                    ultimately resulted in this special issue of the Contributions to Contemporary
                    History (Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino) journal. The issue includes six
                    scientific articles on the topic of Complex Parliaments in Transition: Central
                    European Federations Facing Regime Change. It also includes two reports from the
                    scientific conferences on the history of parliamentarism (from the workshop
                    Complex Parliaments in Transition and the conference Parlamentarismuskritik und
                    Antiparlamentarismus in Europa, which took place in May 2015 in Berlin, also
                    under the umbrella of the EuParl.net) as well as the presentation of the
                    posthumously published study on the Austrian Parliament – the Vienna Reichsrat
                    and Slovenians in the time of the Habsburg Monarchy. </p>
                <p xml:id="ojs133-p-7">All of these contributions undoubtedly demonstrate the
                    complexity of the issue at hand, as well as open and completely convincingly
                    close numerous questions. Besides the specific characteristics of the individual
                    states that they focus on (Czechoslovakia, Germany, Yugoslavia/Slovenia), these
                    contributions also exhibit differences in the intensity of research and
                    approaches in the context of individual national historiographies.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
