<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en" xml:id="ojs-123">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Slovenian Socialist Parliament on the Eve of the Dissolution of the
               Yugoslav Federation</title>
            <title level="a">A Feeble "Ratification Body" or Important Political
               Decision-Maker?</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Jure</forename>
                  <surname>Gašparič</surname>
               </name>
               <roleName>PhD</roleName>
               <roleName>senior researcher</roleName>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                  <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
               </affiliation>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>jure.gasparic@inz.si</email>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2015-11-06</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
               <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
               </address>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>Available at <ref target=" http://hdl.handle.net/11686/36073"
                  >http://hdl.handle.net/11686/36073</ref>
            </pubPlace>
            <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/123</pubPlace>
            <date>2015</date>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="sistory" corresp="#ojs-123 #toc #tables #search #izvlecek #abstract #article #bibliogr #summary">36117</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
            <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
            <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
               historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
               contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
            <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
               foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak and
               Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and Slovenian as well
               as summaries in English.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
            <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
               zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
               stoletje).</p>
            <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
               angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina in
               češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki v
               angleščini.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="sl"/>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>socialist Parliament</term>
               <term>Yugoslavia</term>
               <term>Slovenia</term>
               <term>dissolution</term>
               <term>1989</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords xml:lang="sl">
               <term>socialistični parlament</term>
               <term>Jugoslavija</term>
               <term>Slovenija</term>
               <term>razpad</term>
               <term>1989</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change>
               <date>2015-11-06</date>
               <name>Andrej Pančur</name>
               <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
            </change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="article" n="Articles">
      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>Slovenian Socialist Parliament on the Eve of the Dissolution of the
                  Yugoslav Federation</titlePart>
               <titlePart>A Feeble "Ratification Body" or Important Political
                  Decision-Maker?</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <docAuthor>Jure Gašparič</docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
               <idno type="cobissType">1.01</idno>
               <idno type="UDC">328(497.4)"198"</idno>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>
         <divGen type="toc" xml:id="toc">
            <head>Table of Contents</head>
         </divGen>
         <divGen type="toc" xml:id="tables">
            <head>List of Tables</head>
         </divGen>
         <divGen type="search" xml:id="search">
            <head>Search</head>
         </divGen>
         <div type="abstract" xml:id="izvlecek" xml:lang="sl">
            <head xml:id="head-5">Izvleček</head>
            <head xml:id="head-6" rend="subtitle">Slovenski socialistični parlament na predvečer razpada
               jugoslovanske federacije – bledo "ratafikacijsko telo" ali važen političen
               odločevalec?</head>
            <p xml:id="p-6">Skupščina socialistične republike Slovenije je bila še leta 1986, na
               predvečer razpada jugoslovanske federacije, precej dolgočasen organ, zaprt v
               uradniško-formalistične okvirje. Sestavljali so jo na specifičen posredni način
               izvoljeni neprofesionalni delegati brez večjega družbenega vpliva. Toda prav ta
               skupščina je nato nekaj let kasneje sprejela več ključnih odločitev, ki so uvedle
               večstrankarski sistem, elemente tržnega gospodarstva in okrepile položaj republike.
               Zdi se, da je skupščina takrat postala prvi faktor tranzicije in da je prav ona
               zamajala jugoslovansko federacijo. Toda taka ocena se vendarle ni uveljavila. Njena
               vloga deluje nejasno. Izhajajoč iz tega avtor v prispevku išče odgovor na vprašanje:
               Kakšen organ je bila socialistična skupščina? Pri tem najprej predstavi genezo
               jugoslovanskega skupščinskega sistema in njegove temeljne značilnosti, nato pa
               obravnava tri različne ravni oz. možne poglede na skupščino: pravno raven,
               percepcijsko raven (kako so ljudje dojemali skupščino) in raven notranjih mehanizmov
               (kako se je spreminjala parlamentarna razprava).</p>
            <p xml:id="p-7">Ključne besede: socialistični parlament, Jugoslavija, Slovenija, razpad,
               1989</p>
         </div>
         <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
            <head xml:id="head-7">Abstract</head>
            <p xml:id="p-8">In 1986, on the eve of the dissolution of the Yugoslav Federation, the
               Assembly of the Socialist Republic of Slovenia was a rather boring authority,
               restricted to the bureaucratic and formalist framework. It consisted of
               non‑professional delegates without significant social influence, elected in a
               specific indirect manner. However, it was this very Assembly that passed several key
               decisions a few years later, leading to the introduction of a multi‑party system and
               elements of market economy, as well as strengthening the position of the republic. It
               seems that at the time this Assembly became the primary factor of transition and that
               it was this very institution that destabilised the Yugoslav federation. However, such
               an evaluation has nevertheless not asserted itself. The role of the socialist
               Assembly appears vague. Consequently the author, in his contribution, seeks to answer
               the following question: What sort of an authority body was the socialist Assembly?
               Initially the author presents the genesis of the Yugoslav Assembly system and its
               basic characteristics, and then he explores the three different levels or possible
               outlooks on the Assembly: legal level, perceptual level (how people saw the
               Assembly), and the level of internal mechanisms (how the parliamentary discussions
               changed).</p>
            <p xml:id="p-9">Keywords: socialist Parliament, Yugoslavia, Slovenia, dissolution,
               1989</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="chapter" xml:id="article">
            <head rend="maintitle">Slovenian Socialist Parliament on the Eve of the Dissolution of the Yugoslav
               Federation</head>
            <head rend="subtitle">A Feeble "Ratification Body" or Important Political Decision-Maker?</head>
            <docAuthor>Jure Gašparič<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*">senior researcher,
               PhD, Institute of Contemporary History, Kongresni trg 1, 1000 Ljubljana, Slovenia,
               <ref target="mailto:jure.gasparic@inz.si"
                  >jure.gasparic@inz.si</ref></note></docAuthor>
            <div type="subchapter" xml:id="article-sub01">
               <head xml:id="head-8">To be President of the Socialist Assembly is a "comfortable
                  function"</head>
               <p xml:id="p-10">In April 1986 a relatively young Slovenian politician with quite
                  impressive political mileage Miran Potrč (among other things he had been the
                  President of the Labour Union Association of Yugoslavia a few years earlier; at
                  that time, in terms of protocol, he was in the 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                  place in the Yugoslav hierarchy) was elected as President of the Socialist
                  Assembly of the Republic of Slovenia. Formally this function was very important as
                  well, as in Slovenia only the President of the Republic was superior to him.
                  However, as Potrč wrote in his memoirs, "the President of the Executive Committee,
                  but especially the President of the Central Committee of the League of Communists
                  of Slovenia and occasionally also the President of the Socialist Alliance of the
                  Working People had a greater influence on the situation in the society."<note
                     place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="1">Miran Potrč, <hi rend="italic">Klic k razumu:
                        spomini</hi> (Ljubljana: Modrijan, 2014), 116.</note> To put it differently,
                  Potrč was inferior to the Head of Government, Head of the Party, and Head of a
                  specific "socio-political organisation", the Socialist Alliance of the Working
                  People, whose extensive jurisdiction and open-door policy gave Yugoslav socialism
                  the appearance of democracy. Therefore to be President of the Assembly was, "under
                  normal circumstances", a "comfortable function, as it mostly involved the
                  responsibility for work organisation and prompt decision-making, and even in this
                  regard the President of the Assembly could consult three Presidents of Chambers
                  and a well-organised professional service, while he was not directly responsible
                  for the content of the decisions themselves."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3"
                     n="2">Ibid.</note> In 1986 the circumstances in the state were still
                  "normal".</p>
               <p xml:id="p-11">The economic crisis might have been troubling the country for quite
                  a long time before and no efficient political solutions were on the horizon, but
                  at the same time the spring of 1986 was the time when the Memorandum of the
                  Serbian Academy of Science and Arts – a “Greater Serbian” national programme,
                  which caused so much unrest in Yugoslavia in September 1986 – had not been
                  published yet. Furthermore, the ascent of the Serbian leader Slobodan Milošević,
                  accompanied with a series of worrisome mass rallies, had yet to take place (in
                  1987 and especially 1988). The more serious conflicts with Belgrade and Yugoslav
                  People's Army had not happened yet, either. The resounding 57<hi
                     rend="superscript">th</hi> issue of the Nova revija magazine, containing the
                  contributions to the Slovenian national programme, would not be published until
                  1987, and the so‑called Trial of the Four against Janez Janša and others in front
                  of the Military Court, which mobilised a significant part of the Slovenian
                  community, would not happen for another two years... The public opinion was still
                  quite uncritical and vague at the time.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3">Jure
                     Gašparič and Mojca Šorn, "Od tovariša delegata do gospoda poslanca: O razpravi
                     v socialistični enostrankarski skupščini in demokratičnem tranzicijskem
                     parlamentu v Sloveniji," <hi rend="italic">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</hi>
                     54, no. 1 (2014): 37-47.</note> According to Miran Potrč, the public was
                  focused on the "practical questions", but remained mostly indifferent towards the
                  more general political issues. </p>
               <p xml:id="p-12">Such a social climate was also reflected in the Parliament. Debates
                  about new problematic issues were non‑existent. The proceedings were tedious and
                  very formal, almost bureaucratic, which was the result of the “self‑management”
                  system. As it was, Members of the Assembly were not MPs, but rather “delegates”
                  coming from the so-called basic organisations. Therefore, as the delegates were
                  not skilful politicians, they mostly read the "reports" drawn up by their
                  organisations and agreed with the proposals at the sessions.<note place="foot"
                     xml:id="ftn5" n="4">Miran Potrč, interview by author, Ljubljana, April 24,
                     2014. Sound recordings and transcriptions of the interview are kept by the
                     author.</note>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="p-13">However, the comfortable life in the Republican Socialist Parliament
                  did not last long: the term from 1986 to 1990 turned out to be turbulent and
                  decisive, and also final incarnation of the "classic" delegate Assembly form.
                  Afterwards the Assembly stopped functioning, but not before singing its swan song.
                  As it happened, in its final years the Assembly was often pushed to the forefront
                  and had a decisive impact on the events.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subchapter" xml:id="article-sub02">
               <head xml:id="head-9">Republican Socialist Assemblies in the political system of the
                  Yugoslav Federation</head>
               <p xml:id="p-14">Before we begin with the in-depth exploration of the activities and
                  character of the Republican Assembly in its final period, we should take a look at
                  the genesis of its creation as well as its position in the Yugoslav political
                  system.</p>
               <p xml:id="p-15">Already during World War II a completely new political system, based
                  on the people's authority, started emerging in the occupied Yugoslavia. In this
                  process Slovenia attained a status of a federal unit (as one of the Yugoslav
                  republics) with its own constitution and statehood. At that time the establishment
                  of a new system under the leadership of the communists took place gradually, in
                  agreement with the Allies, but at the same time resolutely and intensely. While,
                  on one hand, new authorities were being created, on the other hand the former
                  Yugoslav King's government-in-exile in London still existed. Therefore both sides
                  sat down at the negotiating table, especially due to the British pressure, and
                  reached a compromise: on one hand the establishment of a joint government of the
                  resistance movement and government-in-exile – a kind of a transitional government,
                  which was nothing special in the European context – and on the other hand the
                  "restoration" of multi-party democracy.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5">For
                     more information see Jerca Vodušek Starič, <hi rend="italic">Prevzem
                        oblasti</hi> (Ljubljana: Cankarjeva založba, 1992), 106−107, 130−145.</note>
                  At this point we should add that the "restoration" of the multi-party system in
                  Yugoslavia in accordance with the King Alexander Karađorđević Imposed Constitution
                  of 1931 and the accompanying electoral law would imply the introduction of public
                  elections where not everyone could run for office. It would therefore mean the
                  introduction of a kind of multi-party democracy disputable even in its formalistic
                     aspect.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="6">Jure Gašparič, <hi rend="italic"
                        >SLS pod kraljevo diktaturo: Diktatura kralja Aleksandra in politika
                        Slovenske ljudske stranke 1929-1935</hi> (Ljubljana: Modrijan, 2007),
                     116−124.</note> After the war the pre-war multi-party system was in fact not
                  fully restored, but rather only partially. Yet in the formal sense this was even
                  more prudent. As it was, the elections were now secret, minor parties allowed, and
                  in the beginning even media pluralism was acceptable.<note place="foot"
                     xml:id="ftn8" n="7">Aleš Gabrič, "Opozicija v Sloveniji po letu 1945," <hi
                        rend="italic">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</hi> 45, no. 2 (2005): 104.
                     Vodušek Starič, <hi rend="italic">Prevzem oblasti</hi>, 166−167,
                     331−337.</note> However, in all other aspects and conditions for the
                  development of the political life this restoration was largely a replication of
                  the 1930s. </p>
               <p xml:id="p-16">In a state where a multi-party system was not desired, a state-wide
                  coalition named the People's Front was established, headed by the Communist
                     Party.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8">The basic characteristics of the
                     "People's Front" approach was the same throughout the Central and Southeastern
                     Europe. For example, a similar platform was also established in Czechoslovakia,
                     where the non-communist politics headed by Beneš had a far stronger starting
                     position as in Yugoslavia. The so‑called "Košice Government Programme", which
                     was the first step towards "people's democracy", was comprehended in various
                     ways at that time. Some people saw in it a maximum package of reforms, while
                     others believed it was merely the beginning of a radical transformation. – Jiří
                     Vykoukal, Bohuslav Litera and Miroslav Tejchman, <hi rend="italic">Východ:
                        Vznik, vývoj a rozpad sovětského bloku 1944−1989</hi> (Praha: Libri, 2000),
                     126.</note> The so‑called extra‑Front opposition was thwarted (the communists
                  controlled the repressive apparatus and the political police), and therefore the
                  opposition ultimately failed to appear at the elections. A single list, which
                  could count on winning in any case, competed for the votes.<note place="foot"
                     xml:id="ftn10" n="9">Vodušek Starič, <hi rend="italic">Prevzem oblasti</hi>,
                     343−369.</note> In the autumn of 1945 the American embassy in Yugoslavia
                  reported to Washington that the country was turning into a totalitarian police
                  state with no freedom of speech and press, but that "significant opposition or
                  objections to the existing situation are nevertheless virtually
                     non-existent".<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="10">Gabrič, "Opozicija po
                     1945," 102.</note>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="p-17">While in certain parts of Yugoslavia, especially in Serbia, the
                  opposition remained active despite the difficulties, the situation in Slovenia was
                  completely different. Here the idea and political form of the People's Front had
                  already been implemented by the communists as early as in 1941, when the
                  Liberation Front was established. At a congress immediately after the war the
                  Liberation Front pronounced itself as the "only political representative for the
                  whole of Slovenia".<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11">Božo Repe, <hi
                        rend="italic">Rdeča Slovenija: Tokovi in obrazi iz obdobja socializma</hi>
                     (Ljubljana: Sophia, 2003), 25.</note> The actual power of the Liberation Front,
                  primarily stemming from the resistance against the occupiers and the victory in
                  the national liberation war, was not questionable either. The political structure
                  of Slovenia after 1945 became increasingly monolithic. However, the complete
                  absence of any opposition did not result exclusively from the activities of the
                  communists, but also from the actions of the pre-war political parties. Their
                  wartime activities and collaborationist heritage had pushed them to the edge of
                  the political space.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="12">Janko Pleterski, "O
                     soslednosti novejše zgodovine Slovencev: Nekaj pripomb ob in k posvetu Slovenci
                     in leto 1941," <hi rend="italic">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</hi> 43, no. 1
                     (2003): 109.</note>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="p-18">After World War II we can therefore no longer speak about classic
                  parliamentarism, since despite the existence of the Assembly and elections only a
                  single political party existed in this period. Apart from the one‑party aspect,
                  the main characteristics of the post‑war system also included the constant
                  distancing from the principles of the functioning of the classic parliamentary
                  system and gradual introduction of a specific corporatist system. This was also
                  evident from the structure of each Assembly.</p>
               <p xml:id="p-19">The Constitutional Assembly consisted of two chambers: the Federal
                  Assembly, elected on the basis of the state-wide and equal right, and the National
                  Assembly, where each republic had 25 representatives. Unicameral Assemblies of the
                  People's Republics existed at the republican level.<note place="foot"
                     xml:id="ftn14" n="13">Aleš Gabrič, "Volitve v Ustavodajno skupščino novembra
                     1945," in <hi rend="italic">Slovenska novejša zgodovina: Od programa Zedinjena
                        Slovenija do mednarodnega priznanja Republike Slovenije: 1848−1992</hi>, ed.
                     Jasna Fischer et al. (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Mladinska
                     knjiga, 2005), 854−860. Aleš Gabrič, "Prva slovenska ustava," in <hi
                        rend="italic">Slovenska novejša zgodovina</hi>, 867−868.</note> After the
                  1953 constitutional reform the National Assembly was annexed to the Federal
                  Assembly, and in its stead a new chamber, called the Council of Producers, was
                  established. Its members were elected indirectly, according to the specific
                  branches of economy, which was the first step towards corporatism. The new
                  constitution of 1963 implemented a further systemic upgrade. The Federal Assembly,
                  later renamed as the Assembly of the Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia, was
                  expanded to five councils (chambers): Federal Council (which included the Council
                  of Nations), Economic Council, Educational and Cultural Council, Social and Health
                  Council, and Organisational-Political Council. The same system was introduced in
                  each of the republics, but here the Republican Council took the place of the
                  Federal Council.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="14">Mateja Režek, "Ustava
                     reforma leta 1953," in <hi rend="italic">Slovenska novejša zgodovina</hi>,
                     950−952. Mateja Režek, "Na pragu reform," in:<hi rend="italic"> Slovenska
                        novejša zgodovina</hi>, 998−999.</note>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="p-20">Despite the one-party Assembly system, several elements of classic
                  parliamentarism can be identified in the activities of the Slovenian Assemblies
                  throughout this time. However, these elements were merely fragmentary and
                  especially characteristic of the period of the so-called Party liberalism in the
                  1960s. Already in 1966 President of the Government Janko Smole tied the question
                  of the government vote of confidence to the vote on a concrete proposal, which was
                  completely unusual for the Assembly system (unlike the parliamentary system);
                  while the classic role of MPs became especially apparent a few years later. In
                  1971 an actual political affair broke out, known as the "Affair of 25 Deputies".
                  At this time a group of deputies proposed, apart from the "official" candidate,
                  its own candidate as a member of the Presidency of the Socialist Federal Republic
                  of Yugoslavia. Although unsuccessful, this action questioned the monopoly of
                  personnel management of the Party leadership.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16"
                     n="15">Ciril Ribičič, <hi rend="italic">Siva tipka 074</hi> (Ljubljana:
                     Enotnost, 1995), 17−24.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subchapter" xml:id="article-sub03">
               <head xml:id="head-10">The "delegate system" (1974-1991)</head>
               <p xml:id="p-21">The last thorough constitutional reform followed in 1974 (before
                  that numerous constitutional amendments had been adopted between 1968 and 1971).
                  This reform represented the peak of the "Yugoslav experiment" and remained in
                  force until the 1990s. A system of delegates was introduced, which was a
                  non‑transparent and impractical indirect concept of total self‑management. The
                  Federal Assembly of the Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia once again became
                  bicameral, consisting of two equal chambers: the Federal Chamber and the Chamber
                  of Republics and Provinces, to which the delegates were appointed from the
                  Assemblies of six republics and two autonomous provinces. The Republican
                  Assemblies, also the Slovenian Assembly, became tricameral, consisting of the
                  Chamber of Associated Labour, Chamber of Municipalities and Socio‑Political
                     Chamber.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16">Zdenko Čepič, "Federaliziranje
                     federacije 1967-1971," in <hi rend="italic">Slovenska novejša zgodovina</hi>,
                     1052−1054. Zdenko Čepič, "Ustava 1974: preureditev jugoslovanske federacije,
                     delegatski sistem in dogovorna ekonomija," in <hi rend="italic">Slovenska
                        novejša zgodovina</hi>, 1094−1101. Božo Repe, "Pravne in politične podlage,
                     okoliščine in pomen prvih demokratičnih volitev," in: <hi rend="italic">Razvoj
                        slovenskega parlamentarizma: Kolokvij ob 10. obletnici parlamentarizma v
                        Sloveniji: Zbornik referatov, koreferatov in razprav</hi>, ed. Tatjana
                     Krašovec (Ljubljana: Državni zbor Republike Slovenije, 2000), 41−62.</note>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="p-22">The delegate system, outlined primarily by the Slovenian politician
                  Edvard Kardelj and his supporters, was, according to Peter Vodopivec, based on the
                  author's "Bolshevik Proudhonistic socio‑political fantasies" (one of the reasons
                  why in the West Kardelj was mockingly referred to as an "ideological tailor"). The
                  architects of the new order deconstructed the whole society together with all
                  organisations into the smallest possible parts (all institutes, institutions,
                  companies, etc.), which would supposedly encourage the mass politicisation of the
                  population and their engagement. In the second half of the 1970s almost 300,000
                  people – in Slovenia with its two million inhabitants – were included into the
                  delegate functions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17">Peter Vodopivec,
                     "Komunistične skupščine v senci partije," in: <hi rend="italic">Analiza razvoja
                        slovenskega parlamentarizma</hi>, ed. Barbara Vogrinec (Ljubljana: Inštitut
                     za civilizacijo in kulturo, 2005), 286-287.</note>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="p-23">How could a citizen become a delegate in the Slovenian Assembly? If
                  it was a question of the Chamber of Municipalities, a citizen had to be first
                  elected as a member of the “basic” delegation, for example in his/her local
                  community. Then the local communities elected delegations for the municipal
                  communities, and after that the municipal communities organised the groups of
                  delegates to join the Republican Assembly. On each occasion one of the delegates
                  from the group attended the session of the Republican Parliament, chosen on the
                  basis of the issues on the agenda.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18">See <hi
                        rend="italic">Zakon o volitvah in delegiranju v skupščine: Zakon o volitvah
                        in odpoklicu Predsedstva Socialistične republike Slovenije s pojasnili
                        Cirila Ribičiča in Franca Grada</hi> (Ljubljana: ČZ Uradni list SRS,
                     1985).</note> If it was a question of the Chamber of Associated Labour, a
                  citizen had to be first elected as a member of the delegation in his/her company
                  (factory). These delegations sent delegates to the Municipal Chamber of Associated
                  Labour, which at the end chose the delegates for the Republican Assembly. If it
                  was a question of the Socio-Political Chamber, a citizen had to be a member of a
                  "socio-political organisation" and as such elected as a member of the Republican
                  Assembly by the municipal socio-political chambers.<note place="foot"
                     xml:id="ftn20" n="19">Apart from these chambers, the "Self-Management Interest
                     Associations" were a part of the assembly system at the time as well (SIS).
                     These "associations" supposedly enabled people to express their common
                     interests in the fields of education, culture, health. Special assemblies of
                     Self-Management Interest Associations made decisions about matters from their
                     jurisdiction on equal footing with the competent Assembly chambers.</note>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="p-24">What this meant for the status of the delegates was described
                  vividly by the literary historian Dušan Pirjevec: "To be a Member of Parliament
                  nevertheless meant something once. Today it means nothing to be a delegate. This
                  is no longer a political function – the only politicians left are members of the
                     Party."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="20">Vodopivec, "Komunistične
                     skupščine v senci partije," 287.</note> Miha Ribarič, secretary of the
                  constitutional commission of the Republican Assembly, said something similar
                  already in 1978: "One of the fundamental unacceptable characteristics of the
                  delegate Assembly system is ... that the delegate Assemblies in fact often
                  function as a sort of ratification or verification bodies of materials, decisions,
                  solutions and proposals, prepared by the executive or administrative bodies."<note
                     place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21">Miha Ribarič, <hi rend="italic">Spomini:
                        Slovenija – Jugoslavija</hi> (Ljubljana: Fakulteta za družbene vede, 2015),
                     61.</note>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="p-25">However, the Yugoslav crisis intensified and a decade after
                  Ribarič's resigned observations the role of Assemblies and delegates started
                  changing. The sessions of the Federal Assembly became increasingly lively and
                  conflicting, and it even happened that in 1988 the President of the Federal
                  Government Branko Mikulić resigned because he failed to secure the Assembly
                  support for his budget proposal.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="22"
                     >Vodopivec, "Komunistične skupščine v senci partije," 292.</note> While this is
                  a rather normal occurrence in classic parliamentary democracies, in Yugoslavia
                  this happened for the first time after 1945. However, at that time certain
                  Republican Assemblies started becoming far more important than the Federal
                  Parliament, among them especially the Slovenian Assembly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subchapter" xml:id="article-sub04">
               <head xml:id="head-11">The final convening of the Slovenian Socialist Assembly and
                  its place in historiography</head>
               <p xml:id="p-26">The crisis, which went on unacknowledged by the Yugoslav political
                  elites for a long time (the leading politicians avoided the term "crisis"
                  consciously), and all its many layers, economic as well as social and political,
                  had an increasingly obvious impact on that period. The numerous solutions that
                  were gradually outlined were very diverse and exceedingly dependent on the
                  individual republican elites. Due to the federal structure of the state this led
                  to severe mutual conflicts. The elite that gathered around Slobodan Milošević
                  (initially the President of the Central Committee of the League of Communists of
                  Serbia, then the President of Presidency of the Socialist Republic of Serbia)
                  asserted itself as the strongest and also most aggressive. Together with its
                  allies (the Montenegrin, Kosovo and Vojvodina leadership) it argued for the
                  increased powers of the central federal authorities, therefore for the reduction
                  of federalism and for the classic socialist system that Yugoslavia had adhered to
                  before the constitutional reforms between 1971 and 1974. On the other hand a
                  tentative alliance formed between Slovenia, Croatia, Bosnia and Herzegovina and
                  Macedonia, brought together especially because of the fear of the centralist and
                  nationalist offensive of the Milošević's circle. Within this circle the leadership
                  of the League of Communists of Slovenia argued for the clearest standpoints, aimed
                  at the democratisation of the society, allowing the formation of non‑communist
                  political groups, a more prominent role of the republics and market economy.<note
                     place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="23">Božo Repe, <hi rend="italic">Jutri je nov
                        dan: Slovenci in razpad Jugoslavije</hi> (Ljubljana: Modrijan, 2002), 63−73,
                     232−235.</note>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="p-27">The already loose federal system kept getting looser and the
                  political control in the individual republics was becoming less and less
                  effective. The demands for pluralism and systemic changes became increasingly
                  decisive, and finally they also manifested themselves in the hall of the Slovenian
                  Assembly of delegates. Thus in its final convening between 1986 and 1990, the
                  Slovenian Assembly became one of the key supporters of a peaceful and evolutionary
                  transformation into a multiparty parliamentary system. The adoption of numerous
                  constitutional amendments to the Slovenian Constitution in September 1989 was
                  especially important.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="24">Miran Potrč, "Za
                     prvo demokratično izvoljeno Skupščino Republike Slovenije je dala zakonsko
                     podlago zakonodaja, sprejeta 27. 12. 1989 v Skupščini Socialistične Republike
                     Slovenije," in <hi rend="italic">Prihodnost parlamentarne demokracije: Zbornik
                        strokovnega srečanja ob 20. obletnici prvih večstrankarskih volitev</hi>,
                     ed. Tatjana Krašovec and Mojca Pristavec Đogić (Ljubljana: Državni zbor
                     Republike Slovenije, 2010), 26−32.</note>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="p-28">In the increasingly tense circumstances at the time, on 27 September
                  1989 the delegates, with the strong engagement of the civil society,<note
                     place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25">For more information about the circumstances
                     see Repe, <hi rend="italic">Jutri je nov dan</hi>, 177-183.</note> actually
                  introduced an asymmetrical position of Slovenia in the federation, as they
                  implemented the "security, economic and developmental priority of interests and
                  needs of Slovenia" before the federation. Furthermore, they enabled the conditions
                  for direct and secret elections,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="26">The
                     elections were called for April 1990. Apart from a few former socio‑political
                     organisations, transformed into political parties, new parties united in the
                     Demos coalition also competed for the votes. Altogether this coalition received
                     the majority of the votes and formed a government. The political life proceeded
                     increasingly in the spirit of multiparty parliamentarism, although "only" the
                     delegate Assembly, consisting of three chambers, existed.</note> allowed for
                  the establishment of political parties, and introduced elements of market
                     economy.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="27">Potrč, <hi rend="italic">Klic
                        k razumu: spomini</hi>, 127-140.</note> Throughout this process important
                  political debates unfolded in the Assembly and far‑reaching decisions were made.
                  Even symbolism – always an important matter in politics – was not lacking. In
                  September 1989, after adopting the constitutional amendments, the delegates
                  spontaneously (and allegedly quite out of tune) sang Zdravljica (A Toast), the
                  song that one of the amendments proclaimed as the Slovenian anthem. Zdravljica was
                  written in 1847 by the most important poet of the Slovenian romantic period France
                  Prešeren, famous among the people and almost synonymous with Slovenian literature.
                  Everybody knew the popular song (structurally a toast), and they declared their
                  adherence by singing it. Many a tear was shed on this occasion, and the Assembly
                  politics was no longer boring, but rather very emotional...</p>
               <p xml:id="p-29">Thus it seems, at the first glance, that in 1989 the Assembly became
                  the primary factor of the transition: as it was, it adopted the acts that shook
                  the Yugoslav federation. However, such assessments cannot be found in the
                  historiographic literature. The authors who focus on the dissolution of Yugoslavia
                  and definitely mention the adoption of the constitutional amendments rarely look
                  carefully at the authority body that adopted them and the way in which they were
                     adopted.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="28">See for example Robert M.
                     Hayden, <hi rend="italic">Blueprints for a House Divided: The Constitutional
                        Logic of the Yugoslav Conflicts </hi>(Ann Arbor: The University of Michigan
                     Press, 2000). Susan L. Woodward, <hi rend="italic">Balkan Tragedy: Chaos and
                        Dissolution after the Cold War</hi> (Washington D. C.: The Brookings
                     Institution, 1995). Sabrina P. Ramet, <hi rend="italic">The Three Yugoslavias:
                        State-Building and legitimation, 1918-2005</hi> (Washington D. C.: Woodrow
                     Wilson Center Press, 2005). Lenard J. Cohen, <hi rend="italic">Broken Bonds:
                        The Disintegration of Yugoslavia</hi> (Boulder, San Francisco, Oxford:
                     Westview press, 1993). There is a noticeable difference between the way in
                     which the Assembly is seen by Slovenian and foreign authors. Slovenian authors
                     generally pay more attention to it and try to explain its decisions; primarily
                     Repe, <hi rend="italic">Jutri je nov dan</hi> and the authors of the work <hi
                        rend="italic">Slovenska novejša zgodovina</hi>, apart from them also Stefano
                     Lusa, <hi rend="italic">Razkroj oblasti: Slovenski komunisti in demokratizacija
                        države</hi> (Ljubljana: Modrijan, 2012). Rosvita Pesek, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Osamosvojitev Slovenije: "Ali naj Republika Slovenija postane samostojna in
                        neodvisna država?"</hi> (Ljubljana: Nova revija, 2007). The Assembly is seen
                     in a similar manner also by Viktor Maier, <hi rend="italic">Wie Jugoslawien
                        verspielt wurde</hi> (München: C. H. Beck, 1995).</note> They usually refer
                  to the voting in the Assembly with expressions like "Slovenia adopted" or
                  "Slovenians decided" or "Slovenian politics opted for", etc. On this basis we can
                  make at least two different conclusions about the character of the Assembly at the
                  time: </p>
               <list type="unordered" xml:id="list-1">
                  <item>either that in the opinion of numerous experts in Yugoslavia until 1990
                     decisions were still made by a few people in the key positions, while the
                     Assembly merely verified their decisions, which merely happened to be
                     resounding and very significant in 1989;</item>
                  <item>or that despite the delegate system the Assembly was a body of
                     representatives which embodied the political will of the population of the
                     Socialist Republic of Slovenia.</item>
               </list>
               <p xml:id="p-30">The role of the Assembly is thus unclear, and the logical question
                  is therefore the following:</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subchapter" xml:id="article-sub05">
               <head xml:id="head-12">What sort of an authority body was the Socialist
                  Assembly?</head>
               <p xml:id="p-31">In the Yugoslav federation, the Slovenian Socialist Assembly at this
                  time, as the socialist system was falling apart, was a rather complicated
                  organism, and it should be analysed in detail. In order to ensure its
                  understanding and temporal placement I will attempt to deal with three levels: the
                  formalistic legal level, the perceptual level, and the manner in which the
                  Assembly operated.</p>
               <div type="subsubchapter" xml:id="article-sub05-sub01">
                  <head xml:id="head-13">Legal level</head>
                  <p xml:id="p-32">In view of the legal sources (especially the 1974 Constitution)
                     and literature we can state almost definitely that during the dissolution of
                     the state the Assembly was an authority body impossible to bypass. “The
                     Assembly of the Socialist Republic of Slovenia is a social self-management body
                     and the highest authority in the framework of the rights and duties of the
                     republic", stated Article 334 of the republican constitution.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn30" n="29">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ustava Socialistične republike Slovenije</hi>, §
                        334.</note> As such it was an important factor in the process of political
                     decision-making with broad jurisdictions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31"
                        n="30">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ustava Socialistične republike Slovenije</hi>, §
                        335.</note> There was nothing else – not at the federal nor at the
                     republican level – that could replace it. The decision-making process at the
                     time was "implemented through complicated mechanisms and procedures", which
                     often only formally ensured the democratic choice and participation of the
                     people. In fact the purpose of the self-management mechanisms, according to
                     Miran Potrč, was primarily to ensure that the system as envisioned in the Party
                     programmes was not threatened.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="31">Potrč,
                           <hi rend="italic">Klic k razumu: spomini</hi>, 121.</note> However,
                     without the Assembly the adoption of decisions was nevertheless impossible,
                     especially when it came to amending the constitution. In his commentary on the
                     adoption of the constitutional amendments, the constitutional lawyer Miha
                     Ribarič wrote that with these amendments Slovenia addressed some of the key
                     questions regarding its position in Yugoslavia – a federation which in itself
                     had "no original functions and jurisdictions; meaning such that would not
                     originate from its members."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="32">Ribarič,
                           <hi rend="italic">Spomini: Slovenija – Jugoslavija</hi>, 230-234.</note>
                     The members of the federation, the republics, could therefore strengthen or
                     weaken their own position through the decisions adopted in their Assemblies.
                     Furthermore, in 1989 many people in Belgrade found it questionable whether the
                     decisions of the Slovenian Assembly, which strengthened the Slovenian position,
                     were compatible with the Constitution of the Socialist Federal Republic of
                     Yugoslavia. However, no one questioned the formal manner in which these
                     amendments were adopted. </p>
                  <p xml:id="p-33">Thus the Assembly had all of the systemic conditions for actually
                     carrying out an important political role in the system. Without its engagement
                     the political changes would not be possible, at least not in the constitutional
                     manner characteristic of the Slovenian emancipation process and the initial
                     stage of its political transition. After all, even the current Slovenian
                     Constitution from 1991 was adopted in accordance with the constitutional
                     revision procedures, set out in the preceding 1974 Constitution.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="33">Jure Gašparič, <hi rend="italic">Državni
                           zbor Republike Slovenije 1992-2012: O slovenskem parlamentarizmu</hi>
                        (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2012), 42-46.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p xml:id="p-34">At the same time the Assembly was an elected authority body, even
                     if in a special delegate manner. The delegation elections differed
                     significantly from the classic parliamentary elections, as they did not reflect
                     the "single act of the voters, authorising the elected Members of Parliament to
                     adopt governmental decisions as their general representatives and in their
                     name". According to the legal interpretation at the time, the delegation
                     elections meant "the beginning of a permanent, four-year working cooperation
                     between delegations and delegates, working people and citizens..." Supposedly
                     people were "continuously deciding" which guidelines their delegates should
                     observe. The system was a kind of an implementation of direct democracy.
                     Consequently the Assembly was not envisioned as a classic representative
                        body.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="34">
                        <hi rend="italic">Zakon o volitvah in delegiranju v skupščine: Zakon o
                           volitvah in odpoklicu Predsedstva Socialistične republike Slovenije s
                           pojasnili Cirila Ribičiča in Franca Grada</hi>, uvodna pojasnila.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsubchapter" xml:id="article-sub05-sub012">
                  <head xml:id="head-14">Perceptual level / perception of the Assembly</head>
                  <p xml:id="p-35">The second moment, important in order to understand the role and
                     activities of the Assembly, is its perception among the people, the trust in
                     the Assembly and vice versa: the Assembly's interaction with the public
                     opinion, with the impulses of the time as felt by the population. Miran Potrč
                     says:</p>
                  <quote xml:id="quote-1">"I am convinced it is very likely that the connection
                     between the public opinion, the demands of the civil and social organisations
                     as they were established at the time... that the links between them and the
                     Parliament were stronger than today. ... These connections were stronger
                     then... For example in 1990, or between 1986 and 1990, between 1988 and 1990.
                     Much stronger. At that time we paid great attention to the public opinion. We
                     were very mindful of what was discussed in public, what the public demands
                     were. I am not saying that we satisfied all of them, far from it, but we
                     considered more or less all of these demands and met them in many ways."<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="35">Miran Potrč, interview by author,
                        Ljubljana, April 24, 2014.</note>
                  </quote>
                  <p xml:id="p-36">We should also emphasise that at that time the delegates were not
                     the same people for the whole term: due to the system of interchangeable
                     delegates the Assembly sessions could be attended by new, different delegates,
                     sometimes also sympathisers of the new social movements.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn37" n="36">
                        <hi rend="italic">Zakon o volitvah in delegiranju v skupščine: Zakon o
                           volitvah in odpoklicu Predsedstva Socialistične republike Slovenije s
                           pojasnili Cirila Ribičiča in Franca Grada</hi>. Potrč, <hi rend="italic"
                           >Klic k razumu: spomini</hi>, 117.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p xml:id="p-37">Thus the Assembly could follow the wishes and observe the demands
                     of the public, and the delegates were aware of their responsibility. For
                     example, when President of the Assembly Potrč opened the session on the
                     occasion when the amendments were adopted, he said: "It has been a long time
                     since the delegates of this Assembly had such a profound responsibility to the
                     Slovenian nation as we do today."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="37"
                        >"Slovenska ustava stremi k svobodi in kreativnosti ljudi," <hi
                           rend="italic">Delo</hi>, September 28, 1989.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p xml:id="p-38">However, did the public share the opinion that this was the case?
                     Did the people see the Assembly as their representative?</p>
                  <p xml:id="p-39">The results of the public opinion polls at the time are very
                     revealing. In 1986, as far as the municipal level was concerned, 50 % of people
                     answered "yes" to the question: "We have just held the Assembly election. Do
                     you feel that you have taken part in the selection and appointment of the
                     candidates for the leading functions?". However, when their participation in
                     the appointment of the leading candidates at the republican and federal level
                     was in question, almost three quarters of interviewees answered "no".<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="38">Niko Toš et al., <hi rend="italic"
                           >Slovensko javno mnenje 1986 [database]</hi> (Ljubljana: Univerza Edvarda
                        Kardelja, Fakulteta za sociologijo, politične vede in novinarstvo, Center za
                        raziskovanje javnega mnenja in množičnih komunikacij [creation ], 1986;
                        Ljubljana: Univerza v Ljubljani, Fakulteta za družbene vede, Arhiv
                        družboslovnih podatkov [distribution ], 1999).</note> People obviously felt
                     that the delegate system was alienated and they felt that they did not take
                     part in the formation of the Assembly.</p>
                  <p xml:id="p-40">Neither were they very familiar with the political system: in
                     1989, on the eve of the adoption of the constitutional amendments, most of them
                     were unable to name all three Assembly Chambers.</p>
                  <p xml:id="p-41">However, on the other hand the answers of the people were in
                     favour of the Assembly. A minimal percentage responded that they did not trust
                     the Assembly. Mostly they only wished for more (direct) democracy (which is a
                     sort of a paradox, as this very system supposedly implemented direct
                     democracy). It was especially important that at the time a very large majority
                     of people agreed with the constitutional amendments.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn40" n="39">Niko Toš et al., Slo<hi rend="italic">vensko javno
                           mnenje 1989: Stališča o ustavnih dopolnilih [database]</hi> (Ljubljana:
                        Univerza Edvarda Kardelja, Fakulteta za sociologijo, politične vede in
                        novinarstvo, Center za raziskovanje javnega mnenja in množičnih komunikacij
                        [creation ], 1989; Ljubljana: Univerza v Ljubljani, Fakulteta za družbene
                        vede, Arhiv družboslovnih podatkov [distribution ], 1999).</note>
                  </p>
                  <p xml:id="p-42">The favourable inclination that the people showed to the
                     decisions of the Assembly on the day when the amendments were adopted and
                     immediately after that day reached dimensions which are rare even in the system
                     of the classic parliamentary democracy. When the delegates arrived to the
                     Assembly, the representatives of a new social movement (which later grew into a
                     political party, like many others) the Greens of Slovenia distributed apples
                     for encouragement; and when the delegates were leaving, a crowd of people
                     waited for them, applauding. The passing cars honked their horns euphorically.
                     It is also not negligible that the Slovenian delegates were under significant
                     pressure throughout this time. Almost all federal bodies were opposed to the
                     adoption of the amendments. The discussions about them were frequently
                     turbulent and very emotional, the warnings foreboding, and in the end the
                     Slovenian Assembly was "more or less explicitly" advised to postpone the
                     adoption of the amendments. In his commentary after the adoption of the
                     amendments, the journalist of the central Slovenian daily newspaper Delo,
                     Danilo Slivnik, wrote:</p>
                  <quote xml:id="quote-2">"In the following days some people will try to add to or
                     subtract from this event, typical of politics everywhere. However, they will
                     hardly be able to change the fact that the current political turning point in
                     Slovenia is a consequence of wider democratic changes in the republic, in which
                     everyone from the still incomplete national political circle participated: from
                     those individuals who kept sending their "letters to the editor" to various
                     newspapers for months and months... To the representatives of the most
                     "official politics".<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="40">Danilo Slivnik,
                        "Po meri Slovencev," <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, September 28, 1989.
                     </note>
                  </quote>
                  <p xml:id="p-43">Thus in September 1989 the Assembly was implementing the
                     political will of the population. However, as the young Slavko Gaber, later a
                     long-time Minister of Education, underlined in a newspaper column: the Assembly
                     could only acquire this legitimacy by "taking steps towards the normal
                     conclusion of its term". He claimed that the Assembly could not take merit as a
                     classic elected Parliament, therefore he spoke in favour of its
                        abolishment.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="41">Slavko Gaber,
                        "Skupščina komunistov se odpravi," <hi rend="italic">Telex</hi>, October 26,
                        1989.</note> This in fact happened shortly afterwards, but the dilemma
                     remained: was the Assembly only legitimate because with its own decisions it
                     simultaneously abolished itself?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsubchapter" xml:id="article-sub05-sub03">
                  <head xml:id="head-15">Operating principle</head>
                  <p xml:id="p-44">In order to understand the last, 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                     convening of the Slovenian Socialist Assembly, I believed that it was necessary
                     to ask another question: in what way did the Assembly operate, had its cultural
                     pattern changed, had the internal mechanisms during the sessions been altered?
                     In order to find the answer I employed a different methodological approach,
                     making use of the advances of digital humanities. Building on the thesis that
                     every parliament (even the socialist kind) primarily focuses on and pays
                     attention to discussions, I have analysed the quantitative characteristics of
                     discussions on the basis of a few reference books containing verbatim records
                     of the Assembly sessions. Thus my colleague Andrej Pančur and I have checked
                     how many words the delegates (and later MPs) spoke at individual sessions, how
                     many different speeches they held, how many words they used for discussing an
                     individual item, and what was the proportion between the number of words of the
                     President and the other participants of the discussions. The results are not
                     very surprising, even if they may initially appear to be.</p>
                  <table xml:id="table-1" rend="table-scroll hover">
                     <head>A part of the quantitative analysis, prepared by Andrej Pančur on the
                        basis of selected collections of verbatim records of certain Assembly /
                        Parliament sessions in the stated years</head>
                     <row role="label">
                        <cell>Year</cell>
                        <cell>Number of speeches per session</cell>
                        <cell>Number of words per session</cell>
                        <cell>Number of speeches of the President per session</cell>
                        <cell>Number of words of the President per session</cell>
                        <cell>Proportion: words of the President vs. everyone else</cell>
                        <cell>Number of words per session item</cell>
                        <cell>Proportion: words of the President vs. everyone else per item</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1973</cell>
                        <cell>73</cell>
                        <cell>16315</cell>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                        <cell>3524</cell>
                        <cell>0.22</cell>
                        <cell>1991</cell>
                        <cell>0.19</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1982</cell>
                        <cell>71</cell>
                        <cell>18987</cell>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                        <cell>5497</cell>
                        <cell>0.29</cell>
                        <cell>1386</cell>
                        <cell>0.27</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1984</cell>
                        <cell>90</cell>
                        <cell>27252</cell>
                        <cell>53</cell>
                        <cell>7088</cell>
                        <cell>0.26</cell>
                        <cell>1830</cell>
                        <cell>0.22</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1986</cell>
                        <cell>98</cell>
                        <cell>22055</cell>
                        <cell>59</cell>
                        <cell>6909</cell>
                        <cell>0.31</cell>
                        <cell>1396</cell>
                        <cell>0.27</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1987</cell>
                        <cell>111</cell>
                        <cell>25123</cell>
                        <cell>63</cell>
                        <cell>7190</cell>
                        <cell>0.29</cell>
                        <cell>1057</cell>
                        <cell>0.25</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1989</cell>
                        <cell>130</cell>
                        <cell>35530</cell>
                        <cell>75</cell>
                        <cell>10045</cell>
                        <cell>0.28</cell>
                        <cell>1978</cell>
                        <cell>0.25</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1990</cell>
                        <cell>472</cell>
                        <cell>68401</cell>
                        <cell>221</cell>
                        <cell>18610</cell>
                        <cell>0.27</cell>
                        <cell>1904</cell>
                        <cell>0.22</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1991</cell>
                        <cell>258</cell>
                        <cell>54498</cell>
                        <cell>133</cell>
                        <cell>12627</cell>
                        <cell>0.23</cell>
                        <cell>3761</cell>
                        <cell>0.21</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1992</cell>
                        <cell>415</cell>
                        <cell>76544</cell>
                        <cell>225</cell>
                        <cell>26218</cell>
                        <cell>0.34</cell>
                        <cell>2557</cell>
                        <cell>0.31</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <p xml:id="p-45">Since the 1980s the number of speeches at individual sessions was
                     rising steadily, but then increased radically in 1990 (dissolution of the
                     state) and 1992 (swift adoption of new legislation). Simultaneously the number
                     of words spoken at individual sessions was increasing as well, especially after
                     1989. The Presidents spoke more often and longer. Even the number of words,
                     spoken during the discussion of individual items, increased. (Thus the
                     proportion between the number of words spoken at a single session and the
                     number of words spoken by the President remained relatively static.)</p>
                  <p xml:id="p-46">It seems that the political dynamics, felt all around Slovenia
                     and Yugoslavia, also found its way into the Assembly and characterised its
                     work: more was said there. On the basis of certain case studies we may also
                     conclude that gradually not only more was said, but also differently: the
                     language started changing and the reading of "reports" became rarer, while
                     political passion intensified.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="42">Gašparič
                        and Šorn, "Od tovariša delegata do gospoda poslanca," 37-47.</note> The
                     upgrading of the search tools in the context of the digitalisation of session
                     records, currently carried out at the Institute of Contemporary History, will
                     allow for a more advanced and temporally more comprehensive linguistic
                     research, not only regarding the quantitative characteristics, but also the
                     contents of what was said. The stated information is only partial, therefore
                     its representativeness is questionable.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="subchapter" xml:id="article-sub06">
               <head xml:id="head-17">Conclusion</head>
               <p xml:id="p-47">We can establish that the socialist Parliament on the eve of the
                  dissolution of Yugoslavia has not yet been explored in much detail. This is true
                  in case of the republican Assemblies as well as the Federal Assembly in Belgrade.
                  However – at least we can claim this for Slovenia – at this time the Assembly
                  underwent internal changes and, most notably, started adopting important
                  decisions: in the process of the dissolution of Yugoslav federalism it was a
                  constitutional and political factor which could not be ignored.</p>
               <p xml:id="p-48">We can partially agree that the Assembly (also) gained legitimacy by
                  steadily marching towards its end, although in this regard we should also add that
                  the legitimacy of the Assembly and trust in it by the people was encouraged at
                  least in the same degree (if not more so) by the threat that the people saw in
                  Belgrade. In 1989 the answers to the public opinion poll question "In the current
                  circumstances, what represents the greatest threat to the sovereignty of
                  Slovenia?" included especially the following three issues:</p>
               <list type="simple" xml:id="list-2">
                  <item>that "we have excessive economic responsibilities to the federation and the
                     underdeveloped";</item>
                  <item>that "the federal authorities are authoritarian in their rejection of
                     important Slovenian proposals";</item>
                  <item>and that "Slovenian political pluralism and democratisation was under attack
                     outside of Slovenia".</item>
               </list>
               <p xml:id="p-49">Therefore the Slovenian Assembly represented defence from the
                  Belgrade threat. This was reason enough why it was seen as a legitimate
                  representative body, a parliament with a purpose.</p>
               <p xml:id="p-50">The federal institutions, including the League of Communists of
                  Yugoslavia, were different: they were becoming an end in themselves.
                  Paradoxically, these institutions were able to persist precisely because of the
                  Slovenian Assembly and similar authority bodies, as the League of Communists of
                  Yugoslavia as well as other federal institutions justified their own existence at
                  least partially by responding to the decisions of the Slovenian Assembly. In
                  September 1989, during the adoption of the Slovenian constitutional amendments, a
                  motto wittily and evidently illustrating the logic of the Party sessions became
                  popular: "If you have problems, convene a session of the Central Committee. This
                  will result in even more problems, but at least you'll have a Central Committee
                     session."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="43">Rastko Močnik, "Paralogizmi
                     argumentov in logika institucije," <hi rend="italic">Telex</hi>, October 5,
                     1989.</note>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="p-51">The legitimacy of the federal authorities gradually disappeared
                  completely, and only a few Western countries saw the Federal Assembly and the
                  federal government of the reformist prime minister Ante Marković as a credible
                  party.</p>
               <p xml:id="p-52">In the meantime the credibility of the Slovenian Assembly kept
                  strengthening, especially after April 1990 when the first multi-party elections by
                  secret ballot were carried out for the first time after 1927. At that time the
                  Assembly was filled with delegates who, despite the existing constitution, called
                  themselves Members of Parliament, which was more appropriate for the new times.
                  The largest number of MPs came from new parties, but we should note that the
                  former League of Communists of Slovenia and the other former "socio-political
                  organisations" had a very good result as well. The latter can perhaps be
                  interpreted as an additional argument supporting the thesis that in the final
                  period the former Socialist Assembly was nevertheless a legitimate
                  "representative" institution, supported by the population. Finally, in 1991 people
                  in Slovenia believed that democracy in their republic was not very different from
                  the democracies in the Western European countries. They were probably wrong, but
                  still – they (at least partially) based this opinion on their experience with
                  their socialist Parliament, which was, comparatively speaking, the most positive
                  in the whole of Eastern Europe.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="44">
                     <hi rend="italic">Vrednote v prehodu VIII: Slovenija v srednje in
                        vzhodnoevropskih primerjavah</hi>, ed. Niko Toš (Ljubljana: Univerza v
                     Ljubljani, Fakulteta za družbene vede, IDV – CJMMK; Wien: Edition Echoraum,
                     2014), 334.</note>
               </p>
               <table xml:id="table-2" rend="table-scroll hover">
                  <head>Consolidation of Democracy in Central and Eastern Europe, 1991 / 1999</head>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell>Country</cell>
                     <cell>Year</cell>
                     <cell>Our State should develop like Western European Countries</cell>
                     <cell>In our State will never be possible to implement the true
                        Democracy</cell>
                     <cell>Democracy in our State is similar to democracies in Western European
                        countries</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">White Russia</cell>
                     <cell>1999</cell>
                     <cell>62.9</cell>
                     <cell>29.3</cell>
                     <cell>2.8</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="2" role="label">Bolgaria</cell>
                     <cell>1991</cell>
                     <cell>81.2</cell>
                     <cell>17.9</cell>
                     <cell>6.2</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1999</cell>
                     <cell>76.7</cell>
                     <cell>48.2</cell>
                     <cell>92.1</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="2" role="label">Czech Republic</cell>
                     <cell>1991</cell>
                     <cell>77.2</cell>
                     <cell>13.1</cell>
                     <cell>13.4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1999</cell>
                     <cell>76.0</cell>
                     <cell>30.0</cell>
                     <cell>16.3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="2" role="label">Estonia</cell>
                     <cell>1991</cell>
                     <cell>73.5</cell>
                     <cell>16.4</cell>
                     <cell>6.4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1999</cell>
                     <cell>69.3</cell>
                     <cell>18.1</cell>
                     <cell>28.2</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="2" role="label">East Germany</cell>
                     <cell>1991</cell>
                     <cell>80.2</cell>
                     <cell>21.4</cell>
                     <cell>30.2</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1999</cell>
                     <cell>82.8</cell>
                     <cell>21.5</cell>
                     <cell>58.7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">West Germany</cell>
                     <cell>1999</cell>
                     <cell>86.9</cell>
                     <cell>18.7</cell>
                     <cell>64.3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="2" role="label">Hungary</cell>
                     <cell>1991</cell>
                     <cell>94.8</cell>
                     <cell>20.7</cell>
                     <cell>7.6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1999</cell>
                     <cell>94.2</cell>
                     <cell>23.5</cell>
                     <cell>16.9</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Latvia</cell>
                     <cell>1999</cell>
                     <cell>58.5</cell>
                     <cell>14.9</cell>
                     <cell>8.5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="2" role="label">Lithuania</cell>
                     <cell>1991</cell>
                     <cell>86.2</cell>
                     <cell>20.7</cell>
                     <cell>10.7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1999</cell>
                     <cell>81.2</cell>
                     <cell>24.5</cell>
                     <cell>15.1</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="2" role="label">Poland</cell>
                     <cell>1991</cell>
                     <cell>97.1</cell>
                     <cell>31.3</cell>
                     <cell>16.5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1999</cell>
                     <cell>92.9</cell>
                     <cell>46.3</cell>
                     <cell>24.6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="2" role="label">Romania</cell>
                     <cell>1991</cell>
                     <cell>93.9</cell>
                     <cell>23.5</cell>
                     <cell>18.1</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1999</cell>
                     <cell>95.4</cell>
                     <cell>22.8</cell>
                     <cell>24.3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Russia</cell>
                     <cell>1999</cell>
                     <cell>34.0</cell>
                     <cell>35.6</cell>
                     <cell>10.0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="2" role="label">Slovakia</cell>
                     <cell>1991</cell>
                     <cell>67.2</cell>
                     <cell>15.8</cell>
                     <cell>12.2</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1999</cell>
                     <cell>73.5</cell>
                     <cell>40.3</cell>
                     <cell>10.8</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="2" role="label">Slovenia</cell>
                     <cell>1991</cell>
                     <cell>96.9</cell>
                     <cell>17.2</cell>
                     <cell>41.1</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1999</cell>
                     <cell>89.4</cell>
                     <cell>18.5</cell>
                     <cell>45.5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="2" role="label">Ukraine</cell>
                     <cell>1991</cell>
                     <cell>74.1</cell>
                     <cell>35.1</cell>
                     <cell>7.4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1999</cell>
                     <cell>66.1</cell>
                     <cell>44.7</cell>
                     <cell>3.9</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="bibliogr" xml:id="bibliogr">
            <head xml:id="head-19">Sources and references</head>
            <div type="subchapter" xml:id="bibliogr-sub01">
               <head xml:id="head-20">Literature</head>
               <listBibl xml:id="listBibl-1">
                  <bibl>Čepič, Zdenko. "Federaliziranje federacije 1967-1971." In <hi rend="italic"
                        >Slovenska novejša zgodovina: Od programa Zedinjena Slovenija do
                        mednarodnega priznanja Republike Slovenije: 1848−1992</hi>, edited by Jasna
                     Fischer et al., 1052−1054. Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Mladinska
                     knjiga, 2005.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Čepič, Zdenko. "Ustava 1974: preureditev jugoslovanske federacije,
                     delegatski sistem in dogovorna ekonomija." In <hi rend="italic">Slovenska
                        novejša zgodovina: Od programa Zedinjena Slovenija do mednarodnega priznanja
                        Republike Slovenije: 1848−1992</hi>, edited by Jasna Fischer et al.,
                     1094−1104. Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Mladinska knjiga,
                     2005.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Cohen, Lenard J. <hi rend="italic">Broken Bonds: The Disintegration of
                        Yugoslavia</hi>. Boulder, San Francisco, Oxford: Westview Press,
                     1993.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Gabrič, Aleš. "Opozicija v Sloveniji po letu 1945." <hi rend="italic"
                        >Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</hi> 45, no. 2 (2005): 97-120.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Gabrič, Aleš. "Prva slovenska ustava." In <hi rend="italic">Slovenska
                        novejša zgodovina: Od programa Zedinjena Slovenija do mednarodnega priznanja
                        Republike Slovenije: 1848−1992</hi>, edited by Jasna Fischer et al.,
                     867−868. Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Mladinska knjiga,
                     2005.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Gabrič, Aleš. "Volitve v Ustavodajno skupščino novembra 1945." In <hi
                        rend="italic">Slovenska novejša zgodovina: Od programa Zedinjena Slovenija
                        do mednarodnega priznanja Republike Slovenije: 1848−1992</hi>, edited by
                     Jasna Fischer et al., 854-858. Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino,
                     Mladinska knjiga, 2005.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Gašparič, Jure and Mojca Šorn. "Od tovariša delegata do gospoda poslanca: O
                     razpravi v socialistični enostrankarski skupščini in demokratičnem
                     tranzicijskem parlamentu v Sloveniji." <hi rend="italic">Prispevki za novejšo
                        zgodovino</hi> 54, no. 1 (2014): 37-47.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Gašparič, Jure.<hi rend="italic"> Državni zbor Republike Slovenije
                        1992-2012: O slovenskem parlamentarizmu</hi>. Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo
                     zgodovino, 2012.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Gašparič, Jure. <hi rend="italic">SLS pod kraljevo diktaturo: Diktatura
                        kralja Aleksandra in politika Slovenske ljudske stranke 1929-1935</hi>.
                     Ljubljana: Modrijan, 2007.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Hayden, Robert M. <hi rend="italic">Blueprints for a House Divided: The
                        Constitutional Logic of the Yugoslav Conflicts</hi>. Ann Arbor: The
                     University of Michigan Press, 2000.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Lusa, Stefano.<hi rend="italic"> Razkroj oblasti: Slovenski komunisti in
                        demokratizacija države</hi>. Ljubljana: Modrijan, 2012. </bibl>
                  <bibl>Maier, Viktor. <hi rend="italic">Wie Jugoslawien verspielt wurde</hi>.
                     München: C. H. Beck, 1995.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Pesek, Rosvita.<hi rend="italic"> Osamosvojitev Slovenije: "Ali naj
                        Republika Slovenija postane samostojna in neodvisna država?."</hi>
                     Ljubljana: Nova revija, 2007.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Pleterski, Janko. "O soslednosti novejše zgodovine Slovencev: Nekaj pripomb
                     ob in k posvetu Slovenci in leto 1941." <hi rend="italic">Prispevki za novejšo
                        zgodovino</hi> 43, no. 1 (2003): 103-124.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Potrč, Miran. "Za prvo demokratično izvoljeno Skupščino Republike Slovenije
                     je dala zakonsko podlago zakonodaja, sprejeta 27. 12. 1989 v Skupščini
                     Socialistične Republike Slovenije." In <hi rend="italic">Prihodnost
                        parlamentarne demokracije: Zbornik strokovnega srečanja ob 20. obletnici
                        prvih večstrankarskih volitev</hi>, edited by Tatjana Krašovec, and Mojca
                     Pristavec Đogić, 26-32. Ljubljana: Državni zbor Republike Slovenije,
                     2010.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Potrč, Miran. <hi rend="italic">Klic k razumu: spomini</hi>. Ljubljana:
                     Modrijan, 2014.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Ramet, Sabrina P. <hi rend="italic">The Three Yugoslavias: State-Building
                        and legitimation, 1918-2005</hi>. Washington D. C.: Woodrow Wilson Center
                     Press, 2005.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Repe, Božo. "Pravne in politične podlage, okoliščine in pomen prvih
                     demokratičnih volitev." In <hi rend="italic">Razvoj slovenskega
                        parlamentarizma: Kolokvij ob 10. obletnici parlamentarizma v Sloveniji:
                        Zbornik referatov, koreferatov in razprav</hi>, edited by Tatjana Krašovec,
                     26-69. Ljubljana: Državni zbor Republike Slovenije, 2000.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Repe, Božo.<hi rend="italic"> Jutri je nov dan: Slovenci in razpad
                        Jugoslavije</hi>. Ljubljana: Modrijan, 2002.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Repe, Božo.<hi rend="italic"> Rdeča Slovenija: Tokovi in obrazi iz obdobja
                        socializma</hi>. Ljubljana: Sophia, 2003.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Režek, Mateja. "Na pragu reform." In <hi rend="italic">Slovenska novejša
                        zgodovina: Od programa Zedinjena Slovenija do mednarodnega priznanja
                        Republike Slovenije: 1848−1992</hi>, edited by Jasna Fischer et al.,
                     998−999. Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Mladinska knjiga,
                     2005.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Režek, Mateja. "Ustava reforma leta 1953." In <hi rend="italic">Slovenska
                        novejša zgodovina: Od programa Zedinjena Slovenija do mednarodnega priznanja
                        Republike Slovenije: 1848−1992</hi>, edited by Jasna Fischer et al.,
                     950−952. Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Mladinska knjiga,
                     2005.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Ribarič, Miha.<hi rend="italic"> Spomini: Slovenija – Jugoslavija</hi>.
                     Ljubljana: Fakulteta za družbene vede, 2015.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Ribičič, Ciril.<hi rend="italic"> Siva tipka 074</hi>. Ljubljana: Enotnost,
                     1995.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Vodopivec, Peter. "Komunistične skupščine v senci partije." In <hi
                        rend="italic">Analiza razvoja slovenskega parlamentarizma</hi>, edited by
                     Barbara Vogrinec, 258-297. Ljubljana: Inštitut za civilizacijo in kulturo,
                     2005.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Vodušek Starič, Jerca. <hi rend="italic">Prevzem oblasti</hi>. Ljubljana:
                     Cankarjeva založba, 1992.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Woodward, Susan L. <hi rend="italic">Balkan Tragedy: Chaos and Dissolution
                        after the Cold War</hi>. Washington D. C.: The Brookings Institution,
                     1995.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Vykoukal, Jiří, Bohuslav Litera, and Miroslav Tejchman. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Východ: Vznik, vývoj a rozpad sovětského bloku 1944−1989</hi>. Praha:
                     Libri, 2000.</bibl>
               </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="subchapter" xml:id="bibliogr-sub02">
               <head xml:id="head-21">Newspaper sources</head>
               <listBibl xml:id="listBibl-2">
                  <bibl>
                     <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>. "Slovenska ustava stremi k svobodi in kreativnosti
                     ljudi." September 28, 1989.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Gaber, Slavko. "Skupščina komunistov se odpravi."<hi rend="italic">
                        Telex</hi>, October 26, 1989.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Močnik, Rastko. "Paralogizmi argumentov in logika institucije." <hi
                        rend="italic">Telex</hi>, October 5, 1989.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Slivnik, Danilo. "Po meri Slovencev."<hi rend="italic"> Delo</hi>, September
                     28, 1989.</bibl>
               </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="subchapter" xml:id="bibliogr-sub03">
               <head xml:id="head-22">Sources (oral, legal, databases)</head>
               <listBibl xml:id="listBibl-3">
                  <bibl>Toš, Niko et al. <hi rend="italic">Slovensko javno mnenje 1986
                        [database]</hi>. Ljubljana: Univerza Edvarda Kardelja, Fakulteta za
                     sociologijo, politične vede in novinarstvo, Center za raziskovanje javnega
                     mnenja in množičnih komunikacij [creation], 1986; Ljubljana: Univerza v
                     Ljubljani, Fakulteta za družbene vede, Arhiv družboslovnih podatkov
                     [distribution], 1999.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Toš, Niko et al. <hi rend="italic">Slovensko javno mnenje 1989: Stališča o
                        ustavnih dopolnilih [database]</hi>. Ljubljana: Univerza Edvarda Kardelja,
                     Fakulteta za sociologijo, politične vede in novinarstvo, Center za raziskovanje
                     javnega mnenja in množičnih komunikacij [creation], 1989; Ljubljana: Univerza v
                     Ljubljani, Fakulteta za družbene vede, Arhiv družboslovnih podatkov
                     [distribution], 1999.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi rend="italic">Ustava Socialistične republike Slovenije</hi>.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi rend="italic">Vrednote v prehodu VIII: Slovenija v srednje in
                        vzhodnoevropskih primerjavah</hi>, edited by Niko Toš. Ljubljana: Univerza v
                     Ljubljani, Fakulteta za družbene vede, IDV – CJMMK; Wien: Edition Echoraum,
                     2014.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi rend="italic">Zakon o volitvah in delegiranju v skupščine: Zakon o volitvah
                        in odpoklicu Predsedstva Socialistične republike Slovenije s pojasnili
                        Cirila Ribičiča in Franca Grada</hi>. Ljubljana: ČZ Uradni list SRS,
                     1985.</bibl>
               </listBibl>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="summary" xml:id="summary" xml:lang="sl">
            <head xml:id="head-24">Povzetek</head>
            <head type="main" xml:id="head-23" rend="subtitle">Slovenski socialistični parlament na predvečer
               razpada jugoslovanske federacije – bledo "ratafikacijsko telo" ali važen političen
               odločevalec?</head>
            <docAuthor xml:id="docAuthor-2">Jure Gašparič</docAuthor>
            <p xml:id="p-53">Avtor ugotavlja, da socialističnemu parlamentu na predvečer razpada
               Jugoslavije doslej ni bilo posvečene veliko raziskovalne pozornosti; to velja tako za
               republiške skupščine kakor za zvezno skupščino v Beogradu. Toda (to lahko trdimo za
               Slovenijo) skupščina je v tem času doživljala notranje spremembe in zlasti sprejemala
               važne odločitve; v procesu razgradnje jugoslovanskega federalizma je bila ustavni in
               politični faktor, ki ga ni bilo mogoče zaobiti. Slovenska skupščina je tako med
               drugim septembra 1989 sprejela številne ustavne amandmaje k republiški ustavi, ki so
               uvedli večstrankarski sistem, elemente tržnega gospodarstva in okrepili položaj
               republike. Zdi se, da je nenadoma postala prvi in odločilni politični faktor. Toda
               take ocene republiške skupščine ni nikjer najti. Ob zapleteni sestavi, ki je
               temeljila v delegatskem sistemu iz leta 1974, ostaja skupščina precej zagoneten
               faktor zgodnje tranzicije. Izhajajoč iz tega se zato avtor v prispevku sprašuje,
               kakšen organ je skupščina sploh bila? Pri tem najprej predstavi genezo
               jugoslovanskega skupščinskega sistema in njegove temeljne značilnosti, nato pa
               obravnava tri različne ravni oz. možne poglede na skupščino. Najprej pravno raven,
               kjer ugotavlja, da je skupščina imela vse sistemske pogoje za to, da dejansko
               opravlja važno politično vlogo v sistemu. Brez njenega angažmaja politične spremembe
               ne bi bile mogoče, vsaj ne po ustavni poti, ki je bila značilna za slovenski
               osamosvojitveni proces in prvo fazo politične tranzicije. Nato analizira raven
               dojemanja skupščine med prebivalstvom, kjer meni, da je skupščina septembra 1989
               dejansko bila predstavniško telo, udejanjala je politično voljo prebivalstva. Ob
               koncu se loti še ravni notranjih mehanizmov, saj s pomočjo orodij digitalne
               humanistike pogleda nekatere kvantitativne kazalce parlamentarne razprave. Iz teh se
               vidi, da je politična dinamika, ki jo je bilo čutiti povsod po Sloveniji in
               Jugoslaviji, zašla tudi v skupščino in zaznamovala njeno delo – govorilo se je
               več.</p>
            <p xml:id="p-54">Skupščina je torej tedaj bila legitimno telo, a je vprašanje, s čim je
               svojo legitimiteto pridobivala. Po eni strani vsaj deloma s korakanjem k svojemu
               koncu, s sprejemanjem sklepov, ki so pomenili spodkopavanje sistema. Toda po drugi
               strani je bržkone njeno legitimiteto in zaupanje med ljudmi vsaj v enaki meri (če ne
               večji) dvigala grožnja, ki so jo ljudje videli v Beogradu. Z institucijami
               federacije, vključno z Zvezo komunistov Jugoslavije, je bila situacija drugačna, vse
               bolj so bile same sebi namen. Njihova legitimnosti je sčasoma povsem usahnila.
               Kredibilnost slovenske skupščine se je medtem le še krepila, zlasti po aprilu 1990,
               ko so bile prvič po letu 1927 izvedene večstrankarske in tajne volitve. V skupščino
               so tedaj sedli delegati, ki so se navkljub veljavni ustavi novim časom primerno
               nazivali z izrazom poslanci. Med njimi je bil največ članov novih strank, a velja
               opaziti, da je tudi nekdanja Zveza komunistov Slovenije z drugimi bivšimi
               družbeno-političnimi organizacijami osvojila zelo dober rezultat. Slednje morda lahko
               interpretiramo kot dodaten argument, ki govori v prid tezi, da je bila bivša
               socialistična skupščina v zadnjem obdobju vendarle legitimna "predstavniška"
               ustanova, blizu prebivalstvu.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
