<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en" xml:id="ojs-120">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a">Changing Dynamics of Democratic Parliamentary Arena in
                    Slovenia</title>
                <title level="a">Voters, Parties, Elections</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Simona</forename>
                        <surname>Kustec</surname>
                        <surname>Lipicer</surname>
                    </name>
                    <roleName>Associate Professor and researcher</roleName>
                    <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Faculty of Social sciences, University of Ljubljana</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kardeljeva pl. 5</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Slovenia</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>simona.kustec-lipicer@fdv.uni-lj.si</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Andrija</forename>
                        <surname>Henjak</surname>
                    </name>
                    <roleName>Assistant Professor</roleName>
                    <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Faculty of Political Sciences</affiliation>
                    <affiliation>University of Zagreb</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Lepušićeva ul. 6</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>10000 Zagreb</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Croatia</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>ahenjak@fpzg.hr</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2015-12-08</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/120</pubPlace>
                <date>2015</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="PID">sistory.36119</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>parliament</term>
                    <term>political parties</term>
                    <term>democracy</term>
                    <term>Republic of Slovenia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>parlament</term>
                    <term>politične stranke</term>
                    <term>demokracija</term>
                    <term>Republika Slovenija</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2015-12-09</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en" type="article" n="Articles">
        <front>
            <titlePage>
                <docAuthor>Simona Kustec Lipicer</docAuthor>
                <docAuthor>Andrija Henjak</docAuthor>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart>Changing Dynamics of Democratic Parliamentary Arena in
                        Slovenia</titlePart>
                    <titlePart>Voters, Parties, Elections</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <docImprint>
                    <idno type="cobissType">1.01</idno>
                    <idno type="UDC">328:340.134(497.4)"1991/2014"</idno>
                </docImprint>
            </titlePage>
            <divGen type="toc" xml:id="ojs-120-toc">
                <head>Table of Contents</head>
            </divGen>
            <divGen type="toc" xml:id="ojs-120-images">
                <head>List of Images</head>
            </divGen>
            <divGen type="toc" xml:id="ojs-120-tables">
                <head>List of Tables</head>
            </divGen>
            <divGen type="search" xml:id="ojs-120-search">
                <head>Search</head>
            </divGen>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl" xml:id="ojs-120-izvlecek">
                <head xml:id="ojs-120-head-1">Izvleček</head>
                <head rend="subtitle" xml:id="ojs-120-head-2">Spreminjajoča se dinamika slovenske
                    demokratične parlamentarne arene: Volivci, stranke, volitve</head>
                <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-6">Glavni namen članka je podati deskritptivni analitični
                    pregled in ocene dosedanjega razvoja slovenske parlamentarne arene od prehoda v
                    demokracijo do današnjih dni. Članek je razdeljen na dva dela: (1) pregled
                    normativnih podlag parlamentarnega in strankarskega delovanja, in (2) analitične
                    ocene strukture parlamentarne arene, kot jo odražajo volilne ter strankarske
                    izbire in politične ponudbe. Vpogled v sodobno demokratično parlamentarno areno
                    v Sloveniji kaže, da je ta dokaj stabilna, a da ob naraščajočem nezaupanju in
                    spreminjajoči se volilni podpori politične stranke kot sestavni deli
                    parlamentarne arene posebej v drugem desetletju demokracije postajajo manj
                    stabilne, njihovo delovanje pa tudi manj predvidljivo, kar ima posledično lahko
                    vpliv tudi na prihodnjo stabilnost same parlamentarne arene.</p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-7">Ključne besede: parlament, politične stranke, demokracija,
                    Republika Slovenija</p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract" xml:id="ojs-120-abstract">
                <head xml:id="ojs-120-head-3">Abstract</head>
                <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-8">The main goal of this paper is to provide a descriptive
                    analytical overview of the existing evolution of the Slovenian parliamentary
                    arena since its transition to democracy and independence. The paper is divided
                    into two main parts: (1) an overview of a normative insight into the
                    parliamentary and party system, and (2) an analytical assessment of the
                    structure of the parliamentary arena as it is reflected in electoral and
                    parties’ choices and policy preferences. A look at the contemporary democratic
                    parliamentary arena in Slovenia shows that it, in itself, has been quite stable,
                    while, on the contrary, its main integral parts – political parties – have
                    gradually become less stable and less predictable, especially in the second
                    decade of democracy, which can potentially influence the future stability of
                    parliamentary arena, too.</p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-9">Keywords: parliament, political parties, democracy, Republic
                    of Slovenia</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="chapter" xml:id="ojs-120-article">
                <head xml:id="ojs-120-head-4">Changing Dynamics of Democratic Parliamentary Arena in
                    Slovenia</head>
                <head rend="subtitle" xml:id="ojs-120-head-5">Voters, Parties, Elections</head>
                <docAuthor xml:id="ojs-120-docAuthor-3">Simona Kustec Lipicer<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ojs-120-ftn1" n="*">Associate Professor and researcher, PhD, Faculty
                        of Social sciences, University of Ljubljana, Kardeljeva pl. 5, 1000
                        Ljubljana, Slovenia, <ref
                            target="mailto:simona.kustec-lipicer@fdv.uni-lj.si"
                            >simona.kustec-lipicer@fdv.uni-lj.si</ref>
                    </note>
                </docAuthor>
                <docAuthor xml:id="ojs-120-docAuthor-4">Andrija Henjak<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ojs-120-ftn2" n="**">Assistant Professor, PhD, Faculty of Political
                        Sciences, University of Zagreb, Lepušićeva ul. 6, 10000 Zagreb, Croatia,
                            <ref target="mailto:ahenjak@fpzg.hr">ahenjak@fpzg.hr</ref>
                    </note>
                </docAuthor>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-120-articel-sub01">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-120-head-6">Main Characteristics of the Slovenian Party
                        System</head>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-10">Slovenia is a country without a long tradition of
                        statehood. It has had its current borders since 1945, when it was
                        constituted as a federal republic of the socialist Yugoslavia. Slovenia
                        became independent at the same time as it transformed into a democracy: with
                        the collapse of communism and disintegration of Yugoslavia in 1991. As the
                        most developed of Yugoslav republics – with the most advanced economy,
                        already well integrated in the West European markets, and ethnically the
                        most homogenous of the former Yugoslav federal republics – the Slovenian
                        transition to democracy was both smooth and quick. The process was only
                        interrupted by a brief but intense war at the end of June 1991, resulting
                        from the intervention of the federal army, which tried to prevent the
                        inevitable process of the Yugoslav breakup.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-120-ftn3" n="1">Niko Toš and Vlado Miheljak, "Transition in
                            Slovenia: Towards Democratization and the Attainment of Sovereignty," in
                                <hi rend="italic">Slovenia Between continuity and change
                                1990–1997</hi>, ed. Niko Toš and Vlado Miheljak (Berlin: Sigma,
                            2002).</note> Like in other post-socialist countries, political parties
                        in Slovenia played a crucial role as proponents of change in the transition
                        process from the former communist regime, which has been labelled as
                            transplaced<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn4" n="2">Samuel P.
                            Huntington, <hi rend="italic">The Third Wave: Democratization in the
                                late twentieth century</hi> (London: Univeristy of Oklahoma Press,
                            1991).</note> or ruptforma<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn5" n="3"
                            >Juan Linz, "The Breakdown of Democratic Regimes: Crisis," in <hi
                                rend="italic">Breakdown and Reequilibration,</hi> ed. Juan Linz and
                            Alfred Stepan (Baltimore: John Hopkins University Press, 1978).</note>
                        form of transition. The Slovenian transition was characterised by the
                        cooperation and bargaining between the emerging civil society and new social
                        movements, newly emerging opposition political parties, and existing
                        political elites.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn6" n="4">Danica
                            Fink-Hafner, "Between continuity and change," in <hi rend="italic"
                                >Slovenia Between Continuity and Change 1990–1997</hi>, ed. Niko Toš
                            and Vlado Miheljak (Berlin: Sigma, 2002).</note> As assessed by
                            Fink-Hafner,<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn7" n="5"> Ibid.,
                            43.</note> political parties became the agents of the formation of the
                        Slovenian state,<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn8" n="6">Janko Prunk,
                            "Politično življenje v samostojni Sloveniji," in <hi rend="italic"
                                >Dvajset let slovenske države</hi>, ed. Janko Prunk and Tomaž
                            Deželan (Maribor: Aristej; Ljubljana: Fakulteta za družbene vede, Center
                            za politološke raziskave, Ljubljana 2012), 17–57.</note> but they were
                        also shaped by this process. Some new parties emerged from the
                        transformation of the League of Communists of Slovenia (in 1993 renamed as
                        the United List of Social Democrats, and in 2005 as Social Democrats); the
                        League of Socialist Youth (later the Liberal Democracy of Slovenia); the
                        Socialist League of the Working People (later renamed as the Socialist
                        Alliance); and the Social Democratic League (later renamed as the Social
                        Democratic Party of Slovenia). Simultaneously the opposition to the old
                        regime, emerging from the society, first called the Alliance of
                        Intellectuals and later renamed as the Slovenian Democratic Alliance/Union,
                        was established at the end of the 1980s. Since then it has served as a base
                        for the foundation of a number of political parties. It included social
                        groups with specific issues at heart, such as religious groups (Slovenian
                        Christian Democrats; Christian Socialists), peasants (the Slovenian Peasant
                        Party - People’s Party, later renamed as the Slovenian People’s Party),
                        pensioners (the Democratic Party of Pensioners), regional parties (e.g. the
                        Alliance of Haloze, Alliance for Primorska, Party of Slovenian Štajerska),
                        and ethnic interests (e.g. the Alliance of Roma, Communita Italiana).
                        Certain other contemporary issue‑oriented social movements of that period,
                        such as the Greens of Slovenia, also evolved into parties.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-11">Out of these parties, the Democratic Opposition of
                        Slovenia, also known as the DEMOS coalition, was created through an
                        agreement between the <ref
                            target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slovenian_Democratic_Union"
                            >Slovenian Democratic Union</ref>, the <ref
                            target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slovenian_Democratic_Party">Social
                            Democrat Alliance of Slovenia</ref>, the <ref
                            target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slovene_Christian_Democrats"
                            >Slovene Christian Democrats</ref>, the <ref
                            target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slovenian_People%27s_Party">Peasant
                            Alliance</ref> and the <ref
                            target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greens_of_Slovenia">Greens of
                            Slovenia</ref>. In 1992 the Slovenian Democratic Union split into two
                        parties: the social-liberal wing became the <ref
                            target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Democratic_Party_(Slovenia)"
                            >Democratic Party</ref>, and the <ref
                            target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conservatism">conservative</ref>
                        faction established the <ref
                            target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Democratic_Party_(Slovenia)"
                            >National Democratic Party</ref>. A third group, dissatisfied with both
                        options, joined the Social Democratic Party (SDSS, later simplified to SDS),
                        which suffered a clear defeat at the 1992 elections, barely securing its
                        entry in the <ref
                            target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slovenian_National_Assembly"
                            >Parliament</ref>. Nevertheless, it formed a coalition with the winning
                            <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liberal_Democracy_of_Slovenia"
                            >Liberal Democracy of Slovenia</ref> and even became a member of the
                        governing coalition. Later it became the dominant party of the right of
                        center under the name of Slovenian Democratic Party.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-12">Only those socio-political organisations from the old
                        regime that successfully transformed themselves, as well as new formations
                        which managed to establish clear political identities and organisations,
                        were able to survive the transition processes and constitute the new
                        democratic party system. The successful parties generally managed to create
                        a widespread organisation in the field, while at the same time maintaining a
                        strong central party organisation and a high degree of party unity – all of
                        this despite the lack of politically experienced members and with only
                        limited financial resources. All other parties, including those with strong
                        international support, vanished from the public life almost overnight.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn9" n="7">Fink-Hafner, "Between
                            continuity and change," 48.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-13">In its first two decades, the party system of Slovenia
                        was characterised by the relative openness, allowing for a relatively easy
                        entry of new parties. However, at the same time it exhibited a high degree
                        of party stability, with parties creating stable organisations, membership
                        bases and political identities. At the level of interparty competition, the
                        party system was initially characterised by the dominance of Liberal
                        Democracy of Slovenia (LDS). This was followed by the increasing bipolarity,
                        with one end dominated initially by the LDS and then a succession of three
                        other, often new parties; while the other end has become increasingly
                        dominated by the Slovenian Democratic Party (SDS).<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-120-ftn10" n="8">For more information about the
                            characteristics of the Slovenian political parties since 1990 see Danica
                            Fink-Hafner, "Strankarski sistem v Sloveniji: Od prikrite k
                            transparentni bipolarnosti," in <hi rend="italic">Političke stranke i
                                birači u državama bivše Jugoslavije,</hi> ed. Zoran Lutovac
                            (Beograd: Friderich Ebert Stiftung, 2006), 363–384. Danica Fink-Hafner,
                            "Slovenia: Between Bipolarity and Broad Coalition-Building," in <hi
                                rend="italic">Post-Communist EU Member States: Parties and Party
                                Systems,</hi> ed. Susanne Jungerstam-Mulders (Aldershot, Burlington:
                            Ashgate, 2006), 203–231.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-14">Despite the relative openness of the Slovenian party
                        system, only a small number of new parties entered the Slovenian Parliament
                        in the first two decades. This trend started to change at the 2008
                        parliamentary elections, with the rapid decline of the LDS, strengthening of
                        the SD as the temporary strongest party on the left, and the entry of a new
                        party splintering from the LDS into the Parliament (Zares). At the 2011 and
                        2014 elections the instability of party systems reached new heights, with
                        the once dominant LDS almost completely disappearing from the scene, being
                        supplanted on the broad left first by the SD, then by the Positive Slovenia,
                        and finally by the Miro Cerar's Party, later renamed as the Modern Centre
                        Party. This opened a new trend of single-term parties, emerging and
                        disappearing from one election to the next, leading to a huge turnover in
                        the Parliament. Despite the increasing instability, no anti-system parties
                        have emerged in Slovenia, although some parties have occasionally challenged
                        the legitimacy of the ruling political elite and called for its replacement
                        at early elections.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn11" n="9">Jure
                            Gašparič, <hi rend="italic">Državni zbor 1992-2012: o slovenskem
                                parlamentarizmu</hi> (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino,
                            2012). Danica Fink-Hafner, Damjan Lajh and Alenka Krašovec, <hi
                                rend="italic">Politika na območju nekdanje Jugoslavije</hi>
                            (Ljubljana: Fakulteta za družbene vede, 2005).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-15">Generally we can state that political parties in
                        Slovenia are not based on the representation and advocacy of narrow
                            interests<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn12" n="10">In contrast to
                            most EU countries, "actual" Eurosceptic parties cannot be detected in
                            Slovenia. In the period of the Slovenian integration into the EU the
                            parliamentary Slovenian National Party was characterised as a
                            "Eurosceptic" party. However, during, for example, the campaign for the
                            referendum on the Slovenian accession to the EU it remained completely
                            inactive and inconspicuous.</note> (e.g. individual social classes,
                        interest groups, regions, etc...) and cannot be distinguished easily
                        according to the standard understanding of the left and right wing,
                        primarily based on the economic or social issues. For the most part,
                        Slovenian parties aim to be "catch-all" organisations, as their programmes
                        and appeals address a wide range of voters with varying concerns. This is
                        also true in case of the rare parliamentary “interest-group parties” such as
                        the DESUS. However, for the most of the time since multiparty democracy was
                        established, the principal political parties did possess a clear political
                        identity and identifiable, if not always permanently loyal, electoral base.
                        Additionally, we should also note that in the past the parties which have
                        shown a narrower focus on the specific issues and policies were not
                        electorally successful in the long term, and the Green parties in the
                        nineties are a typical example of this.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-120-articel-sub02">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-120-head-7">Legal and Financial Frameworks for a Transparent
                        Functioning of Political Parties in Slovenia</head>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-16">In accordance with the Political Parties Act, a
                        political party in Slovenia is defined as "<hi rend="italic">an association
                            of citizens who pursue their political goals as adopted in the party's
                            programme through the democratic formulation of the political will of
                            the citizens and by proposing candidates for elections to the National
                            Assembly, elections for the president of the republic and for elections
                            to local community bodies</hi>."<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-120-ftn13" n="11">"Political Party Act. Official
                            consolidated text," <hi rend="italic">Official Gazette of the RS</hi>,
                            no. 100 (2005): art. 1.</note> The <hi rend="long_text">Slovenian
                            Constitution itself does not define neither political parties nor their
                            functioning, but it provides for the individuals' right to freely
                            associate with others, maintaining certain legal limitations on that
                            right if required by the national security, public safety, and
                            protection against the spread of infectious diseases.</hi>
                        <note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn14" n="12">
                            <hi rend="italic">Constitution of the Republic of Slovenia</hi>, art.
                            42.</note> Political parties are regulated by the Political Parties Act
                        and the Elections and Referendum Campaign Act. A party may be founded by no
                        less than 200 adult citizens of the Republic of Slovenia who sign a
                        declaration on the founding of the party. A party becomes a legal entity and
                        shall act in accordance with the Slovenian laws after the registration body
                        (Ministry of the Interior) marks the application of a party (for the entry
                        in the register) with the time and date when the application was received.
                        Each party must add to the application for entry in the register a) 200
                        founding signatures, b) the party statute and its program, c) a record of
                        the founding assembly, meeting or congress, naming the elected bodies of the
                        parties and the office-holder who, in accordance with the statute,
                        represents the party as the responsible person, d) a graphic representation
                        of the symbol of the party.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn15" n="13"
                            >Ibid., art. 8.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-17">In terms of internal democratic governance, all the
                        main political parties must establish rules for the election of its
                        leadership, the selection of candidates for elections, and the
                        decision-making processes of the party’s programme platforms. There are also
                        certain legal restrictions with regard to persons who cannot become party
                        members or representatives in the leadership bodies of political parties.
                        However, at the same time no demand for the public availability of the
                        membership information is defined.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn16"
                            n="14">"Political Party Act. Official consolidated text," <hi
                                rend="italic">Official Gazette of the RS</hi>, no. 100
                            (2005).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-18">In terms of resources parties mostly rely on public
                        funds, while privately provided funding has a smaller role. Legally,
                        political parties in Slovenia can obtain funds from membership fees,
                        contributions from private or legal persons, income from property, gifts,
                        requests, the budget (national or local), and profit from the income of a
                        company owned by it, but not from international funds or any type of
                        domestic organisations with public ownership of at least 50 percent.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn17" n="15">"Political Party Act.
                            Official consolidated text," <hi rend="italic">Official Gazette of the
                                RS</hi>, no. 100 (2005): art. 21 and 26. See also Article 22 for
                            certain criteria and limitations that are set for obtaining the stated
                            for the acquisition of the relevant eligible funds.</note> The most
                        frequent and most ‘welcome’ party financial contribution by far comes from
                        the national budget. Parties that propose candidates for the elections to
                        the National Assembly have the right to receive funds from the national
                        budget, provided that they received at least 1 percent (or 1.2 % if two
                        parties compete on a joint list; or 1.5 % if three or more compete together
                        on one list) of votes nationwide. The amount of the public funds available
                        to the political parties depends on the electoral result. It should also be
                        noted that the political parties which are represented in the National
                        Assembly are entitled to other "indirect" (financial, personnel,
                        administrative) resources, which they receive from the National Assembly
                        budget. It should be noted that although a 4-percent threshold is set at the
                        national level as the level of eligibility for the reception of public
                        funds, there are also some non-parliamentary parties – those which received
                        more than one percent or less than four percent of the votes of voters at
                        the national level – which are also entitled to public funding. In light of
                        all of the above, in practice this means that Slovenian parliamentary
                        parties receive a substantial portion of their resources from the budget
                        (national and municipal), and only a moderate amount from membership fees
                        and donations.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-19">However the issues with regard to the integrity of
                        political parties, especially with regard to the transparency of party
                        membership and funding, as well as issues related to the assurance of
                        effective control over funding have been on the agenda almost constantly
                        ever since the Slovenian independence. Political parties frequently, mostly
                        on their own initiative, fail to inform the public about their membership,
                        democratic governance procedures, as well as financial management. In light
                        of the loose legal regulations, the general public therefore only has few
                        limited possibilities to gain direct access to the information about the
                        activities of the parties.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn18" n="16"
                            >Supervision is carried out by the Ministry of Interior and the Ministry
                            of Finance, while financial auditing control is assured by the Court of
                            Audit. For more information see also "Political Party Act. Official
                            consolidated text," <hi rend="italic">Official Gazette of the RS</hi>,
                            no. 100 (2005): art. 27–29.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-20">All these factors result in significant distrust
                        towards political parties, facilitating the search for new but not actually
                        innovative party choices in the increasing bipolarity of the multi-party
                        system, maintained not only by the voters’ choices, but also through the
                        media representation of the political parties and their actions.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn19" n="17">For media reports see: <hi
                                rend="italic">Delo</hi>, accessed December 3, 2015, <ref
                                target="http://www.delo.si">www.delo.si</ref>. <hi rend="italic"
                                >Dnevnik</hi>, accessed December 3, 2015, <ref
                                target="http://www.dnevnik.si">www.dnevnik.si</ref>. <hi
                                rend="italic">Večer</hi>, accessed December 3, 2015, <ref
                                target="http://www.vecer.si">www.vecer.si</ref>. <hi rend="italic"
                                >Prvi interaktivni multimedijski portal, MMC RTV Slovenija</hi>,
                            accessed December 3, 2015, <ref target="http://www.rtvslo.si"
                                >www.rtvslo.si</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Planet Siol.net</hi>,
                            accessed December 3, 2015, <ref target="http://www.siol.net"
                                >www.siol.net</ref>. <hi rend="italic">MLADINA.si</hi> , accessed
                            December 3, 2015, <ref target="http://www.mladina.si"
                                >www.mladina.si</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Revija Reporter</hi>,
                            accessed December 3, 2015, <ref target="http://www.reporter.si"
                                >www.reporter.si</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Tednik Demokracija</hi>,
                            accessed December 3, 2015, <ref target="http://www.demokracija.si"
                                >www.demokracija.si</ref>. See also Greco country monitoring reports
                            at: <hi rend="italic">Untitled 1</hi>, accessed December 3, 2015, <ref
                                target="http://www.coe.int/t/dghl/monitoring/greco/default_en.asp"
                                >http://www.coe.int/t/dghl/monitoring/greco/default_en.asp</ref>.
                        </note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-120-articel-sub03">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-120-head-8">Parties in the Party System</head>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-21">In the second half of 2015, there were 84 registered
                        political parties in Slovenia, which is an increase from the 74 parties
                        which were registered in 2012.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn20"
                            n="18">Ministry of Interior, Political Party Register, at <hi
                                rend="italic">Društva, politične stranke in ustanove - objave na
                                spletu</hi>, <ref
                                target="http://mrrsp.gov.si/rdruobjave/ps/index.faces"
                                >http://mrrsp.gov.si/rdruobjave/ps/index.faces</ref>.</note> Seven
                        of these are represented in the National Assembly, which is about the
                        average number of political parties represented in the National Assembly
                        after the 1992 elections. So far, on average, one third of all parties
                        competing in the elections have successfully entered the Parliament.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn21" n="19">No. of all competeing parties
                            in the period 1992–2014, divided with the number of parties, elected in
                            the Parliamnet in the period 1992–2014.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-22">Regarding the number of party members in Slovenia we
                        can only give a rough estimate, as it is very difficult to obtain credible
                        information from the parties. According to some estimates,<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-120-ftn22" n="20">Ingrid van Biezen, Peter Mair and Thomas
                            Poguntke, "Going, Going…Gone? Party Membership in the 21<hi
                                rend="superscript">st</hi> Century," paper prepared for the workshop
                            on ‘Political Parties and Civil Society’, ECPR Joint Sessions, Lisbon,
                            April 2009.</note> in 2008 108,000 people were members of political
                        parties in Slovenia, which represents 6.26 percent of the Slovenian
                        electorate. In comparison with the number in 1998, when members of the
                        parties represented 9.86 percent of the electorate, in 2008 the membership
                        in political parties decreased approximately by 3.5 percentage points.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn23" n="21">Ibid.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-23">If we compare the number of parties competing at the
                        national parliamentary elections in Slovenia between 1990 and 2014, we can
                        see that the aggregate numbers indicate a relatively stable dynamic of the
                        party system, without dramatic changes in the numbers of parties competing
                        in the elections, or parties entering the Parliament, and without
                        significant changes in the government formula. Table 1 shows that the number
                        of parties competing at the elections ranged from 17 to 23, reaching 26 only
                        in 1992, after the departure of the DEMOS coalition from the political scene
                        resulted in a large number of new parties contesting the elections.
                        Throughout the period, except for the first elections, seven or eight
                        parties were elected to the Parliament at all the elections.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-24">The number of parties in the governing coalitions
                        ranged between two and five, but most of the time the government consisted
                        of three or four parties. The patterns of governmental changes for the whole
                        period of the Slovenian independence were characterised by the partial
                        alternation of governing parties and partial changes in the government
                        formula. Complete changes of governing parties were almost completely absent
                        from the Slovenian party system, while innovations of the governmental
                        formula mostly came about as the consequence of the emergence of new
                        parties. In fact, the largest source of instability and volatility in the
                        Slovenian party system has been the disappearance of old and emergence of
                        new parties. This trend has become more important after the 2008 elections,
                        given that the subsequent two elections resulted in completely new parties
                        heading the government.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-25"><ref target="#ojs-120-table-1">Table 1</ref> also indicates that at each of the elections
                        since 1992 at least one new party was elected to the Parliament and at least
                        two or three parties dropped from the Parliament. However, in some cases
                        certain parties, such as New Slovenia (NSi) which failed to gain electoral
                        representation at a certain point, managed to enter the Parliament on a
                        later date.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-26">In the last decade the changes of the party system have
                        picked up the pace. This was especially the case at the last two elections,
                        held in 2011 and 2014, both of them called one year before the parliamentary
                        term expired. At both of these elections two new and very successful
                        political parties were established without being formed through a merger or
                        secession from of one of the existing political parties. Conversely, before
                        the 2011 elections most new parties came about mostly through splits or
                        mergers of the existing political parties. The elections of 2011 and 2014
                        were also different because a few parliamentary parties existing from 1992 –
                        two of them playing an important part in all the governments between 1992
                        and 2011 – failed to enter the Parliament. In 2011 the LDS and the only
                        nationalistic party, the SNS, lost parliamentary representation, while in
                        2014 the oldest Slovenian political party, the Slovenian Peoples Party
                        (SLS), failed to win any seats. These went to the winner of the 2011
                        elections Positive Slovenia (PS) as well as the newly established Citizens
                        List (DLGV), which was the third biggest parliamentary party in the
                        2011–2014 term.</p>
                    <table xml:id="ojs-120-table-1" rend="table-scroll hover">
                        <head>Data regarding the number of parties in the parliamentary
                            elections in Slovenia, 1990-2014</head>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell role="label">1990</cell>
                            <cell role="label">1992</cell>
                            <cell role="label">1996</cell>
                            <cell role="label">2000</cell>
                            <cell role="label">2004</cell>
                            <cell role="label">2008</cell>
                            <cell role="label">2011</cell>
                            <cell role="label">2014</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell role="label">No. of candidates</cell>
                            <cell>851</cell>
                            <cell>1475</cell>
                            <cell>1300</cell>
                            <cell>1007</cell>
                            <cell>1395</cell>
                            <cell>1182</cell>
                            <cell>1300</cell>
                            <cell>na</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell role="label">No. of competing parties</cell>
                            <cell>17</cell>
                            <cell>26</cell>
                            <cell>22</cell>
                            <cell>23</cell>
                            <cell>23</cell>
                            <cell>17</cell>
                            <cell>20</cell>
                            <cell>17</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell role="label">No. of elected parties</cell>
                            <cell>9</cell>
                            <cell>8</cell>
                            <cell>7</cell>
                            <cell>8</cell>
                            <cell>7</cell>
                            <cell>7</cell>
                            <cell>7</cell>
                            <cell>7</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell role="label">No. of newely elected parties</cell>
                            <cell>/</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>2/3*</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell role="label">No. of unelected parties</cell>
                            <cell>/</cell>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                            <cell>2/3**</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell role="label">No. of coalition parties</cell>
                            <cell>Demos, 5, later 6</cell>
                            <cell>4, later 3 and then 2</cell>
                            <cell>3 dropping to 2 </cell>
                            <cell>5 dropping to 4 </cell>
                            <cell>4</cell>
                            <cell>4</cell>
                            <cell>5 droping to 4</cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                        </row>
                        <note type="trailer" n="*">Counting the ZaAB as a new party, not as one of
                            the successors to the PS<lb/></note>
                        <note type="trailer" n="**">Not counting the ZaAB as one of the successors
                            to the PS<lb/></note>
                        <note type="trailer" n="">Source: National Electoral Commission
                            (2015).<lb/></note>
                    </table>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-27">Despite the frequent creation of new parties and
                        elimination of existing parties, the Slovenian party system has been
                        characterised by a relative stability. In the first decade of democratic
                        politics, the Slovenian political arena was dominated by the Liberal
                        Democracy of Slovenia (LDS), which controlled the government for 12 years
                        after 1992 through coalitions that included left and right-wing parties
                        alike. With the strengthening of the SDS, more clearly defined bloc
                        alternatives emerged, and the last four elections were characterised by a
                        bipolar pattern of competition between the SDS and a strong left-wing party:
                        first the LDS, then the SD, PS, and now the Party of Modern Centre
                        (SMC).</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-28">So far the most important changes in the structure of
                        the party system the last two elections, affecting predominantly the
                        formerly dominant left and centre-left parties. In 2011 the LDS received
                        slightly less than 2 % of votes, while its splinter party Zares, formed for
                        the 2008 elections, also failed to enter the Parliament. The elimination of
                        the only nationalist party, Slovene National Party (SNS), which had been a
                        member of the Parliament since 1992, was significant as well. In 2011 the
                        newly-established parties – the PS (centre-left) and the DLGV
                            (centre-right)<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn24" n="22">Simona
                            Kustec Lipicer and Niko Toš, "Analiza volilnega vedenja in izbir na
                            prvih predčasnih volitvah v državni zbor," <hi rend="italic">Teorija in
                                praksa</hi> 50, no. 3/4 (2013): 503.</note> – gained seats and
                        participated in the government, together receiving more than 37 percent of
                        the votes. These parties soon dropped out of the Parliament in the 2014
                        elections, when they gained less than 4 percent of the votes in total. At
                        the 2014 elections two new parties entered parliament: the Party of Miro
                        Cerar, now renamed as the Modern Centre Party (SMC), and the United Left
                        (ZL), together won more than 40 percent of the votes, while the 2011–2014
                        term parliamentary parties – the PS, DLGV and SLS – dropped out of the
                        Parliament.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-29">When we shift our focus from the number of parties to
                        the movement of voters, we can observe that the level of volatility at the
                        Slovenian elections, as shown in <ref target="#figure1">Figure 1</ref>,
                        remained comparatively high after the first elections (above 30 percent).
                        However, in 2004 it dropped to 23 percent as a stronger bipolar pattern of
                        party competition emerged. Since the 2008 elections volatility has been
                        increasing again, topping 50 percent in 2014 and indicating a heightened
                        instability of the party system as well as the weakening of links between
                        the parties and voters and an increased willingness of voters to switch
                        support between parties or move on to supporting an entirely new political
                        party.</p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure1">
                        <head>Volatility and vote share of new parties in the
                            parliamentary elections in Slovenia 1992-2014</head>
                        <graphic url="PNZ-ojs-120-figure1.jpg"/>
                        <p>Source: own calculations on the basis of the data provided by the
                            National Electoral Commission (2015)</p>
                    </figure>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-31">If we analyse the share of votes for the new parties at
                        each elections we get a somewhat better picture of what drives such high
                        level of volatility over time. In <ref target="#figure1">Figure 1</ref>
                        above we can observe that both volatility and votes for new parties have
                        increased significantly since 2008. Still, while volatility has been fairly
                        high from the beginning, we can see that the vote share of the new parties
                        was relatively modest until the 2008 elections, suggesting that volatility
                        was mostly driven by the shifts of the electorate within the established
                        parties. However, at last two elections the share of votes belonging to new
                        parties has been on the rise precipitously, and this accounts for most of
                        the volatility taking place in the Slovenian elections.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-32">When we look at the number of votes of the relevant
                        parties in the period between 1992 and 2014, we see that the changes in the
                        amount of party support were considerable, not only as far as the share of
                        votes parties gained is concerned, but also with regard to the actual number
                        of votes parties won at elections. What clearly comes across as the starkest
                        finding is that with the end of the LDS dominance on the political scene,
                        the voters supporting the broad left side of the political spectrum have
                        shifted their support from the LDS to the SD, then to the PS, and finally to
                        the SMC. On the right side, after the SLS lost the position of the second
                        party in the party system at the 2000 elections, this consolidation took
                        place primarily around the SDS in the second decade of democratic politics.
                        The SDS managed to win the support of almost a third of the electorate
                        between 2004 and 2011, only to witness the demobilization of about one third
                        of its voters at the 2014 elections while still retaining the status of the
                        second largest party in the context of the significantly reduced turnout. </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-33">The seats in the National Assembly over time and in
                        particular since 2000, are increasingly becoming distributed in such a way
                        as to make a clear distinction between the smaller and larger parties in the
                        context of an increasing bipolarity. In this context two principal parties
                        control over 50 % of the seats, while the remaining five or six
                        parliamentary parties distribute the remaining seats among themselves more
                        or less evenly.</p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure2">
                        <head>Vote choice at the Slovenian parliamentary elections (in
                            thousands of votes)</head>
                        <graphic url="PNZ-ojs-120-figure2.jpg"/>
                        <p>Source: National Electoral Commission (2015).</p>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="figure3">
                        <head>Share of the parliamentary seats at the Slovenian
                            parliamentary elections</head>
                        <graphic url="PNZ-ojs-120-figure3.jpg"/>
                        <p>Source: National Electoral Commission (2014).</p>
                    </figure>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-36">Although the party system sees parties emerging and
                        disappearing, for most of the period under consideration the electoral
                        system has performed relatively efficiently in securing that the voters’
                        preferences have been represented and that votes have not been wasted. Since
                        the establishment of the party system we have been able to observe that the
                        share of voters who voted for parties represented in the Parliament, or, in
                        other words, the share of voters whose votes are represented, increased just
                        after the first elections. However, since then this share has remained
                        between 84 percent and 93 percent within the period. The lowest share of
                        represented voters (76 percent) can be traced back to the first elections in
                        1992, which are also the elections with the highest number of parties
                        competing, while the best representation was achieved in 2000, when less
                        than 10 percent of voters voted for parties that did not manage to enter the
                        Parliament. The fact that despite the significant instability of the party
                        system in the last decade 85 % of voters voted for parties that are
                        represented in the Parliament is perhaps related to this very party system
                        instability. As it happens, in the eyes of the voters such instability
                        implies a reasonable probability that switching support to a different party
                        will not result in a wasted vote. Furthermore, it also signifies that a
                        large number of parties does not lead to a large number of wasted votes, or
                        to a continued concentration of support for marginal parties. </p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure4">
                        <head>Share of voters voting for parties represented in the
                            Parliament</head>
                        <graphic url="PNZ-ojs-120-figure4.jpg"/>
                        <p>Source: National Electoral Commission (2014).</p>
                    </figure>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-38">In conclusion, when we observe the development of the
                        Slovenian electoral and parliamentary party system, we can pinpoint several
                        significant developments affecting the stability of the party system and
                        changing the way it has functioned after the first decade of democracy:</p>
                    <list rend="ordered" xml:id="ojs-120-list-1">
                        <item>As a result of the 2004 elections, the first centre-right government,
                            led by the SDS, was formed after the twelve-year dominance of the
                            centre-left coalition government of LDS, leading to a more pronounced
                            bipolarisation of the party system.</item>
                        <item>In 2008 the centre-right government lost the elections. Once again a
                            centre-left government was formed, with the SD (the former communist
                            party) as the leader of the coalition with the DeSUS and two centre-left
                            parties, the LDS and Zares, the parties that arose from the split of the
                            LDS. The term of this government was characterised by the beginning of
                            the economic slowdown and modest growth as well as increasing financial
                            problems in the banking sector, as well as conflicts within the
                            government. The term ended with the 2011 early elections effectively
                            removing the SD from the position of the principal party of the
                            centre-left. </item>
                        <item>In 2011 early elections were held. The SDS and the newly formed
                            Positive Slovenia won the most votes. The following three years were
                            characterised by the changes of the government without elections and
                            severe conflicts within the PS, the new DLGV, as well as within both
                            governments in the 2011-2014 parliamentary term – one led by the SDS and
                            the other by the PS.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn25" n="23">On
                                20 September 2011 the vote of no confidence was passed in the
                                Parliament. On 21 October 2011 the President of the Republic
                                dismissed the Parliament and called for elections. The elections
                                were held on 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> December 2011. On 22
                                October 2011 Zoran Janković, the mayor of the Slovenian capital of
                                Ljubljana, established the Zoran Janković List - Positive Slovenija
                                party, which won the 2011 parliamentary elections with 28.51 % of
                                votes and became the leading parliamentary opposition party. Gregor
                                Virant as one of the lieutenants of the SDS party leader Janez
                                Janša, also the Minister of Public Administration in Janša's
                                2004-2008 government, resigned from the SDS in late summer of 2011
                                and established a new party, the Gregor Virant's Civic List, on 21
                                October 2011. His list won 8.37 % of votes and became one of the
                                government coalition parties.</note> Both the PS and DLGV came into
                            existence as alternatives to the existing established parliamentary
                            parties, and both claimed to represent new agendas and boasted highly
                            visible individuals as leaders in combination with relatively basic
                            party organisations.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn26" n="24">See
                                for example Krašovec and Tim Haughton, "Europe and the Parliamentary
                                Elections in Slovenia December 2011," <hi rend="italic">EPERN
                                    Election Briefing</hi> 69 (2012).</note> This set in motion a
                            new trend of one-shot parties, established by very prominent
                            personalities shortly before the elections and without clear programme
                            orientations, political identities or organisations, in order to be
                            propelled into the government virtually overnight.</item>
                        <item>A similar picture emerged in the second consecutive early elections in
                            2014, where the SMC repeated the Positive Slovenia's success from 2011,
                            and the United Left (ZL), as a left-wing socialist alternative, entered
                            the Parliament and extended the ideological scope of the political
                            spectrum on the left. On the right end of the political spectrum, the
                            oldest Slovenian party SLS dropped out of the Parliament. The same
                            happened to the Civic List (DLGV), which entered the Parliament only in
                            2011 and reduced the number of the political actors right of
                            center.</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-120-articel-sub04">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-120-head-14">Parties and the Public Opinion</head>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-39">The significant instability of the party system in the
                        last decade, in comparison with the first decade of democratic politics, may
                        indicate that the public attitudes towards political parties may be changing
                        as well. If this is the case, it can be expected that other political
                        institutions could be affected as well. The fact that some political parties
                        are losing support and disappearing while others are rising without clear
                        programmes, party identities or organisation may indicate that the voters
                        feel a certain degree of dissatisfaction with the parties. </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-40">This is confirmed if we look at the level of the public
                        support for the political parties and political institutions through which
                        the parties operate. The public image of the political parties and the
                        National Assembly as the principal arena of their institutional activities
                        is fairly low in Slovenia. Regarding the central government political
                        institutions as well as some other societal institutions, the political
                        parties and the National Assembly are consistently assessed by the
                        respondents as the least trustworthy. The public opinion survey polls
                        (called Polibarometer) in 2010<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn27"
                            n="25">
                            <hi rend="italic">Survey Politbarometer</hi> 12/2010 (Ljubljana: Center
                            za raziskovanje javnega mnenja, 2010).</note> revealed that only three
                        percent of respondents trusted the political parties, while as much as 64
                        percent did not trust them. According to a study carried out in March
                            2011,<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn28" n="26">
                            <hi rend="italic">Survey Politbarometer</hi> 03/2011 (Ljubljana: Center
                            za raziskovanje javnega mnenja, 2011).</note> the level of trust was
                        even lower – only two percent of respondents trusted the political parties,
                        while distrust increased to 68 percent. Such considerable (and increasing)
                        rate of distrust in the parties is also a result of the increasing
                        perception of the clientelistic relationships between the parties and
                        various interest groups as reported by the various media.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-120-ftn29" n="27">Data available in various media presses:
                                <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, <ref target="http://www.delo.si"
                                >www.delo.si</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Dnevnik</hi>, <ref
                                target="http://www.dnevnik.si">www.dnevnik.si</ref>. <hi
                                rend="italic">Večer</hi>, <ref target="http://www.vecer.si"
                                >www.vecer.si</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Prvi interaktivni
                                multimedijski portal, MMC RTV Slovenija</hi>, <ref
                                target="http://www.rtvslo.si">www.rtvslo.si</ref>. <hi rend="italic"
                                >Planet Siol.net</hi>, <ref target="http://www.siol.net"
                                >www.siol.net</ref>. <hi rend="italic">MLADINA.si</hi>, <ref
                                target="http://www.mladina.si">www.mladina.si</ref>, <hi
                                rend="italic">Revija Reporter</hi>, <ref
                                target="http://www.reporter.si">www.reporter.si</ref>. <hi
                                rend="italic">Tednik Demokracija</hi>, <ref
                                target="http://www.demokracija.si">www.demokracija.si</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-41">While the parties suffered from the lack of trust by
                        the public since the middle of the 1990s, over the last few years the trust
                        in the government and the Parliament has declined significantly as well. The
                        timing of this development closely coincides with the economic crisis
                        affecting the country. However, it also coincides with the increase in
                        volatility of the electorate and the increased turnover, or emergence and
                        disappearance of political parties from one election to the next. All of
                        this indicates that the public opinion sees political parties as
                        institutions that fail to fulfil their function, and their failure is
                        affecting the attitude of voters towards the whole political system.</p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure5">
                        <head>Share of respondents indicating that they do not trust
                            particular political institutions</head>
                        <graphic url="PNZ-ojs-120-figure5.jpg"/>
                        <p>Source: Niko Toš et. al., <hi rend="italic">Politbarometer 3/2011 and
                                1/2012. Meritve v času izrednih parlamentarnih volitev v DZ RS
                                oktober 2011 – januar 2012 [dataset]</hi> (Ljubljana: Public Opinion
                            and Mass Communication Research Centre, 2012)</p>
                    </figure>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-43">Electoral participation in the elections at various
                        levels is a further sign of the shift in the popular attitudes towards the
                        political system. <ref target="#figure3">Figure 3</ref> shows a considerable decline in the electoral
                        turnout since the 1992 elections, signifying a changing attitude of the
                        public towards the elected institutions. In 1992 the turnout at the
                        parliamentary elections was 85 percent. In 1996 and 2000 it dropped to just
                        above 70 percent, only to fall to only 60 percent in 2004. The turnout
                        remained between 60 and 65 percent until 2014, when it dropped to 51 %,
                        which is one of the lowest levels in Europe for national elections. Similar
                        trends are evident also for the presidential and local elections, where the
                        turnout (initially at a lower level than in the case of parliamentary
                        elections) was declining in accordance with the trends at the national
                        elections. The level of turnout was the lowest for the European Parliament
                        elections, as it did not exceed 30 percent in any of the three European
                        Parliament elections so far.</p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure6">
                        <head>Election turnout in Slovenia, 1992-2014</head>
                        <graphic url="PNZ-ojs-120-figure6.jpg"/>
                        <p>Source: National Electoral Commission (2015).</p>
                        <note n="">Legend: * due to the legislative changes, in a certain period the
                            local elections were not called for all the local communities at the
                            same time, which makes the collection of turnout data for the local
                            elections turnout more challenging for the terms under consideration,
                            although this does not have any direct impact on the turnout
                            interpretations for the purposes of this paper.</note>
                    </figure>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-120-articel-sub05">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-120-head-17">Party Identification and Preferences</head>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-45">The comparative analysis of the relationship between
                        the ideological positioning of voters and political parties in Slovenia,
                        with respect to their position on the political spectrum, has so far shown
                        that the classic economic left-right position in Slovenia is one of the
                        least relevant factors of electoral choice.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-120-ftn30" n="28">Russell J Dalton, David M. Farrell and Ian
                                McAllister, <hi rend="italic">Political Parties and Democratic
                                Linkage: How parties organize democracy</hi> (Oxford: Oxford
                            University Press, 2011).</note> Instead, most studies reveal that the
                        main ideological division in Slovenia revolves around the interpretation of
                        history, and in that context primarily around the interpretation of the
                        political divisions during World War II, the interpretation of the nature of
                        war and its participants in Slovenia, as well as the character of the
                        post-war state and the events related to it.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-120-ftn31" n="29">Hans-Dieter Klingemann, Dieter Fuchs and
                            Jan Zielonka, <hi rend="italic">Democracy and Political Culture in
                                Eastern Europe</hi> (London: Routledge, 2006). Drago Zajc and Tomaz
                            Boh, "10. Slovenia," in <hi rend="italic">The Handbook of Political
                                Change in Eastern Europe,</hi> ed. Sten Berglund  (Cheltenham,
                            Northampton (MA): Edward Elgar Publishing, 2004). Danica Fink-Hafner and
                            Alenka Krašovec, "Europeanisation of the Slovenian party system–from
                            marginal European impacts to the domestication of EU policy issues?" <hi
                                rend="italic">Politics</hi> (2006).</note> The issues of the
                        traditional versus modern attitudes and values regarding individual freedom,
                        role of family, religion and morality, as well as the definition of national
                        identity are closely related to these historical divisions. These elements
                        have formed another dimension of the dominant symbolic division.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-46">What appears to characterise the social foundations of
                        the Slovenian party system is a stable distribution of the voters' party
                        identification across the political spectrum, with somewhat lesser stability
                        of party identity in case of the left-wing voters. Furthermore, we cannot
                        observe any consistent classic ideological divisions based on the
                        socio-economic differences, despite the issue of the role of the old and new
                        economic and social elites. The interpretation of history, attitude towards
                        the communist regime and other similar issues form a very clear symbolic
                        division. This dominance of symbolic politics means that with respect to
                        economic issues, parties sometimes behave in a way which is not likely to be
                        consistent with their overall ideological orientation.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-120-ftn32" n="30">Russell J Dalton, David M. Farrell and Ian
                            McAllister, "The Dynamics of Political Representation," in <hi
                                rend="italic">How Democracy Works: Political Representation and
                                Policy Congruence in Modern Societies,</hi> ed. Martin Rosema, Kees
                            Aarts and Bas Denters (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2011). Samo
                            Kropivnik and Simona Kustec Lipicer, "Party Manifestos in
                            Slovenia," Prepared for delivery at the 2012 Annual Meeting of the
                            American Political Science Association, August 30 – September 2,
                            2012.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-47">The analysis of the Slovenian parties’ electoral
                        programmes reveals that the character of party competition is in some
                        respects typical of the electoral politics in other Central and Eastern
                        European countries with respect to the scope and type of the prevailing
                        policy issues.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn33" n="31">Hans-Dieter
                            Klingemann, Andrea Volkens, Judith Bara, Ian Budge, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Mapping policy preferences II: estimates for parties, electors, and
                                governments in Eastern Europe, European Union, and OECD
                                1990–2003</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2006). According to
                            the applied methodology, the scope of electoral program issues is
                            analyzed by measuring the frequency of the following seven domains in
                            each program 1) External Relations; 2) Freedom and Democracy; 3)
                            Political System; 4) Economy; 5) Welfare and Quality of life; 6) Fabric
                            of Society; 7) Social Groups.</note> Moreover, it is apparent that the
                        contemporary Slovenian political parties are not formed as representatives
                        of narrow interests, but rather that they have a position of so-called
                        "catch-all" parties, as their programmes address a wide range of voters,
                        even when they are nominally representing particular social groups, like the
                        DeSUS.</p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure7">
                        <head>Distribution of political issues in the party programmes –
                            averages for all parties</head>
                        <graphic url="PNZ-ojs-120-figure7.jpg"/>
                        <p>Sources: own data and calculations on the dateset methodology by
                            Hans-Dieter Klingemann, Andrea Volkens, Judith Bara, Ian Budge, <hi
                                rend="italic">Mapping policy preferences II: estimates for parties,
                                electors, and governments in Eastern Europe, European Union, and
                                OECD 1990-2003</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2006); Simona
                            Kustec Lipicer and Samo Kropivnik. "Dimensions of Party Electoral
                            Programs: Slovenian Experience," <hi rend="italic">Journal of
                                Comparative Politics</hi> 4.1 (2011): 52</p>
                    </figure>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-49">The data shows that the Slovenian parties, in general,
                        keep the contents of their programmes increasingly stable over time, despite
                        the significant contextual changes in the society and economy over the last
                        decade. The priority given to particular issues in the party programmes has
                        been changing over time, but generally, welfare and quality of life issues
                        have topped the list, while the economic issues have grown in importance
                        over time, mostly at the expense of the decline in the priority of welfare
                        issues as well as all the issues related to social policy. This shift is
                        more obvious in the case of the leading centre-right Slovenian Democratic
                        Party (SDS), where we can observe a sharp shift of focus between the two
                        periods. A less prominent but still obvious shift took place in the
                        programmes of other parties, where we observe slow, gradual changes leading
                        to a shift in the policy orientation.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-120-ftn34" n="32">Including also a unique and very strong
                            focus on the political system issues.</note> It is reasonable to
                        speculate that these changes have appeared mostly as a result of the ongoing
                        external social, economic and political turbulences, manifesting themselves
                        in the local context. Apart from the shifts in focus, we can observe that
                        the structures of party programmes have become more similar over time with
                        respect to the structure of the issues included in the party
                            programmes.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn35" n="33">More on this
                            in: Simona Kustec Lipicer and Samo Kropivnik, "Dimensions of Party
                            Electoral Programmes: Slovenian Experience," <hi rend="italic">Journal
                                of Comparative Politics</hi> 4.1 (2011): 52.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-50">A further analysis of the 2004-2011 period reveals that
                        the structural differences in issue priorities clearly separate the
                        parliamentary from the non-parliamentary parties rather than, as already
                        indicated, along the lines between the left vs. right or government vs.
                            opposition.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-120-ftn36" n="34">Ibid.</note>
                        Parliamentary parties are more focused on the political system and economy,
                        while non-parliamentary parties prioritise welfare, quality of life, and
                        social fabric. These differences are expected and correspond to the findings
                        of the general policy analyses. They imply that non-parliamentary parties
                        are much more issue-oriented and focus on the policies related to the
                        welfare and/or societal issues than the leading parliamentary parties are
                        far more catch-all oriented and focus on the fundamental issues of the
                        political system. On the other hand, there are no obvious differences in the
                        issue structure between the more and less successful parliamentary parties.
                        The only exception, to a degree, to the general trend shown in <ref target="#figure7">Figure 7</ref>
                        seems to emerge in 2014, where the issue dimensions are more evenly
                        represented in the party programmes in comparison with the previous
                        elections.</p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure8">
                        <head>Party programmes and electoral success</head>
                        <graphic url="PNZ-ojs-120-figure8.jpg"/>
                        <p>Sources: own data and calculations; Simona Kustec Lipicer and Niko Toš,
                            "Analiza volilnega vedenja in izbir na prvih predčasnih volitvah u
                            državni zbor," <hi rend="italic">Teorija in praksa 50</hi>, no. 3/4
                            (2013): 503</p>
                    </figure>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-52">Furthermore, even the new parties (PS and DLGV, SMC or
                        ZL), which ran at the 2011 and 2014 elections with atypically short and
                        general programmes but nevertheless experienced significant electoral
                        success, are close to the other parliamentary parties as far as the issue
                        structure of their party programmes is concerned. This may point to the
                        conclusion that the electoral upheaval, affecting Slovenian politics at the
                        2011 and 2014 elections, was not so much about the voters trying to find a
                        new political direction, but rather that it was a case of the voters being
                        dissatisfied with the old political elites, therefore trying to replace them
                        with a new set of actors without asking for credentials or assurances that
                        the new elites in fact have any new solutions to the problems.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-120-articel-sub06">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-120-head-20">Final remarks</head>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-53">The Slovenian party system as an integral element of
                        parliamentary democracy since the Slovenian transition to democracy has
                        exhibited several significant trends. On one hand the party system has
                        exhibited a significant degree of stability in its aggregate
                        characteristics. The number of parties competing at elections as well as the
                        number of elected and governing parties, the broad contours of party
                        programmes, and the patterns of governmental alterations have remained
                        broadly stable over time.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-54">At the same time, while the party system has exhibited
                        a significant degree of stability at the aggregate level, over time the
                        instability at the level of political parties has increased. This has taken
                        place in the context of the increased dissatisfaction of the citizens with
                        the political parties. Electoral volatility, always high, further increased
                        dramatically at the 2011 and 2014 elections, when the old parties were
                        eliminated from the government from one election to the next and the share
                        of votes for new parties reached 40 % or more. Increased volatility is just
                        one of the trends indicating the increasingly critical attitude of citizens
                        towards the parties and political institutions most closely related to the
                        political parties, such as the government and the Parliament. It remains to
                        be seen whether such a critical attitude of citizens towards the political
                        parties will continue in the next electoral cycle. However, it is evident
                        from the developments in the last few years that the new parties have a
                        number of weaknesses and lack the resilience that the old parties have in
                        terms of stable links with voters, stable party organisations allowing for
                        steady and effective patterns of political recruitment, and stable party
                        identity. The new parties that emerged in the 2014 elections are vulnerable
                        the same as were their predecessors in 2011, and it is not unlikely that the
                        degree of instability will persist, though the external pressure on the
                        party system might decline if the economic conditions and modes of
                        transparent governance are stabilised.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-55">Finally, the party system is an essential element of
                        the parliamentary system. Parties are the principal conduit for the
                        recruitment of political elites and representation of the political
                        preferences of voters. It is therefore not unlikely that the changes in the
                        party system could ultimately lead to changes in the parliamentary
                        arena.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr" xml:id="ojs-120-bibliogr">
                <head xml:id="ojs-120-head-21">Sources and references</head>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-120-bibliogr-sub01">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-120-head-22">Literature</head>
                    <listBibl xml:id="ojs-120-listBibl-1">
                        <bibl>Biezen, Ingrid van, Peter Mair and Thomas Poguntke. "Going,
                            Going…Gone? Party Membership in the 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>
                            Century." Paper prepared for the workshop on ‘Political Parties and
                            Civil Society’, ECPR Joint Sessions, Lisbon, April 2009.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Dalton, Russell J., David M. Farrell and Ian McAllister. "The Dynamics
                            of Political Representation." In <hi rend="italic">How Democracy Works:
                                Political Representation and Policy Congruence in Modern
                                Societies,</hi> edited by Martin Rosema, Kees Aarts and Bas Denters.
                            Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2011.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Dalton, Russell J., David M. Farrell and Ian McAllister. <hi
                                rend="italic">Political Parties and Democratic Linkage: How parties
                                organize democracy</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University Press,
                            2011.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Fink-Hafner, Danica and Alenka Krašovec. "Europeanisation of the
                            Slovenian party system–from marginal European impacts to the
                            domestication of EU policy issues?" <hi rend="italic"
                            >Politics</hi> (2006).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Fink-Hafner, Danica, Damjan Lajh and Alenka Krašovec. <hi
                                rend="italic">Politika na območju nekdanje Jugoslavije.</hi>
                            Ljubljana: Fakulteta za družbene vede, 2005.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Fink-Hafner, Danica. "Slovenia: Between Bipolarity and Broad
                            Coalition-Building." In <hi rend="italic">Post-Communist EU Member
                                States: Parties and Party Systems,</hi> edited by Susanne
                            Jungerstam-Mulders, 203–231. Aldershot, Burlington: Ashgate,
                            2006.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Fink-Hafner, Danica. "Strankarski sistem v Sloveniji: Od prikrite k
                            transparentni bipolarnosti." In <hi rend="italic">Političke stranke i
                                birači u državama bivše Jugoslavije,</hi> edited by Zoran Lutovac,
                            363–384. Beograd: Friderich Ebert Stiftung, 2006.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Fink-Hafner, Danica. "Between continuity and change." In <hi
                                rend="italic">Slovenia Between Continuity and Change 1990–1997</hi>,
                            edited by Niko Toš and Vlado Miheljak. Berlin: Sigma, 2002.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Fink-Hafner, Danica. <hi rend="italic">Nova družbena gibanja -
                                subjekti politične inovacije</hi>. Ljubljana: Fakulteta za družbene
                            vede, 2002.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Gašparič, Jure. <hi rend="italic">Državni zbor: 1992–2012: o
                                slovenskem parlamentarizmu</hi>. Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo
                            zgodovino, 2012.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Huntington, Samuel P. <hi rend="italic">The Third Wave:
                                Democratization in the late twentieth century.</hi> London:
                            University of Oklahoma Press, 1991.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Klingemann, Hans-Dieter, Andrea Volkens, Judith Bara and Ian Budge.
                                <hi rend="italic">Mapping policy preferences II: estimates for
                                parties, electors, and governments in Eastern Europe, European
                                Union, and OECD 1990–2003</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University Press,
                            2006.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Klingemann, Hans-Dieter, Dieter Fuchs and Jan Zielonka. <hi
                                rend="italic">Democracy and Political Culture in Eastern
                                Europe.</hi> London: Routledge, 2006.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Krašovec, Alenka and Tim Haughton. "Europe and the Parliamentary
                            Elections in Slovenia December 2011." <hi rend="italic">EPERN Election
                                Briefing</hi> 69 (2012).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Kropivnik, Samo and Simona Kustec Lipicer. "Party Manifestos in
                            Slovenia." Prepared for delivery at the 2012 Annual Meeting of the
                            American Political Science Association, August 30 – September 2,
                            2012.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Kustec Lipicer, Simona and Niko Toš. "Analiza volilnega vedenja in
                            izbir na prvih predčasnih volitvah v državni zbor." <hi rend="italic"
                                >Teorija in praksa</hi> 50, no. 3/4 (2013): 503–529.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Kustec Lipicer, Simona and Samo Kropivnik. "Dimensions of Party
                            Electoral Programs: Slovenian Experience." <hi rend="italic">Journal of
                                Comparative Politics</hi> 4.1 (2011): 52.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Linz, Juan. "The Breakdown of Democratic Regimes: Crisis." In <hi
                                rend="italic">Breakdown and Reequilibration,</hi> edited by Juan
                            Linz and Alfred Stepan. Baltimore: John Hopkins University Press,
                            1978.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Prunk, Janko. "Politično življenje v samostojni Sloveniji." In <hi
                                rend="italic">Dvajset let slovenske države</hi>, edited by Janko
                            Prunk and Tomaž Deželan, 17–57. Maribor: Aristej; Ljubljana: Fakulteta
                            za družbene vede, Center za politološke raziskave 2012.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Toš, Niko and Vlado Miheljak. "Transition in Slovenia: Towards
                            Democratization and the Attainment of Sovereignty." In <hi rend="italic"
                                >Slovenia Between Continuity and Change 1990–1997</hi>, edited by
                            Niko Toš and Vlado Miheljak. Berlin: Sigma, 2002.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Toš, Niko et. al. <hi rend="italic">Politbarometer 3/2011 and 1/2012.
                                Meritve v času izrednih parlamentarnih volitev v DZ RS oktober 2011
                                – januar 2012 [dataset]</hi>. Ljubljana: Public Opinion and Mass
                            Communication Research Centre, 2012.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Zajc, Drago and Tomaz Boh. "10. Slovenia." In <hi rend="italic">The
                                Handbook of Political Change in Eastern Europe,</hi> edited by Sten
                            Berglund. Cheltenham, Northampton (MA): Edward Elgar Publishing,
                            2004.</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-120-bibliogr-sub02">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-120-head-23">Other sources</head>
                    <listBibl xml:id="ojs-120-listBibl-2">
                        <bibl>
                            <hi rend="italic">Constitution of the Republic of Slovenia</hi>.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <hi rend="italic">Official Gazette of the RS</hi>, no. 100
                            (2005).</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl" xml:id="ojs-120-summary">
                <head xml:id="ojs-120-head-24">Povzetek</head>
                <head rend="subtitle" xml:id="ojs-120-head-25">Spreminjajoča se dinamika slovenske
                    demokratične parlamentarne arene: Volivci, stranke, volitve</head>
                <docAuthor xml:id="ojs-120-docAuthor-5">Simona Kustec Lipicer</docAuthor>
                <docAuthor xml:id="ojs-120-docAuthor-6">Andrija Henjak</docAuthor>
                <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-56">Glavni namen članka je podati opisni analitični pregled
                    razvoja slovenskega parlamentarnega prostora od prehoda v demokracijo in
                    neodvisnost do današnjih dni. Sodobni demokratični parlamentarni prostor v
                    Sloveniji je sam po sebi videti sorazmerno stabilen. Nasprotno so njegovi
                    sestavni deli – politične stranke – postopno postali manj stabilni in
                    predvidljivi, zlasti v drugem desetletju demokracije. To je razvidno tudi iz vse
                    večjega nezaupanja volivcev – ne samo v politične stranke, ampak tudi v
                    parlament in vlado – ter iz naraščajoče nestanovitnosti.</p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-57">Razprava se najprej posveti normativnemu vpogledu v
                    parlamentarni in strankarski sistem, nato pa analitični oceni strukture
                    parlamentarnega prostora, kot jo izražajo odločitve volivcev na volitvah in
                    politična stališča strank. </p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-58">Pri slovenskem sistemu političnih strank kot sestavnem delu
                    parlamentarne demokracije lahko od prehoda v demokracijo opazimo več različnih
                    pomembnih trendov. Po osamosvojitvi so se postopno vzpostavili zakonski okviri
                    za ustanavljanje političnih strank, ki so opredelili pojem, financiranje in
                    delovanje političnih strank v državi ter jim hkrati omogočili tako visoko raven
                    samoregulacije, da je javnost njih in njihovo podobo pogosto ocenjevala kot
                    netransparentno. Strankarski sistem se je po eni strani v celoti izkazal za
                    precej stabilnega. Število strank, ki so sodelovale na volitvah, število
                    izvoljenih in vladajočih strank, splošni obrisi strankarskih programov in vzorci
                    menjavanja vlad so na splošno stabilni. Hkrati je tej splošni stabilnosti
                    sledila vse večja nestabilnost na ravni političnih strank, do katere je prišlo v
                    okviru naraščajoče nezadovoljnosti državljanov s političnimi strankami.
                    Nestanovitnost volivcev in nezaupanje do političnih strank sta se zelo okrepila,
                    kar kaže na vse bolj kritičen odnos državljanov do strank. To velja tudi za
                    politične institucije, ki so najtesneje povezane s političnimi strankami, na
                    primer za vlado in parlament. Nestabilnost na ravni političnih strank se je
                    kazala skozi številne nove stranke, ki so nastajale in izginjale od enih volitev
                    do drugih. To je pomembno vplivalo na vzorce oblikovanja vlad in vladnih
                    koalicij, saj so stranke vstopale v vlado, nato pa izginile na naslednjih
                    volitvah, na katerih so jih nadomestile nove stranke. Vzrok za to nestabilnost
                    so predvsem številne pomanjkljivosti novih strank, ki očitno nimajo ključnih
                    stabilizacijskih elementov političnih strank, kot so stabilna povezava z volivci
                    ter stabilna strankarska organizacija in identiteta. To velja tudi za uspešne
                    nove stranke, ki so se pojavile v obdobju med volitvami leta 2008 in zadnjimi
                    volitvami leta 2014, drugimi v nizu predčasnih volitev. Zato bi se lahko podobna
                    raven nestabilnosti nadaljevala tudi v prihodnje, čeprav je možno, da bi se s
                    stabilizacijo gospodarskih razmer in težav z upravljanjem zmanjšal zunanji
                    pritisk na strankarski sistem in posamezne stranke. Vprašanje je tudi, ali bodo
                    slovenskih državljani ohranili tako kritičen odnos do političnih strank v
                    naslednjem volilnem ciklusu ali pa bi stabilnejše gospodarstvo in upravna
                    struktura lahko morda spremenila stališča državljanov do strank in politike.</p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-120-p-59">Navsezadnje ima usoda strankarskega sistema širši pomen.
                    Strankarski sistem je bistveni sestavni del parlamentarnega sistema, stranke pa
                    so osnovni kanal za rekrutiranje političnih elit in zastopanje politične volje
                    volivcev. Zato bi lahko spremembe v strankarskem sistemu sčasoma pripeljale tudi
                    do mnogo bolj temeljnih sprememb tudi v dosedanjem delovanju v političnem
                    parlamentarnem prostoru.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
