<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en" xml:id="ojs-129">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a">Coming to (a Short) Life</title>
                <title level="a">The Czechoslovak Parliament 1989-1992</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Adéla</forename>
                        <surname>Gjuričová</surname>
                    </name>
                    <roleName>senior researcher</roleName>
                    <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Institute of Contemporary History of the Czech Academy of
                        Sciences</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Puškinovo náměstí 9</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Prague 6</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>16000</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Czech Republic</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>gjuricova@usd.cas.cz</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2015-12-03</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/129</pubPlace>
                <date>2015</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="PID">sistory.36115</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Czechoslovakia 1989-1992</term>
                    <term>Parliamentarism</term>
                    <term>Federal systems of government</term>
                    <term>Post-Communist transition</term>
                    <term>Break-up of Czechoslovakia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>Češkoslovaška 1989–1992</term>
                    <term>parlamentarizem</term>
                    <term>zvezni sistemi oblasti</term>
                    <term>postkomunistična tranzicija</term>
                    <term>razdružitev Češkoslovaške</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2015-12-03T17:01:00Z</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en" type="article" n="Articles">
        <front>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart>Coming to (a Short) Life</titlePart>
                    <titlePart>The Czechoslovak Parliament 1989-1992</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <docAuthor>Adéla Gjuričová</docAuthor>
                <docImprint>
                    <idno type="cobissType">1.01</idno>
                    <idno type="UDC">328(437)"1989/1992"</idno>
                </docImprint>
            </titlePage>
            <divGen type="toc" xml:id="ojs-129-toc">
                <head>Table of Contents</head>
            </divGen>
            <divGen type="search" xml:id="ojs-129-search">
                <head>Search</head>
            </divGen>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl" xml:id="ojs-129-izvlecek">
                <head xml:id="ojs-129-head-3">Izvleček</head>
                <head xml:id="ojs-129-head-4" rend="subtitle">(Kratko) življenje: Češkoslovaški
                    parlament 1989–1992</head>
                <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-6">Češkoslovaški zvezni parlament je bil vzpostavljen leta
                    1968, da bi nadomestil državni zbor unitaristične države in tako formalno
                    izrazil enakopravnost Čehov in Slovakov v novoustanovljeni federaciji. Po zlomu
                    reform praške pomladi je socialistični parlament izgubil večino suverenosti,
                    ohranil pa je zvezni značaj in formalne postopke, s čimer je predstavljal
                    nekakšno »podporno« zakonodajno telo. Leta 1989 je žametna revolucija, ki se je
                    opredelila za spoštovanje miru in zakonitosti, v središču nove politike seveda
                    našla parlament starega režima. V revolucionarnem parlamentu 1989–1990 je
                    koncept socialističnega parlamentarizma trčil ob nove motive, kot so nacionalna
                    enotnost, prelom s komunistično preteklostjo, liberalna demokracija in
                    subsidiarnost. Posledično se je oblikovalo več mešanih socialističnih,
                    revolucionarnih in liberalno demokratičnih pogledov na parlament. Vse te
                    koncepte in politične prakse pa so češka in slovaška javnost ter politični
                    predstavniki dojemali in sprejemali na nasprotujoče si načine. Nekatere od teh
                    razlik so se izkazale za nezdružljive in zvezni parlament je nazadnje odigral
                    ključno vlogo pri vodenju razdružitve češkoslovaške federacije leta 1992.</p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-7">Ključne besede: Češkoslovaška 1989–1992, parlamentarizem,
                    zvezni sistemi oblasti, postkomunistična tranzicija, razdružitev
                    Češkoslovaške</p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract" xml:id="ojs-129-abstract">
                <head xml:id="ojs-129-head-5">Abstract</head>
                <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-8">The Czechoslovak federal parliament was designed in 1968 to
                    replace the National Assembly of a unitary state and thus formally express
                    equality between Czechs and Slovaks in the newly established federation. After
                    the crash of the Prague Spring reforms, the socialist parliament lost most of
                    its sovereignty, while preserving its federal character and formal procedures,
                    thus providing a sort of “backup” legislature. The Velvet Revolution of 1989,
                    with its proclaimed respect to peace and legality, logically found the ancient
                    régime’s parliament in the centre of new politics. In the revolutionary
                    parliament of 1989-1990, the concept of socialist parliamentarianism began to
                    clash with new motives, such as the national unity, a break with the Communist
                    past, liberal democracy, or subsidiarity. Various blends of socialist,
                    revolutionary and liberal democratic views of the parliament consequently came
                    to life, while each of these concepts as well as every practical policy was
                    perceived and accepted in conflicting manners by the Czech and Slovak publics as
                    well as political representations. Some of these differences turned out to be
                    irreconcilable and the federal parliament eventually played a key role in
                    administering the break-up of Czechoslovak federation in 1992.</p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-9">Keywords: Czechoslovakia 1989-1992, Parliamentarism, Federal
                    systems of government, Post-Communist transition, Break-up of Czechoslovakia</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="chapter" xml:id="ojs-129-article">
                <head xml:id="ojs-129-head-6">Coming to (a Short) Life</head>
                <head xml:id="ojs-129-head-7" rend="subtitle">The Czechoslovak Parliament 1989-1992</head>
                <docAuthor xml:id="ojs-129-docAuthor-2">Adéla Gjuričová<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ojs-129-ftn1" n="*">senior researcher, PhD, Institute of
                        Contemporary History of the Czech Academy of Sciences, Puškinovo náměstí 9,
                        Prague 6, 16000, Czech Republic, <ref target="mailto:gjuricova@usd.cas.cz"
                            >gjuricova@usd.cas.cz</ref>
                    </note>
                </docAuthor>
                <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-10">In his renowned report of the Central European <hi
                        rend="italic">Year of Miracles</hi>, Timothy Garton Ash offers a detailed
                    and extensive description of the discussions inside the revolutionary Civic
                    Forum headquarters as well as the atmosphere of Prague street demonstrations.
                    The country’s parliament, the Czechoslovak Federal Assembly was given only a
                    brief comment: “The women with putty faces, cheap perms and schoolmistress
                    voices. The men in cheap suits, with hair swept straight back from sweaty
                    foreheads. The physiognomy of power for the last forty years. But at the end of
                    the day they all vote ‘yes’ to the prime minister’s proposal, as agreed
                    yesterday with the Forum, to delete the leading role of the Party from the
                    constitution, and remove Marxism-Leninism as the basis of education.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn2" n="1">Timothy Garton Ash, <hi
                            rend="italic">We the People. The Revolution of ’89 Witnessed in Warsaw,
                            Budapest, Berlin &amp; Prague</hi> (London: Granta Books, 1990),
                        111.</note> Parliament occupied a minor, rather obscure place in the
                    Czechoslovak revolution and real power was to be found elsewhere, Ash concluded. </p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-11">However, the material put together for the following
                        analysis<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn3" n="2">This paper was
                        written within a research project supported by the Czech Science Foundation
                        (GAČR, GA15-14271S).</note> offers a more complex picture. The parliamentary
                    archives, legal documents, memoires and interviews of former deputies suggest
                    that the first post-Communist and the last federal parliament of Czechoslovakia,
                    no matter how short-lived, was in fact a multifaceted body with surprising
                    continuities with socialist times as well as striking discontinuities within the
                    early post-socialist period. The legislature obviously lived an independent, yet
                    influential life: Almost none of the important turning points in the
                    parliament’s history of 1989-1992 match the official landmarks of the democratic
                    revolution and early post-socialist transformations of Czechoslovakia. </p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-12">The two chambers of the Federal Assembly were designed in
                        1968<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn4" n="3">The Constitutional Act on
                        the Czechoslovak Federation was adopted in October 1968. It amended the
                        Constitution of Czechoslovakia from 1960, formally placing many of the
                        former functions of the central government under the jurisdiction of the two
                        national governments.</note> to replace the existing National Assembly of a
                    unitary state and to formally express the equality between Czechs and Slovaks in
                    the thus established federation. After the crash of the Prague Spring reforms,
                    the socialist parliament lost most of its sovereignty that it had briefly
                    experienced in 1968. However, unlike almost all other reforms, the parliament
                    preserved its federal character as well as its elaborate formal procedures. This
                    “backup” legislature was first mobilized during the <hi rend="italic"
                        >perestroika</hi> reforms of the late-socialist régime and then became one
                    of the cornerstones of the post-socialist transformation.</p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-13">The Czechoslovak revolution of 1989, with its proclaimed
                    respect to peace and legality, logically found the <hi rend="italic">ancient
                        régime’s</hi> parliament in the centre of new politics. In what will further
                    be called the “revolutionary parliament” of 1989-1990, the concept, values and
                    practices of socialist parliamentarianism began to clash with new motives, such
                    as the calls for national unity, for a break with the communist past, concepts
                    of liberal democracy, the civic principle or subsidiarity. Various blends of
                    socialist, revolutionary and liberal democratic practices and views of
                    parliament consequently came to life, while each of these concepts as well as
                    every policy was perceived, practiced and accepted in conflicting manners by the
                    Czech and Slovak publics as well as political representations. As will be shown
                    further, some of these differences turned out to be irreconcilable and the
                    federal parliament eventually played a key role in administering and
                    legitimizing the break-up of Czechoslovak federation in 1992.</p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-14">This article follows the logic of neo-institutionalist
                    approaches to explaining parliaments as organizations. Traditional
                    historiographical works on institutions used to describe the most easily visible
                    parts. In case of parliaments, they would refer to the most evident archival
                    traces such as the foundation of the body, its composition, official actors and
                    their speeches, the legislation passed etc. The so called new institutionalism
                    can be understood as a reaction to the development in social sciences turning
                    the researcher’s attention away from the central to less visible actors and
                    processes. Descriptions of organizations began to focus on practices, habits,
                    values and myths generally accepted and further transferred by institutions.
                    Parliaments are thus often seen as relatively stable structures with established
                    social norms, methods of bargaining and expertise. These seem to sooner or later
                    overwhelm every newcomer and make him or her adapt to the norms and start
                    practising them as well. We will be able to trace this process during the régime
                    change and demonstrate some interesting continuities between the socialist,
                    revolutionary and liberal democratic parliaments within the Federal Assembly. </p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-15">The following interpretation also tries to cope with the
                    usual premise that in case of context modification such as régime change,
                    political institutions immediately adapt to external interventions such as new
                    legal regulation etc.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn5" n="4">Foundation
                        texts of new institutionalism by Paul J. DiMaggio, Walter W. Powell, W.
                        Richard Scott and John W. Meyer have been published together in Walter W.
                        Powell and Paul J. DiMaggio, ed., <hi rend="italic">The New Institutionalism
                            in Organizational Analysis</hi> (London, Chicago: Chicago UP, 1991),
                        41–62, 63–82 and 108–142.</note> Our approach goes further past the
                    neo-institutional search for underground myths carried on by institutions. We
                    tend to see interactive relations between institutions and actors, producing
                    rather fluid organizations. Parliaments can then be observed as somewhat
                    “vulnerable” environments that constantly seek to find balance between the
                    existing rules, institutional regulations and myths – and the current as well as
                    former members, their expectations, beliefs and self-concepts.</p>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-129-article-sub01">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-129-head-8">Overlooking the Revolution</head>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-16">Physically speaking, the Federal Assembly was situated
                        right in the heart of the Velvet Revolution. The steel and glass
                            construction<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn6" n="5">For recent
                            photos of the internationally acclaimed project by Karel Prager, Jiří
                            Kadeřábek and Jiří Albrecht see “Federal Assembly Building at Wenceslas
                            Square, Prague,” accessed October 30, 2015, <ref
                                target="http://www.parliamentsintransition.cz/dokumenty/federalassemblybuildingatwenceslassquareprague"
                                >http://www.parliamentsintransition.cz/dokumenty/federalassemblybuildingatwenceslassquareprague</ref>.</note>
                        was designed in the reformist era of the late 1960s at the upper end of
                        Wenceslas Square to institutionally counterweight the Prague Castle. And
                        yet, for many days, the parliament was absent from the symbolic topography
                        of the revolution.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn7" n="6">Petr
                            Roubal, <hi rend="italic">Starý pes, nové kousky: kooptace do
                                Federálního shromáždění a vytváření polistopadové politické
                                kultury</hi> (Praha: Ústav pro soudobé dějiny AV ČR, 2013),
                            15–16.</note> The reasons were manifold. First, demonstrations and
                        protests traditionally centred round the statue of St Wenceslas, which had
                        been separated from the parliament’s building by a busy crossroad and an
                        urban motorway constructed in the late 1970. Second, the demonstrators
                        rather turned their attention to the organs of the Communist Party and the
                        media headquarters, by which they assessed the parliament’s significance in
                        the political system quite appropriately, as it seemed. And third, the
                        Federal Assembly itself did neither try to join in the revolution nor did it
                        stand up openly to hold it back. </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-17">As a result, for almost two weeks following the police
                        action against the student demonstration at Národní Street, and the
                        consequent student strike and an establishment of the revolutionary
                        movements it seemed that the life in the parliamentary building went on as
                        if nothing was happening and no crowds of thousands were to be seen from the
                        windows. The sessions of committees were held according to a yearly schedule
                        adopted in late 1988, dealing with draft bills prepared by the government,
                        most often without any notice to the events spreading through the
                            country.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn8" n="7">APCR, FA-5,
                            Minutes of Committee on Industry, Transport and Trade, 22nd meeting,
                            November 20–23, 1989.</note> In reality, there were fierce fights about
                        what to do inside the Communist Party. The Civic Forum, on the other hand,
                        feared that an activated parliament might quickly pass the reformist
                        legislation prepared by the Communist government. Yet since no clear
                        guideline came, the socialist parliament chose to exemplify stability,
                        political decency, and expert knowledge and organization in what it
                        perceived as potentially chaotic situation.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-18">In reality, however, the Federal Assembly had been
                        experiencing a considerable change of atmosphere, attitudes and roles
                        throughout the late 1980s. It is certainly true that the Czechoslovak
                        Communist Party was extremely reluctant as it came to transferring Mikhail
                        Gorbachev’s <hi rend="italic">perestroika</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                            >glasnost</hi> from the Soviet Union. For Czechoslovak leaders, these
                        policies fatefully resembled the Prague Spring reforms, the suppression of
                        which brought them to power. But reforms in general were perceived as
                        necessary, and the federal parliament became one of the few official
                        political arenas where the principles of <hi rend="italic">perestroika</hi>
                        were to be tested and presented. The committees and chambers found
                        themselves under pressure exerted by the government: the parliamentary
                        bodies were expected to pass the drafts of economic reform regulations
                        quickly and smoothly, while at the same time showing “a spirit of openness”.
                        Pressure also came from the public: members of parliament were bound to
                        participate at numerous meetings in their constituencies, and in these
                        years, they met immediate critique wherever they showed up.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn9" n="8">See e.g. “Interview of Josef
                            Bartončík, Brno, Dec. 3, 2012,” in <hi rend="italic">Sbírka rozhovorů s
                                bývalými poslanci Federálního shromáždění</hi>, ed. Adéla Gjuričová
                            et. al, (Collection of Interviews of MPs, Institute of Contemporary
                            History, Oral History Centre).</note> The Communist Party Central
                        Committee also pressed on resignation on nine deputies who were either
                        abroad at diplomatic postings or had been ill for a long time. For the first
                        time in forty years, the experimental by-elections of Spring 1989 allowed
                        voters to choose new MPs from a list of two or three candidates.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn10" n="9">František Cigánek,
                            “Předlistopadový parlament ve světle archivní dokumentace,” in <hi
                                rend="italic">Dvě desetiletí před listopadem 89,</hi> ed. Emanuel
                            Mander (Praha: ÚSD AV ČR – Maxdorf, 1993), 57-72.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-19">There were also important internal shifts. The
                        parliament itself used the new setting of <hi rend="italic">perestroika</hi>
                        to emancipate from the government’s automatic expectations of loyalty if not
                        obedience. Respective ministers, presenting the government drafts in the
                        committees, were confronted with parliamentary criticism of not respecting
                        the MPs’ standpoints as well as with pointing to specific shortages of
                        consumer goods or poor quality of public services.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-129-ftn11" n="10">See e.g. Minutes of Constitutional and
                            Legal Affairs Committee, 18th meeting, May 29–June 6, 1989 (APCR, FA-5)
                            which demonstrates both the growing length of sessions as well as the
                            endless scope of criticism.</note> The parliament grew more active in
                        quantitative sense as well. More legislation was passed. In 1988, for the
                        first time since 1971, a plenary session took as long as three days.
                        Nonetheless, the principle of the parliament being subjected to the
                        Communist Party Central Committee and to “the needs of the government” had
                        never been seriously conceptually challenged.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-129-article-sub02">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-129-head-9">Socialist Parliamentarism</head>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-20">It is difficult to evaluate the power effect of these
                        changes since parliaments occupied a highly ambiguous position in
                        state-socialist systems. By 1948, as the Czechoslovak socialist dictatorship
                        came to being, the original radical scepticism of Marx’s, tending to propose
                        a complete break-down of parliamentary system, had been abandoned. The
                        Communist movement adopted a more pragmatic Leninist interpretation that
                        stressed the Marxist requirement of “conversion of the representative
                        institutions from talking shops into ‘working’ bodies” that would be
                        “executive and legislative at the same time”.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-129-ftn12" n="11">Karl Marx, <hi rend="italic">Civil War in
                                France</hi>, Chapter 5 [The Paris Commune], accessed October 30,
                            2015, <ref
                                target="https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1871/civil-war-france/index.htm"
                                >https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1871/civil-war-france/index.htm</ref>.
                            Cf. Vladimir Ilyich Lenin, <hi rend="italic">The State and Revolution:
                                Experience of the Paris Commune of 1871. Marx’s Analysis,</hi>
                            Chapter 3, accessed October 30, 2015, <ref
                                target="https://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1917/staterev/ch03.htm"
                                >https://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1917/staterev/ch03.htm</ref>.
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-21">Along the post-war Stalinist guideline, the Communist
                        parties infiltrated the existing parliaments and after taking over converted
                        them into representative bodies of the Soviet type under direct Party
                            control.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn13" n="12">For
                            Czechoslovakia, see e.g. Karel Kaplan, <hi rend="italic">Národní fronta
                                1948-1960</hi> (Praha: Academia, 2012), 100–101.</note> Parliaments
                        stopped calling themselves parliaments and were referred to as
                        “representative assemblies”. Their composition was no longer derived purely
                        from party electoral support: the bodies needed to mirror the society in a
                        more literal sense. This system of the so called descriptive representation
                        produced parliaments consisting of deputies who reflected the society’s
                        occupation, gender, ethnic and age structure to a considerable extent – as
                        opposed to mere political preference expressed by bourgeois parliaments.
                        However, finding such matrix of candidates, some of whom had to combine
                        several categories, was a challenging task as well as in fact a substitute
                        for the electoral process. The actual election only approved the candidates
                        included in a single list of the National Front.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-22">While rejecting the whole concept of separation of –
                        executive, legislative, and judicial – powers and offering one, unified
                        power representing the working people, the Communist doctrine also abolished
                        the exclusiveness of the parliament in the political system to a
                        considerable extent. Even the federal parliament of the late-socialist
                        Czechoslovakia was “merely” the supreme level of the united system of
                        representative organs. The system, stretching from the Federal Assembly and
                        the two sub-federal National Councils to the National Committees at local,
                        municipal and district levels, both adopted the norms and put them into
                            practice.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn14" n="13">Jan Bartuška,
                                <hi rend="italic">Státní právo Československé republiky</hi> (Praha:
                            Státní nakladatelství učebnic, 1952), 39, 74–75. Cf. František Koranda
                            et al., <hi rend="italic">Slovník socialistického poslance</hi> (Praha:
                            Svoboda, 1985), 152–156, 436–437.</note> The joint legislative and
                        executive role was also expressed through a specific concept of the mandate.
                        Members of parliament were understood as “elected political and state
                        functionaries” obliged to work in the constituency as well as in the
                        representative body and other state institutions. They would bring the
                        working people’s inputs in the parliament, inform the people about
                        legislative work as well as observe how the laws work in the constituency.
                        They were under the voters’ direct control: Those who did not work
                        appropriately could be dismissed by voters any time.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-129-ftn15" n="14">Koranda et al., <hi rend="italic"
                                >Slovník</hi>, 225-226.</note> This extreme focus on direct
                        accountability obviously created a very weak mandate which served the
                        purpose of Party control over the parliament. The system also tended to
                        include the legislature in the system of state administration,<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn16" n="15">Jan Bartuška et al., <hi
                                rend="italic">Státní právo Československé republiky</hi> (Praha:
                            Orbis, 1953), 244–245.</note> forgetting about its originally
                        self-governing principle.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-23">This notion of parliament, established in the Stalinist
                        era of Czechoslovak socialism and fundamentally different from the liberal
                        democratic parliamentarism, did not substantially change through adoption of
                        the new constitution of 1960. The federalization of 1968 only formally
                        replaced the national tier by the federal one and added one more at the
                        level of the Czech and Slovak Republics. The collapse of the Prague Spring
                        reforms, however, diminished the federal aspect of the structure to
                        something similar as “compulsory figures” that political actors had to
                        practice on formally given occasions. The general concept of the
                        representative structure, through which the sovereign people execute state
                        power, remained the core of representative legitimacy until 1989.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-24">As a result, the Velvet Revolution encountered an
                        established system of federal and sub-federal parliaments which had strong
                        formal powers, as they occupied the status of supreme state bodies, but in
                        practice were not expected to seek any stronger power position at the
                        expense of the Communist Party. Neither did the two levels share much real
                        power: the federal tier possessed most of it, a fact producing much
                        reluctance on the Slovak side. However, the parliament’s formal strength
                        represented a major obstacle to what was nicknamed the “articled
                            revolution”<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn17" n="16">Roubal, <hi
                                rend="italic">Starý pes</hi>, 27-32. On the origin of the nickname,
                            Valtr Komárek, “Děkujeme, přijďte,” in <hi rend="italic">Pocta Zdeňkovi
                                Jičínskému k 80. narozeninám</hi>, ed. Vladimír Mikule et al.
                            (Praha: ASPI, 2009), 294.</note>, i.e. a quick and negotiated régime
                        change which sought to respect the country’s legislation at the same time.
                        Petr Roubal’s article in this issue of <hi rend="italic">Contributions to
                            Contemporary History</hi> also explains the federal parliament’s
                        reconstruction by co-optation as a response to the same problem.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn18" n="17">Petr Roubal, “Revolution by
                            the law: Transformation of the Czechoslovak Federal Assembly” in this
                            issue.</note> Another aspect of the clash of the Velvet Revolution and
                        the socialist parliament, namely the parliament’s amalgamation with the
                        National Front, the permanent coalition of the Communist Party and its
                        satellites, and the specific parliamentary mathematics directing the
                        revolution, is analysed by Tomáš Zahradníček further in the issue.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn19" n="18">Tomáš Zahradníček, “Debates
                            were to be held in the Parliament, but it proved impossible” in this
                            issue.</note> In other words, the revolutionary movement found itself
                        next to a highly unpopular socialist parliament which it did not control,
                        but which it desperately needed in order to pass any legislative amendment.
                        As a way out of the gridlock, the revolutionary parliament was set up as an
                        interim form between the socialist and liberal democratic parliaments.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-129-article-sub03">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-129-head-10">New MPs for a New Era<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-129-ftn20" n="19">“Nová doba – noví poslanci,” <hi
                                rend="italic">Svobodné slovo</hi>, January 31, 1990, 1.</note>
                    </head>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-25">In late January 1990, a special law was passed which
                        allowed that about half of all members of the federal parliament, if they
                        were not willing to resign by themselves, could be deprived of their
                        mandate, “following their previous activity” or “in the interest of a
                        balanced distribution of political powers”. New MPs, who supposedly provided
                        “better guarantees of developing political democracy”, were co-opted.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn21" n="20">Act No. 4/1990 Coll., on
                            dismissing deputies of representative bodies and on electing new
                            deputies of the National Committees, Art. I.</note> The result was the
                        establishment of a provisional revolutionary parliament with specific
                        characteristics.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-26">Until that point, all important decisions were made at
                        round tables where the revolutionary forces as well as the up-to-date
                        Communist negotiators were represented. Almost none of them held
                        parliamentary mandates. Now that they gained the seats, the decision-making
                        could be transferred to the legislature. The Parliament had been integrated
                        into politics. But while the political actors as well as the media talked
                        about “urgent tasks for epoch-making times”, in reality, the parliament was
                        given only a limited mandate to meet them. The term was shortened to last
                        only until June 1990 and explicit limits were put on the contents of the
                        legislative work as well. For example, preparing a new democratic
                        constitution was saved for the next, freely elected parliament. The present
                        body was only expected to personify the new “national unity” rejecting and
                        correcting the Communist past.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-27">Since part of the legislative body came from the
                        undemocratic election of 1986 and part was co-opted by revolutionary
                        political parties or movements, it obviously did not match the previous
                        system of representation in the sense of replicating the social structure.
                        However, it was expected to represent society in a different sense. By its
                        voting, the revolutionary parliament was supposed to legalize the changes
                        required by the revolutionary public, be it the ratification of new
                        executive figures, constitutional amendments or laws establishing elementary
                        civic freedoms and principles of political competition. The parliament was
                        to pass over its own autonomy and serve the public. Even President Václav
                        Havel did not approach the MPs as people carrying a mandate or representing
                        certain political organizations or programmes, but as citizens fulfilling
                        their respective duties, “who care for the future of their country rather
                        than their own personal comfort“.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn22"
                            n="21">“President’s Speech in the Federal Assembly, May 9, 1990,” in <hi
                                rend="italic">Projevy z let 1990-1992. Letní přemítání (Spisy sv.
                                6)</hi>, ed. Václav Havel (Praha: Torst, 1999), 133.</note> The
                        irony was that Václav Havel, whose presidential mandate stemmed from the
                        wholly Communist parliament of December 1989, considered himself a much more
                        convincing incarnation of the awakened popular will. The parliament, on the
                        other hand, was only supposed to mediate and legalize that will.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn23" n="22">“President’s Speech in the
                            Federal Assembly, Jan. 23, 1990,” in Havel, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Projevy</hi>, 26.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-28">In spite of this restricting expectation, there were
                        autonomous processes in the parliament that were out of control by external
                        actors, including those with stronger legitimacy. President Havel provided a
                        perfect example. By delivering his first speech to the parliament on 23
                            January,<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn24" n="23">“President’s
                            Speech in the Federal Assembly, Jan. 23, 1990,” in Havel, <hi
                                rend="italic">Projevy</hi>, 25–43. P. Roubal provides a detailed
                            analysis of the speech in his article in this issue, see ref. 17.</note>
                        he wanted to use his authority and dramatic talent to make it quickly pass
                        his proposal of a constitutional amendment which would change the country’s
                        name from Czechoslovak Socialist Republic to Czechoslovak Republic. But he
                        was not aware of the current struggle the chambers were engaged in and
                        neither did he have the “expert” knowledge of procedure, expecting that he
                        would “storm in and before they wake up, they will have passed my
                            proposal”<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn25" n="24">For versions
                            of the quote and further analysis of Havel’s entry into parliament see
                            Jiří Suk, <hi rend="italic">Konstituční, nebo existenciální revoluce?
                                Václav Havel a Federální shromáždění 1989–1990</hi> (Praha: ÚSD AV
                            ČR, 2014), 36.</note>. In fact, he had staged his performance much
                        better than that. While young pretty hostesses brought an oversize model of
                        the new state symbols, he gave a speech of high literary quality. Yet no
                        success followed. Not only was the President referred to the committees and
                        the legal procedure, but in effect, he set off the so called “hyphen war”
                        between the Czech and Slovak political élites that lasted for months. The
                        Slovaks expected a deeper change of the federal system than just letting out
                        a word from the state’s name. But as of this moment, they explicitly
                        demanded a hyphen and a capital S in the word Czecho-Slovak.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-29">This is only one example of the emancipation of the
                        federal parliament which was, under the provisional and limited-mandate
                        appearance, in fact negotiating and establishing a new democratic
                        parliamentary procedure that would better express the parliament’s changing
                        position within the political system. Until June 1990, the Federal Assembly
                        was seeking a new relation to the President, the Government, the Czech and
                        Slovak National Councils, the Czech and Slovak publics and the media. And it
                        also experienced a first tough election campaign on parliamentary soil. The
                        revolutionary parliament as defined above inhabited this difficult
                        environment together with remnants of the socialist parliament as well as
                        images and first attributes of the liberal democratic one. The three
                        parliaments co-existed.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-129-article-sub04">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-129-head-11">Laboratory of Professionalization</head>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-30">Czechoslovak politics in 1990 had immense tasks to
                        complete – pass enormous amounts of legislation, build up political parties,
                        find a balance between political institutions without the Communist Party
                        dominance, set up a non-destructive relationship with the media etc. – and
                        it did not have an established professional political class. Most of the
                        political professionals from the socialist era have been discredited and
                        replaced by new people. Parliaments became the main arena in which
                        professionalization of the new political élites took place. This important
                        social process can generally be defined as assimilation of the standards and
                        values prevalent in a given profession. Every profession, including
                        politics, tends to have some set or sets of values which determine what it
                        means to be a professional in that field.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-129-ftn26" n="25">Gordon S. Black, “A Theory of
                            Professionalization in Politics,” <hi rend="italic">The American
                                Political Science Review</hi> 3 (1970): 865–878.</note> When
                        successful, it also involves certain power, prestige, income, social status
                        and privileges. Within parliaments, we will therefore operationalize it
                        through observing the legal regulation of the mandate execution as a job,
                        the special skills that deputies have to acquire, and their group
                        identity.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-31">Professionalism in the sense of special skills and
                        expert knowledge was a factor present even in the socialist parliament.
                        Although as was shown previously, the actual power was difficult to measure,
                        making a professional impression became a crucial imperative in the late
                        state-socialism. The Communist Party evaluators used to express it through
                        the requirements of “thorough preparation”, “successful coordination” of
                        speeches and “high quality” of the sessions.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-129-ftn27" n="26">See e.g. speech by Richard Nejezchleb,
                            Minutes of the Defence and Security Committee, 4th meeting, Feb. 4, 1987
                            (APCR, FA-5). Cf. speech by Dalibor Hanes, Minutes of the Presidium, 2nd
                            meeting, June 24, 1986 (APCR, FA-5).</note> The interviews of MPs of the
                        time show what a key element of their collective identity it was. For them,
                        the main disillusionment associated with the 1989 revolution was exactly the
                        disruption of this professionalism producing chaos and a lack of awareness
                        of procedure and of good manners.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn28"
                            n="27">See e.g. “Interview of Štefánia Michalková, Bratislava, Nov. 15,
                            2011,” in Gjuričová, <hi rend="italic">Sbírka rozhovorů.</hi>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-32">For the revolutionary parliament, continuity seemed out
                        of reach. Approximately half of the deputies were replaced by new ones
                        through co-opting in January1990. The first free elections in June changed
                        the parliament painstakingly once again: three quarters of the elected
                        deputies were newcomers. The continuity of parliamentary work – which
                        involved immense legislative tasks of re-introducing democratic procedures
                        in state administration as well as numerous elements of retribution – was
                        more or less provided by the parliament’s administration, the Federal
                        Assembly Office. Historical legitimacies made things even more complicated:
                        first, employees expelled from the administration after 1968 were accepted
                        back, and then, if things were not going well, conspiracy by the Communist
                        Secret Service was declared to be the reason and alleged collaborators of
                        the Secret Service found among the employees. The revolutionary
                        professionalism was therefore a remarkable mix of old and new, skilled and
                        inexperienced, and of victims of retribution and new, supposedly
                        democracy-protecting purges.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-33">The question of formal professionalization of the
                        highly time-consuming parliamentary occupation had been discussed since the
                        beginning of 1990, but was seriously solved only after the summer general
                        election. Being a deputy became a regular paid job. The salary that the
                        parlamentarians approved for themselves was about three times the usual
                        wage. This became one of the first income inequalities that the
                        post-Communist public was exposed to<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-129-ftn29" n="28">Act No. 304/1990 Col., on salary and
                            reimbursement of expenses of deputies of the Federal Assembly. For
                            figures concerning the income see e.g. “Czech Statistical Office,”
                            accessed October 30, 2015, <ref
                                target="http://csugeo.i-server.cz/csu/dyngrafy.nsf/graf/mzdy_1960_"
                                >http://csugeo.i-server.cz/csu/dyngrafy.nsf/graf/mzdy_1960_</ref>.</note>
                        and caused a storm of criticism in the media. On the other hand,
                        interrupting one’s previous job at this point for a two-year mandate
                        basically meant leaving it for good, since returning into professional
                        context dramatically changed by the social and economic transformation
                        turned out to be practically impossible. </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-34">There was yet another paradox. While the public and the
                        media expressed their expectation from the parliament to do a professional
                        job for a professional salary, on the other hand, specific anti-professional
                        ethic was widely shared. In this period, it seemed that in order to cut the
                        link with the Communist era, the political sphere needed people with no
                        political experience, leadership or legal education, people who do not wish
                        to become politicians, but are willing to temporarily sacrifice themselves
                        for the good of others. This approach was very close to the prevailing
                        dissident rhetoric embodied by Václav Havel. But it became one of the
                        decisive factors in the process of disintegration of the revolutionary
                        catch-all movements. In the new parliamentary term, there was a completely
                        new set of skills to acquire. Clubs organized along the immature electoral
                        lists of wide anti-Communist movements began to fall apart in real time at
                        the Federal Assembly meetings as of 1990 and re-organize into a number of
                        political fractions. The segment of post-socialist parliamentary élite that
                        was building up political parties worshipped new professionalism by which it
                        openly protested against the dissident political and historical
                        legitimacy-based amateurism.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn30" n="29"
                            >Magdalena Hadjiisky, “Vznik občanské demokratické strany: Pokus o
                            sociologickou analýzu,” in <hi rend="italic">Kapitoly z dějin české
                                demokracie po roce 1989,</hi> ed. Adéla Gjuričová et. al. (Praha,
                            Litomyšl: Paseka, 2008), 68–90. Srov. Michal Kopeček, “Disent jako
                            minulost, liberalismus jako projekt. Občanské hnutí – Svobodní demokraté
                            v české polistopadové politice,” in <hi rend="italic">Rozděleni
                                minulostí. Vytváření politických identit v České republice po roce
                                1989</hi>, ed. Adéla Gjuričová et. al. (Praha: Knihovna Václava
                            Havla, 2011), 61–106.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-35">Similarly as in case of other issues mentioned above,
                        even in case of political professionalization, the Czech and Slovak élites
                        employed quite different and sometimes incompatible strategies. While the
                        Czech post-socialist activists relied upon the federal level to bring them a
                        long-term political perspective, the Slovak leaders opted for sub-federal
                        institutions of the Slovak Republic in Bratislava. Being kicked-up to the
                        federal parliament in Prague was perceived as risky by Slovak politicians.
                        Because of long sessions in Prague, they grew isolated from Slovak politics
                        which were going through a dramatic transformation.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-129-ftn31" n="30">See e.g. Gabriela Rothmayerová, <hi
                                rend="italic">Zo zápisníka poslankyne</hi> (Bratislava: Perex,
                            1992), 36.</note> In the Slovak society, there was also widespread
                        distrust to the so called “federal” Slovaks based in Prague. And no wonder
                        the Czech MPs felt distant from their Slovak counterparts who showed
                        constant dissatisfaction with the functioning of the federal system and who
                        used parliamentary procedure pragmatically to push through their partial
                        Slovak interests. The Czech MPs said they were identified with the federal
                        state, but, as will be further explained, even in this respect, reality
                        proved to be more complicated.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-129-article-sub05">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-129-head-12">A constituent assembly that never adopted a
                        constitution</head>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-36">From the very moment Czechoslovakia was established in
                        1918, the two nations‘ respective shares in governing the country had been
                        problematic. The Czechs tended to dominate in the country they created for
                        both themselves and the Slovaks who, on the other hand, showed reluctance
                        and took any strategy to oppose the Czech domination. The federalization was
                        a surprisingly radical constitutional transformation of the country that was
                        passed by parliament in October 1968, but was not preceded by any
                        substantial debate among both experts and the public. The surprisingly easy
                        Czech consent might have been caused by the shock of the military
                            invasion.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn32" n="31">Tomáš
                            Zahradníček, “Federalization – The Path to Demise,” <hi rend="italic"
                                >Aspen Review. Central Europe</hi> 1 (2013): 25–30.</note> But it
                        soon became clear that in the post-1968 Czechoslovakia very little would
                        change in the day-to-day business of governance. As a result, when the
                        Czechs claimed they were identified with federal Czechoslovakia in the
                        1990s, what they had in mind was the usual Czech centralism.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-37">The tension between Slovak and Czech political
                        representations of revolutionary publics could be felt from the very outset
                        of the 1989 revolution. Soon the former manifested that redistribution of
                        powers between the federal and republics’ institutions was a primary issue
                        of a democratic transformation, while the latter saw this as an obstacle to
                        more urgent tasks of democratization and de-communization and showed
                        surprise. For several weeks the problem seemed to lie in the different
                        position of the Civic Forum vs. the Slovak Public Against Violence within
                        their respective publics and a much easier incorporation of former socialist
                        elites in Slovakia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn33" n="32">See e.g.
                            Jiří Suk, <hi rend="italic">Labyrintem revoluce. Aktéři, zápletky a
                                křižovatky jedné politické krize (od listopadu 1989 do června
                                1990)</hi> (Praha: Prostor, 2003), 170–180. </note> At least since
                        the hyphen war, however, it was obvious that a serious reform of the federal
                        system, including a substantial redistribution of powers would be
                        necessary.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-38">Although this was never said explicitly, the
                        federalization of 1968 in fact involved the demise of the original
                        Czechoslovakia and two new republics, a Czech and a Slovak one, each with
                        its own citizenship, parliament and government, came into being on the
                        territory of the previously united country. As the unicameral National
                        Assembly was replaced with a bicameral Federal Assembly, its two chambers
                        were given equal authority, and one of them, the Chamber of the Nations,
                        contained an equal number of Czechs and Slovaks. Moreover, certain decisions
                        required the majority consent of each half (Czech and Slovak) of the Chamber
                        of the Nations. Now that the Communist Party domination was over, this
                        resulted in that half of the Slovak part of the Chamber was able to block
                        any important decision.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-39">The revolutionary parliament experienced this during
                        the hyphen war, when it seemed impossible to agree on any version of the
                        state’s new name. Other federalization issues, all of them highly
                        controversial, were left up to the next, freely elected parliament. Only
                        this legislature was supposed to have the legitimacy to draft a new
                        constitution for both nations and a federation for the new era. However, the
                        existing federal system, originally created only to formally express
                        equality between the Czechs and Slovaks, could not stand the democratic
                        practice. No matter how sophisticated processes of constitution making and
                        its negotiating the federal parliament created,<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-129-ftn34" n="33">See the files of the Commission of Members
                            of the Federal Assembly, the Czech and Slovak National Councils for
                            Preparation of the Constitution and the Expert Commission for Drafting
                            the Constitution, 1990–1991, Federal Assembly 6<hi rend="superscript"
                                >th</hi> term Collection, Archives of the Parliament of the Czech
                            Republic.</note> for the reasons described above – the simultaneous
                        emancipation of parliament(s) from other institutions, re-building the
                        party-political spectrum and creating new political élites involving
                        different strategies of the Czech and Slovak political élites – they were
                        never shared by both national political communities. The Federal Assembly
                        remained isolated from Slovak politics – and allergic reactions to the
                        ongoing bargaining developed on both sides.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-40">President Havel tried to intervene and mediated many of
                        the negotiations between the Czech and Slovak representations. He felt
                        personally responsible for the success of the deals. He supported the
                        process by inviting experts from abroad and hosting their informal meetings,
                        and partly undermined it by having his own version of constitution drafted
                        and trying to get it through the parliament which by then had been blocked
                        up against him.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-129-ftn35" n="34">Adéla
                            Gjuričová, “Anti-politics and anti-parliamentarism: Václav Havel and the
                            Czechoslovak parliament in the 1990s” (paper presented at the conference
                                <hi rend="italic">Parlamentarismuskritik und Antiparlamentarismus in
                                Europa</hi>, Berlin, May 7–8, 2015).</note> The new constitution was
                        never adopted, and the Czecho-Slovak bargaining led to no conclusion.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-41">The next election took place in 1992. It witnessed a
                        professional campaign and produced stable political fractions and a
                        parliament of self-confident and experienced professionals. The Slovak
                        election winner Vladimír Mečiar had ignored the federal parliament for long,
                        however, this assembly did neither include some of the more foresighted
                        Czech leaders such as Václav Klaus, whose party won in the Czech lands, but
                        who himself ran for a seat in the Czech National Council. The federal
                        parliament found itself to be the only remaining federal institution in an
                        ever more fractioned Czechoslovakia. And it also turned out to be the only
                        institution that could once again legalize what had been decided elsewhere,
                        namely at meetings of election winners behind closed doors. The last thing
                        that the federal parliament was asked to do was to validate the dissolution
                        of the Czechoslovak federation, including a “hara-kiri” dissolution of the
                        parliament itself.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr" xml:id="ojs-129-bibliogr">
                <head xml:id="ojs-129-head-13">Sources and references</head>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-129-bibliogr-sub01">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-129-head-14">Archive sources</head>
                    <list xml:id="ojs-129-listBibl-1">
                        <item>APCR, Archives of the Parliament of the Czech Republic:<list>
                                <item>FA-5, Federal Assembly 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> term
                                    Collection</item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-129-bibliogr-sub02">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-129-head-15">Literature</head>
                    <listBibl xml:id="ojs-129-listBibl-2">
                        <bibl>Ash, Timothy Garton. <hi rend="italic">We the People. The Revolution
                                of ’89 Witnessed in Warsaw, Budapest, Berlin &amp; Prague.</hi>
                            London: Granta Books, 1990.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Bartuška, Jan et al. <hi rend="italic">Státní právo Československé
                                republiky.</hi> Praha: Orbis, 1953.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Bartuška, Jan. <hi rend="italic">Státní právo Československé
                                republiky.</hi> Praha: Státní nakladatelství učebnic, 1952.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Black, S. Gordon. “A Theory of Professionalization in Politics,” <hi
                                rend="italic">The American Political Science Review</hi> 3 (1970):
                            865-878.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Cigánek, František. “Předlistopadový parlament ve světle archivní
                            dokumentace.” In <hi rend="italic">Dvě desetiletí před listopadem
                                89,</hi> edited by Emanuel Mandler, 57–72. Praha: ÚSD AV ČR –
                            Maxdorf, 1993.</bibl>
                        <bibl>“Czech Statistical Office.” Accessed October 30, 2015. <ref
                                target="http://csugeo.i-server.cz/csu/dyngrafy.nsf/graf/mzdy_1960_"
                                >http://csugeo.i-server.cz/csu/dyngrafy.nsf/graf/mzdy_1960_</ref>.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Gjuričová, Adéla. “Anti-politics and anti-parliamentarism: Václav
                            Havel and the Czechoslovak parliament in the 1990s”. Paper presented at
                            the conference <hi rend="italic">Parlamentarismuskritik und
                                Antiparlamentarismus in Europa</hi>, Berlin, May 7–8, 2015.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hadjiisky, Magdalena. “Vznik občanské demokratické strany: Pokus o
                            sociologickou analýzu.” In <hi rend="italic">Kapitoly z dějin české
                                demokracie po roce 1989,</hi> edited by Adéla Gjuričová, Michal
                            Kopeček, 68–90. Praha – Litomyšl: Paseka, 2008.</bibl>
                        <bibl>“Interview of Josef Bartončík, Brno, Dec. 3, 2012.” In <hi
                                rend="italic">Sbírka rozhovorů s bývalými poslanci Federálního
                                shromáždění,</hi> edited by Adéla Gjuričová, Petr Roubal, Jiří Suk,
                            Tomáš Zahradníček. Collection of Interviews of MPs, Institute of
                            Contemporary History, Oral History Centre.</bibl>
                        <bibl>“Interview of Štefánia Michalková, Bratislava, Nov. 15, 2011.” In <hi
                                rend="italic">Sbírka rozhovorů s bývalými poslanci Federálního
                                shromáždění,</hi> edited by Adéla Gjuričová, Petr Roubal, Jiří Suk,
                            Tomáš Zahradníček. Collection of Interviews of MPs, Institute of
                            Contemporary History, Oral History Centre.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Kaplan, Karel. <hi rend="italic">Národní fronta 1948–1960.</hi> Praha:
                            Academia, 2012.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Komárek, Valtr. “Děkujeme, přijďte.” In <hi rend="italic">Pocta
                                Zdeňkovi Jičínskému k 80. narozeninám,</hi> edited by Vladimír
                            Mikule, Radovan, Suchánek, 294–296. Praha: ASPI, 2009.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Kopeček, Michal. “Disent jako minulost, liberalismus jako projekt.
                            Občanské hnutí – Svobodní demokraté v české polistopadové politice.” In
                                <hi rend="italic">Rozděleni minulostí. Vytváření politických identit
                                v České republice po roce 1989</hi>, edited by Adéla Gjuričová,
                            Michal Kopeček, Petr Roubal, Jiří Suk, Tomáš Zahradníček, 61-106. Praha:
                            Knihovna Václava Havla, 2011.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Koranda František et al. <hi rend="italic">Slovník socialistického
                                poslance.</hi> Praha: Svoboda, 1985.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Lenin, Ilyich Vladimir. <hi rend="italic">The State and Revolution:
                                Experience of the Paris Commune of 1871. Marx’s Analysis,</hi>
                            Chapter 3. Accessed October 30, 2015. <ref
                                target="https://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1917/staterev/ch03.htm"
                                >https://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1917/staterev/ch03.htm</ref>.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Marx, Karl. <hi rend="italic">Civil War in France</hi>, Chapter 5 [The
                            Paris Commune]. Accessed Oct. 30, 2015. <ref
                                target="https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1871/civil-war-france/index.htm"
                                >https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1871/civil-war-france/index.htm</ref>.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Photos of the project by Karel Prager, Jiří Kadeřábek and Jiří
                            Albrecht. “Federal Assembly Building at Wenceslas Square, Prague.”
                            Accessed October 30, 2015, <ref
                                target="http://www.parliamentsintransition.cz/dokumenty/federalassemblybuildingatwenceslassquareprague"
                                >http://www.parliamentsintransition.cz/dokumenty/federalassemblybuildingatwenceslassquareprague</ref>. </bibl>
                        <bibl>Powell, Walter W., and Paul J. DiMaggio. <hi rend="italic">The New
                                Institutionalism in Organizational Analysis.</hi> London, Chicago:
                            Chicago UP, 1991. </bibl>
                        <bibl>“President’s Speech in the Federal Assembly, Jan. 23, 1990.” In<hi
                                rend="italic"> Projevy z let 1990–1992. Letní přemítání (Spisy sv.
                                6)</hi>, edited by Vaclav Havel, 25-43, Praha: Torst, 1999. </bibl>
                        <bibl>“President’s Speech in the Federal Assembly, May 9, 1990.” In <hi
                                rend="italic">Projevy z let 1990-1992. Letní přemítání (Spisy sv.
                                6)</hi>, edited by Vaclav Havel, 132–136. Praha: Torst, 1999.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Rothmayerová, Gabriela. <hi rend="italic">Zo zápisníka
                                poslankyne.</hi> Bratislava: Perex, 1992.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Roubal, Petr. <hi rend="italic">Starý pes, nové kousky: kooptace do
                                Federálního shromáždění a vytváření polistopadové politické
                                kultury.</hi> Praha: Ústav pro soudobé dějiny AV ČR, 2013.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Suk, Jiří. <hi rend="italic">Konstituční, nebo existenciální revoluce?
                                Václav Havel a Federální shromáždění 1989–1990.</hi> Praha: ÚSD AV
                            ČR, 2014.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Suk, Jiří. <hi rend="italic">Labyrintem revoluce. Aktéři, zápletky a
                                křižovatky jedné politické krize (od listopadu 1989 do června
                                1990).</hi> Praha: Prostor, 2003.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Zahradníček, Tomáš. “Federalization – The Path to Demise,” <hi
                                rend="italic">Aspen Review. Central Europe</hi> 1 (2013):
                            25–30.</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-129-bibliogr-sub03">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-129-head-16">Newspaper sources</head>
                    <listBibl xml:id="ojs-129-listBibl-3">
                        <bibl>
                            <hi rend="italic">Svobodné slovo.</hi> “Nová doba – noví poslanci.”
                            January 31, 1990, 1.</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-129-bibliogr-sub04">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-129-head-17">Other sources</head>
                    <listBibl xml:id="ojs-129-listBibl-4">
                        <bibl>Act No. 4/1990 Coll., on dismissing deputies of representative bodies
                            and on electing new deputies of the National Committees, Art. I.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Act No. 304/1990 Col., on salary and reimbursement of expenses of
                            deputies of the Federal Assembly.</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="summary"  xml:id="ojs-129-summary" xml:lang="sl">
                <head xml:id="ojs-129-head-19">Povzetek</head>
                <head xml:id="ojs-129-head-18" rend="subtitle">(Kratko) življenje: Češkoslovaški
                    parlament 1989–1992</head>
                <docAuthor xml:id="ojs-129-docAuthor-3">Adéla Gjuričová</docAuthor>
                <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-42">Češkoslovaški zvezni parlament je bil vzpostavljen leta
                    1968, da bi nadomestil državni zbor unitaristične države in tako formalno
                    izrazil enakopravnost Čehov in Slovakov v novoustanovljeni federaciji. Po zlomu
                    reform praške pomladi je socialistični parlament izgubil večino suverenosti,
                    ohranil pa je zvezni značaj in formalne postopke, ter tako predstavljal nekakšno
                    »podporno« zakonodajno telo. Leta 1989 je žametna revolucija, ki se je
                    opredelila za spoštovanje miru in zakonitosti, v središču nove politike, ki je
                    nazadnje pripeljala do razdružitve Češkoslovaške, seveda našla parlament starega
                    režima.</p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-43">V članku je uporabljen neoinstitucionalni pristop, ki
                    dojema odnose med institucijami in njihovimi akterji kot interaktivne. Parlament
                    se tako opazuje kot »ranljivo« okolje, ki nenehno išče ravnovesje med veljavnimi
                    pravili, institucionalnimi predpisi in miti ter sedanjimi in nekdanjimi
                    poslanci, njihovimi pričakovanji, prepričanji in samopodobami. S tega stališča
                    lahko v razvoju zveznega parlamenta ob koncu osemdesetih in na začetku
                    devetdesetih let 20. stoletja razločimo tri faze, ki so opisane v članku: prva
                    faza – socialistični parlament, ki je izhajal iz stalinistične doktrine in so ga
                    omajale reforme perestrojke; druga faza – revolucionarni parlament, ki ga je
                    vzpostavilo revolucionarno gibanje in se je znašel ob strani zelo
                    nepriljubljenega socialističnega parlamenta, ki ga je potreboval, ni pa ga
                    nadzoroval; tretja faza – liberalno-demokratični parlament, ki je bil skupni
                    teoretični ideal, vendar ni dobil dolgotrajne možnosti za razvoj. Te trije
                    parlamenti naj bi soobstajali in delovali vzajemno.</p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-129-p-44">Češkoslovaška politika je morala leta 1990 opraviti izjemno
                    veliko nalog – sprejeti je morala ogromne količine zakonodaje, vzpostaviti
                    politične stranke, najti ravnovesje med političnimi institucijami brez nadvlade
                    komunistične partije, vzpostaviti neškodljive odnose z mediji itd. – ni pa imela
                    izoblikovanega profesionalnega političnega razreda. Parlamenti so postali glavno
                    prizorišče profesionalizacije novih političnih elit. Vendar pa so češke in
                    slovaške elite v tem procesu uporabljale precej različne in včasih nezdružljive
                    strategije. To je veljalo tudi za številne druge vidike postsocialistične
                    preobrazbe: češka in slovaška javnost ter politični predstavniki so dojemali in
                    sprejemali politične koncepte in prakse na nasprotujoče si načine. Nekatere od
                    teh razlik so se izkazale za nezdružljive in zvezni parlament je nazadnje
                    odigral ključno vlogo pri vodenju razdružitve češkoslovaške federacije leta
                    1992.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
