<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en" xml:id="ojs-125">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a">The 10th Volkskammer of the GDR – Just a Keen Student or a
                    Parliament with its Own Culture?</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Bettina</forename>
                        <surname>Tüffers</surname>
                    </name>
                    <roleName>researcher</roleName>
                    <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Kommission für Geschichte des Parlamentarismus und der politischen
                        Parteien</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Schiffbauerdamm 40</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>10117 Berlin</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Germany</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>tueffers@kgparl.de</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2015-12-09</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/125</pubPlace>
                <date>2015</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="PID">sistory.36116</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>GDR</term>
                    <term>parliament</term>
                    <term>German unification</term>
                    <term>federalism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>NDR</term>
                    <term>parlament</term>
                    <term>nemška združitev</term>
                    <term>federalizem</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2015-12-09</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article" n="Articles">
        <front>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart>The 10th Volkskammer of the GDR – Just a Keen Student or a Parliament
                        with its Own Culture?</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <docAuthor>Bettina Tüffers</docAuthor>
                <docImprint>
                    <idno type="cobissType">1.01</idno>
                    <idno type="UDC">328.32(430.3)"1990"</idno>
                </docImprint>
            </titlePage>
            <divGen type="toc" xml:id="ojs-125-toc">
                <head>Table of Contents</head>
            </divGen>
            <divGen type="search" xml:id="ojs-125-search">
                <head>Search</head>
            </divGen>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl" xml:id="ojs-125-izvlecek">
                <head xml:id="ojs-125-head-3">Izvleček</head>
                <head rend="subtitle" xml:id="ojs-125-head-4">10. skupščina NDR – Le zavzeta učenka
                    ali parlament z lastno kulturo?</head>
                <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-6">Zadnji parlament NDR, ki je obstajal le od marca do oktobra
                    1990, se je nedvomno razlikoval od parlamentov v drugih vzhodnoevropskih
                    komunističnih državah. To je bilo povezano s posebnim položajem, ki ga je imel
                    kot parlament  polovice nekdaj enotne države.. Po zmagi konservativcev na
                    volitvah marca 1990 je bilo jasno, da večina volivcev želi čim hitrejšo
                    združitev z Zahodno Nemčijo. Glavna naloga skupščine je bila organizacija tega
                    procesa. Ker je bilo 400 novoizvoljenih poslancev popolnoma neizkušenih, je bilo
                    zgledovanje po nemškem Bundestagu najbrž edina možnost za reševanje težav, s
                    katerimi so se spoprijemali. To pa je pomenilo, da ni bilo veliko priložnosti in
                    časa za razvoj lastnih rešitev. Kritiki so obsežno pomoč zahodnonemških
                    političnih strank in institucij videli kot svojevrstno kolonizacijo. Tudi veliko
                    poslancev je bilo zelo kritičnih do skupščinskega dela. Občutek pomanjkanja
                    vpliva in nemoči je bil vsesplošen, toda obe strani sta bili obenem zmožni
                    dosegati konsenz.</p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-7">Pričujoči članek poskuša odgovoriti na vprašanje, ali je bil
                    ta parlament le prizadeven učenec zahodnonemškega učitelja ali pa je bil kljub
                    okoliščinam sposoben razviti lastno parlamentarno kulturo in držo.</p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-8">Ključne besede: NDR, parlament, nemška združitev,
                    federalizem</p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract" xml:id="ojs-125-abstract">
                <head xml:id="ojs-125-head-5">Abstract</head>
                <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-9">The last parliament of the GDR, the 10. Volkskammer, existed
                    only from March to October 1990 and was undoubtedly different from those in
                    other eastern European communist countries. This had to do with its special
                    situation as the parliament of one half of a former united nation. After the
                    victory of the conservatives in the election of March 1990 it was clear that the
                    majority of voters wanted unification with West Germany according to Art. 23 of
                    the German Constitution and as quickly as possible. This meant reunification by
                    accession of the GDR to the Federal Republic. It was the Volkskammer’s main task
                    to organize this process. Given that the 400 newly elected MPs were completely
                    unexperienced following the model of the German Bundestag was probably the only
                    way to be able to tackle the problems they were faced with. But this meant too
                    that there was little room and no time to develop own solutions to their
                    problems. Critics saw the massive support by West German political parties and
                    institutions as a form of colonization. And a lot of MPs too were highly
                    critical of their work. A feeling of lack of influence and powerlessness was
                    widespread. But, as the example of the reintroduction of the five Länder shows,
                    both sides could pull in the same direction too.</p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-10">This article tries to answer the question whether this
                    parliament was only an assiduous student of its West German master or despite
                    the circumstances able to develop its own culture and its own pace.</p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-11">Keywords: GDR, parliament, German unification,
                    federalism</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="chapter" xml:id="ojs-125-article">
                <head xml:id="ojs-125-head-6">The 10th Volkskammer of the GDR – Just a Keen Student
                    or a Parliament with its Own Culture?</head>
                <docAuthor>Bettina Tüffers<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn1" n="*">researcher,
                        PhD, Kommission für Geschichte des Parlamentarismus und der politischen
                        Parteien (KGParl), Schiffbauerdamm 40, 10117 Berlin, Germany, <ref
                            target="mailto:tueffers@kgparl.de">tueffers@kgparl.de</ref>
                    </note>
                </docAuthor>
                <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-12">The 10th Volkskammer of the GDR was undoubtedly an unusual
                    parliament. It existed for barely six months, from the day of its constitution
                    on 5 April 1990 to 2 October 1990, during which it passed more than 150 laws and
                    100 resolutions at a total of 38 plenary meetings. Key examples include the
                    treaty to establish a monetary, economic and social union with the Federal
                    Republic of Germany, the Unification Treaty, the law governing the introduction
                    of the five Länder (states), and the Stasi-Unterlagen-Gesetz,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ojs-125-ftn2" n="1">“Treaty on the establishment of a monetary,
                        economic and social union between the Federal Republic of Germany and the
                        German Democratic Republic,” <hi rend="italic">Gesetzblatt der Deutschen
                            Demokratischen Republik</hi> 1: 332. “Treaty between the Federal
                        Republic of Germany and the German Democratic Republic on the establishment
                        of German unity,” <hi rend="italic">Gesetzblatt der Deutschen Demokratischen
                            Republik</hi> 1: 1627. “Constitutional law on the formation of states
                        within the German Democratic Republic,” <hi rend="italic">Gesetzblatt der
                            Deutschen Demokratischen Republik</hi> 1: 955. “Law on protecting and
                        using personal data from the former Ministry for State Security/National
                        Security Office,” <hi rend="italic">Gesetzblatt der Deutschen Demokratischen
                            Republik</hi> 1: 1419.</note> although there were also laws on hospital
                    financing, freely financed housing, and the application of a trades and crafts
                    code, just to name a few. As the GDR’s first and last freely elected democratic
                    parliament, it was responsible for organising the East German side of the
                    legally and economically complex German unification process, and in doing so
                    dissolve itself and the state whose citizens it represented. As if this were not
                    enough, the task had to be completed by MPs with next to no experience in the
                    workings of a parliamentary democracy or parliamentary operations. Its history
                    is also made interesting by the fact that the (self-)parliamentarisation process
                    played out in the public eye, i.e. people could watch newly-elected MPs rapidly
                    learning the ropes of their “profession” without the guidance of experienced
                    colleagues. And it literally was a case of “watching”, for televisions were
                    there live at all times.</p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-13">The election win by the conservative “Allianz für
                    Deutschland” (“Alliance for Germany”), a coalition of the Christian Democrats
                    (Christlich Demokratische Union, CDU), the Democratic Awakening (Demokratischer
                    Aufbruch, DA) and the German Social Union (Deutsche Soziale Union, DSU), on 18
                    March 1990 clearly demonstrated that most GDR citizens wanted to be reunified
                    with the Federal Republic, and have their living conditions aligned with the
                    West, as quickly as possible, for the Allianz’s proposed policy had included the
                    demand for a liberal constitutional democracy, the federal unification of
                    Germany as per Article 23 of the West German Basic Law, and a consistent,
                    socially and ecologically-oriented marked economy.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ojs-125-ftn3" n="2">“ʻAllianz für Deutschland’ zu den
                        Volkskammerwahlen am 18. März,” <hi rend="italic">Neue Zeit,</hi> February
                        7, 1990. Article 23 of the German Constitution ʻinitiallyʼ established that
                        the Basic Law applied to the then eleven West German states. “It must be
                        enforced in other parts of Germany on their accession”. The alternative,
                        accession under Art. 146 (“This Basic Law, which, upon Germany’s unification
                        and liberation, applies to the entire German people, shall become invalid on
                        the day a constitution freely decided on by the German people takes
                        effect.”), was particularly preferred by opposition parties PDS and Bündnis
                        90/Grüne.</note> The path to reunification had thus almost been completely
                    set; alternatives, be they any kind of “third way” or the unification as per
                    Article 146 of the Basic Law, were no longer matters for discussion.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn4" n="3">Martin Sabrow, “Der vergessene
                        ‘Dritte Wegʼ,” <hi rend="italic">Aus Politik und Zeitgeschichte</hi> 11
                        (2010): 6–13.</note> The primary task of the 10th Volkskammer was now to
                    adjust rights and structures in every conceivable area. However, given it had to
                    be performed by 400 MPs with no parliamentary experience, help from West Germany
                    was required. </p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-14">This raises the question of whether, in these
                    circumstances, the last Volkskammer of the GDR could have been more than just a
                    keen student of its West German teacher, or whether it still managed to develop
                    its own independent parliamentary profile.</p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-15">The initial position of this parliament will thus first be
                    explained below, before its specific working conditions are then examined. The
                    sections thereafter describe how it geared itself around the West German model,
                    and what role the media played. Finally, the example of the formation of the
                    five new states within the GDR shows that, while the West German model did
                    certainly align with some of the East’s ideals, critical aspects were still
                    dictated by the West.</p>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-125-articel-sub01">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-125-head-7">The initial situation</head>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-16">The constitutive meeting held at 11am on the morning of
                        5 April 1990 marked the start of the final legislative period of a
                        parliament which, until just a few months prior, had not even earned its
                        reputation as such.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn5" n="4">Regarding
                            the Volkskammer, cf. Werner J. Patzelt and Roland Schirmer, ed., <hi
                                rend="italic">Die Volkskammer der DDR. Sozialistischer
                                Parlamentarismus in Theorie und Praxis</hi> (Wiesbaden:
                            Westdeutscher Verlag, 2002). Helmut Müller-Enbergs, “Welchen Charakter
                            hatte die Volkskammer nach den Wahlen am 18. März 1990?,” <hi
                                rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Parlamentsfragen</hi> 22
                            (1991).</note> From the 1st election period in 1950 to the election on
                        18 March 1990, the “old” Volkskammer of the GDR was the perfect example of a
                        so-called socialist representative body and therefore, by definition,
                        fundamentally different to what was known in the GDR as a “bourgeois
                        parliament”. Specifically speaking, this meant there were no career
                        parliamentarians, since MPs worked on a voluntary basis. They convened two,
                        maximum three, times a year in East Berlin for a meeting which lasted not
                        much longer than a day, before returning to their homes and regular places
                        of employment. This was allegedly the only way to guarantee close contact
                        with the working population. There was no separation of powers either.
                        According to the official description, the Volkskammer instead fulfilled
                        “the principle of unity in decision-making and execution. [… A]s a working
                        body, it ensures its decisions are implemented, and exercises control
                            here.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn6" n="5">Herbert Kelle and
                            Tord Riemann, <hi rend="italic">Die Volkskammer – wie sie arbeitet</hi>
                            (Berlin: Staatsverlag der Deutschen Demokratischen Republik, 1989),
                            12.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-17">The GDR’s Constitution stated that it was the highest
                        state power. Until well into the 1980s, Volkskammer elections regularly
                        recorded fantastic participation levels of over 98 percent, with equally
                        fantastic results nudging the 100-percent mark for the unity list
                        (Einheitsliste) of the ten GDR mass organisations and parties pooled under
                        the “National Front”. While bloc parties the CDU, Liberal Democrats
                        (Liberaldemokratische Partei Deutschlands, LDPD), National Democrats
                        (National-Demokratische Partei Deutschlands, NDPD) and the Farmers’ Party
                        (Demokratische Bauernpartei Deutschlands, DBD), as well as mass
                        organisations like the Free German Youth (Freie Deutsche Jugend, FDJ) and
                        the Free German Trade Union Association (Freier Deutscher Gewerkschaftsbund,
                        FDGB), officially masqueraded under the guise of pluralism, the Socialist
                        Unity Party of Germany (Sozialistische Einheitspartei, SED) in fact ran
                        roughshod over them. The allocation of seats was already established before
                        any “election”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn7" n="6">Hans Michael
                            Kloth, <hi rend="italic">Vom ʻZettelfaltenʼ zum freien Wählen: Die
                                Demokratisierung der DDR 1989/90 und die ʻWahlfrageʼ</hi> (Berlin:
                            Links, 2000).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-18">At the start, the Volkskammer hardly ever reacted to
                        what was happening on the streets of the GDR in the autumn of 1989,
                        remaining a loyal supporter of the system for some time.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-125-ftn8" n="7">For the course of events, cf. Ilko-Sascha
                            Kowalzcuk, <hi rend="italic">Endspiel: Die Revolution von 1989 in der
                                DDR</hi> (München: Beck, 2009), chs. II, III.</note> However, the
                        pressure of the increasingly vocal protests and the intensifying economic
                        and political crisis occurring in the country meant it, too, ultimately had
                        to make changes. The first signs of life were slow in coming; even the
                        meeting on 24 October, in which Egon Krenz was elected Erich Honecker’s
                        successor as head of the State Council in a public ballot, followed the same
                        familiar format, albeit introducing dissenting votes and abstentions. But
                        all of a sudden, the MPs themselves insisted on tighter meetings schedules
                        and the formation of enquiry committees, and called for previously withheld
                        information and discussions. The beginnings of a humble democratisation
                        process start to show as of 13 November 1989. In December, the SED’s leading
                        role was omitted from the Constitution.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-125-ftn9" n="8">Cf. the minutes of the last nine meetings of
                            the 9th Volkskammer (October 24, 1989 to March 6/7, 1990). Volkskammer
                            der Deutschen Demokratischen Republik, 9. Wahlperiode, Protokolle, vol.
                            25, 221–556.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-19">In this context, it is interesting to note the MPs’
                        reaction to the Central Round Table (Zentraler Runder Tisch), which had
                        convened since December 1989 and had, the Volkskammer believed, become an
                        ominous rival institution because it performed parliamentary functions and,
                        in the eyes of many, was more legitimate than the Volkskammer.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn10" n="9">Uwe Thaysen, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Der Runde Tisch, Oder: Wo blieb das Volk? Der Weg der DDR in die
                                Demokratie</hi> (Opladen: Westdeutscher Verlag, 1990).</note> While
                        the members of the Volkskammer allowed the attending representatives of
                        civil-rights groups and the old regime to discuss current problems, the
                        decisions were to be made by them alone. They could not, however, stop the
                        Volkskammer from rapidly losing authority, with MPs successively resigning
                        from their positions in the final months.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-20">The main legacy of the 9th Volkskammer is thus said to
                        be that, during the last four months of its existence, it created the legal
                        bases for a somewhat seamless transition into the GDR’s first democratic
                        parliament by virtue of the travel law, citizenship law and, most
                        importantly, the electoral law for the election on 18 March 1990, thereby
                        ensuring “institutional restabilisation following the collapse of the SED
                            supremacy”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn11" n="10">Roland
                            Schirmer, “Machtzerfall und Restabilisierung der Volkskammer im Lauf der
                            Friedlichen Revolution,” in <hi rend="italic">Parlamente und ihre Macht.
                                Kategorien und Fallbeispiele institutioneller Analyse,</hi> ed.
                            Werner J. Patzelt (Baden-Baden: Nomos, 2005), 202.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-21">The outcome of this first free and truly secret
                        election in the GDR is well known: Contrary to all predictions, and most
                        likely to the surprise of most people, the “Allianz für Deutschland” – the
                        coalition between the CDU, DA and DSU – won with 48 percent of votes – well
                        ahead of the Social Democrats (Sozialdemokratische Partei Deutschlands,
                        SPD), who didn’t even receive half (namely 21.9 percent), and ahead of SED
                        successor, the Democratic Socialist Party (Partei des Demokratischen
                        Sozialismus, PDS), with 16.4 percent. Way off the mark were the Liberals
                        with 5.3 percent and Alliance 90/The Green Party (Bündnis 90/Grüne), the
                        coalition of various civil-rights and environmental conservation groups,
                        with 4 percent. Rounding things off were the members of Germany’s Democratic
                        Farmers’ Party (DBD) and the Democratic Women’s Federation of Germany
                        (Demokratischer Frauenbund Deutschlands, DFD) on 2.5 percent, and a single
                        member of the United Left (Vereinigte Linke). On 12 April, the CDU, DA, DSU,
                        Liberals and SPD formed a Grand Coalition, which held a crushing majority of
                        303 to 97 votes in the Volkskammer.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn12"
                            n="11">The balances of power were to shift in summer, when, first the
                            Liberals in July, then the Social Democrats in August, left the
                            Coalition: Barely a month before the Volkskammer ended, the CDU and DSU
                            parties still had 196 delegates, while the opposition parties had 204
                            seats.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-22">The task lying before the 400 newly elected MPs – 409
                        including the successors -<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn13" n="12"
                            >Christopher Hausmann, <hi rend="italic">Biographisches Handbuch der 10.
                                Volkskammer der DDR (1990)</hi> (Köln, Weimar, Wien: Böhlau,
                            2000).</note> was colossal, with little time in which to be completed:
                        The MPs initially assumed they had been elected for a full legislative
                        period of four years. While some estimated more time than others for the
                        unification process, no one expected this Parliament’s lifetime to be as
                        short as six months.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-125-articel-sub02">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-125-head-8">Working conditions</head>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-23">The conditions in which the 10th Volkskammer commenced
                        its work were extremely unfavourable. Not only were the newly elected MPs
                        very unclear as to what they had to do and how to go about it, there were
                        other factors as well. One was that they did not know each other. And this
                        did not just mean that, for example, the members of the SPD party were not
                        aware who their colleagues from the CDU, PDS or Liberals were; even within
                        the individual parties, people initially hardly knew the person sitting in
                        front or next to them. Key functions within the parties, whether these be
                        president, committee chairperson or work-group chairperson, had to be filled
                        without properly assessing whether the candidate was even suited to the
                        task. It was the same story when selecting speakers in the plenum. If, due
                        to lack of experience or information, it was impossible to ascertain the
                        strengths and weaknesses of one’s own members, one was dependent on
                        guesswork and leaps of faith.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-24">For many MPs, it only became clear once actually in
                        Berlin that being elected meant giving up their previous job and performing
                        their new task on a full-time basis, at least for a certain period, whose
                        duration was unknown. While the old Volkskammer was content with two or
                        three meetings a year, meeting frequency now rapidly increased. On average,
                        there was one plenary session a week, often more, plus the usual party,
                        work-group and committee meetings, some special sittings, including on
                        Sundays, with some meetings spanning several consecutive days or lasting
                        well into the night. If many MPs initially assumed they would at least have
                        a few hours during the week to continue pursuing their original career, in
                        keeping with the old GDR ideal of voluntary MPs, they were taught otherwise
                        within the first few days of their attendance in parliament: Adoption of the
                        Western parliamentary model had transformed them into career politicians
                        virtually overnight. A Volkskammer mandate left no time for sideline work.
                        But it also meant the MPs had to be paid for their work, since they had lost
                        their original source of income. The introduction of per-diem allowances was
                        inevitable.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-25">Discussions on this topic particularly revealed the
                        unease many parliamentarians felt at having to set their own income amount.
                        Reinhard Höppner (SPD), chairperson of the work group commissioned with the
                        draft legislation, put this malaise into words: “I’d love to find a way out
                        of it. As a result of having to be the chairperson of this committee, I have
                        ended up in the less than ideal position of now also having to report on it
                            here.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn14" n="13">7th meeting on 17
                            May 1990. ̶ Protokolle der Volkskammer der Deutschen Demokratischen
                            Republik: 10. Wahlperiode (vom 5. April bis 2. Oktober 1990), ed.
                            Deutscher Bundestag, Referat Öffentlichkeitsarbeit (Berlin: 2000),
                            200.</note> Although the Members of Parliament Act (Abgeordnetengesetz)
                        passed through the parliament in two readings, there was no debate on either
                        occasion. As many MPs found the amount inappropriately high (3600 GDR Marks
                        plus 2300 GDR Marks flat allowance, said amount being paid out in D-Marks
                        upon the conversion of currency on 1 July. Members of the old Volkskammer
                        only received an allowance of 500 GDR Marks), they donated part of their
                        income. The per-diem allowances did, however, remain a main point of
                        criticism in public discussions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn15"
                            n="14">See BArch DA 1/16731, the letters to the Volkskammer.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-26">In March 1990, it became clear that MPs coming from
                        outside Berlin required permanent housing where they could not only sleep
                        and eat, but ideally also work. Large-volume accommodation was, however,
                        rare in Berlin at this time, and most MPs ended up living in a former home
                        for single Stasi officers on Ruschestraße in Berlin Lichtenberg. The
                        facility first had to be urgently renovated, was not finished on time, and
                        also lacked space, forcing some MPs to share rooms. And these MPs were not
                        always from the same party, resulting in an atmosphere akin to a youth
                        hostel – a notion fuelled further by the fact that the residents would meet
                        in the evenings for guitar sing-alongs. However, this cross-party bonding
                        undoubtedly also helped them get to know each other better, and break down
                        any initial mistrust.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn16" n="15">Paul
                            Krüger, “Für einen geordneten Einigungsprozeß – zur Arbeit der
                            CDU/CDA-Fraktion,” in <hi rend="italic">Mandat für deutsche Einheit. Die
                                10. Volkskammer zwischen DDR-Verfassung und Grundgesetz,</hi> ed.
                            Richard Schröder et al. (Opladen: Leske + Budrich, 2000), 157.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-27">The working conditions were also anything but optimum,
                        with the infrastructure required for normal parliamentary operations
                        virtually completely lacking. There were hardly any offices or meeting
                        rooms, inadequate office materials, poor to negligible telecommunication,
                        and even problematic transportation to and from parliament. The Volkskammer
                        administration catering to the old setup could not handle the increased
                        workload.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-28">The meeting venue (the “Palast der Republik” until the
                        36th sitting) had been erected in the 1970s as a socialist cultural
                        establishment in the centre of Berlin on the site of the demolished City
                            Palace.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn17" n="16">Alexander Schug,
                            ed., <hi rend="italic">Palast der Republik. Politischer Diskurs und
                                private Erinnerung</hi> (Berlin: Berliner Wissenschafts-Verlag,
                            2007).</note> It was a multi-purpose building which the Volkskammer had
                        to share with several restaurants, theatres, a post office and a bowling
                        alley, among other things. As one of many occupants, the Volkskammer had no
                        other choice but to find other rooms to work in. The parties finally took up
                        quarters in the former building of the SED’s central committee at
                        Werderscher Markt, which had now been renamed the “Haus der Parlamentarier”
                        or “House of Parliamentarians”. The plenum also had to relocate there for
                        the last two meetings after the Palast der Republik closed overnight due to
                        an asbestos risk. Many MPs were mortified at having to move to this of all
                        places. Apart from this, the Lenin Hall where meetings were held was merely
                        a conference room and in no way suitable for parliamentary proceedings.
                        There was no separation between the parties; MPs sat closely next to one
                        another, making vote counts extremely complex. Visitors and journalists had
                        to crowd around the room’s side walls, because there was no separate seating
                        for them.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-125-articel-sub03">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-125-head-9">Help from the West</head>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-29">In view of all these challenges, the “big brothers”
                        from the West provided urgently required help and guidance – insofar as
                        sister parties existed, (as with SPD, CDU, the Liberals and Bündnis
                        90/Grüne), for parties like PDS and DBD/DFD had none.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-125-ftn18" n="17">The CDU and Liberals had emerged from the
                            GDR bloc parties CDU/NDPD, LDPD, while the SPD and Grüne were founded
                            during the autumn of 1989.</note> It would likely have been virtually
                        impossible for the Volkskammer to operate without the material and
                        non-material assistance of the Federal Republic of Germany, which included
                        technical equipment such as copiers, fax machines, telephones and cars, but
                        also information, training, counselling or simply money. For example, the
                        SPD, which received probably the best planned and most comprehensive aid,
                        had a contact office in East Berlin from as early as January 1990. The party
                        organised training sessions and information presentations before the 10th
                        Volkskammer was even constituted, and also provided the essential legal
                        support, for the difficulties started with the previously unheard-of
                        technology, which had to be painstakingly learned. At one point, 16 West
                        German consultants were working for the Social Democrats in the
                            Volkskammer.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn19" n="18">Martin
                            Gutzeit, “Aufbau, Organisation und Arbeit der SPD-Fraktion der
                            Volkskammer,” in <hi rend="italic">»Die Handschrift der SPD muss
                                erkennbar sein«: Die Fraktion der SPD in der Volkskammer der
                                DDR</hi>, ed. SPD-Bundestagsfraktion (Berlin: 2000).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-30">Certain periods saw Bonn colleagues figuring in almost
                        all parties and sometimes even in the Volkskammer’s house gallery – a
                        demonstration of affiliation always met by heartfelt approval from the
                            plenum.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn20" n="19">Cf. particularly
                            the meeting on June 17, 1990, which was especially criticised by the
                            PDS. Uwe-Jens Heuer exclaimed: “Do we want to swap places? They can come
                            down and we’ll go up.” ̶ 15th meeting on 17 June 1990, Protokolle,
                            535.</note> There were also a number of personal contacts available to
                        discuss problems. The German Bundestag similarly provided institutional
                        support, whether through administrative information, material resources and
                        money, or counselling on security issues. </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-31">To enable things to get moving quickly and smoothly
                        without any double-handling, attempts were made to establish as many
                        structures as possible parallel to those in Bonn. For example, the number
                        and layout of the committees in the Volkskammer was geared around the Bonn
                        model, as was the number and layout of the ministries or work groups within
                        the parties. The parties themselves also copied their respective sister
                        parties. Bündnis 90/Grüne, for instance, adopted the model of having
                        multiple spokespersons at the head of the party instead of one single leader
                        – which was very appropriate for this highly heterogeneous combination of
                        four groups originating in the civil-rights and environmental movement. This
                        prevented certain members from being disadvantaged during the allocation of
                        leadership positions. In the CDU/DA party, on the other hand, MPs formed
                        state groups at a time when states did not exist in the GDR – another
                        imitation of the West German model. The CDU in the Federal German Republic
                        traditionally had very strong state associations, major regional
                        differences, and a much more pluralist, decentralised organisational
                        structure than, for example, the Social Democrats, and this was also
                        reflected in the organisation of the Bundestag party, which similarly
                        featured regional sub-groups, the strongest of which being the single-party
                            CSU-Landesgruppe.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn21" n="20">Cf.
                            Hans-Peter Schwarz, ed., <hi rend="italic">Die Fraktion als Machtfaktor.
                                CDU/CSU im Deutschen Bundestag 1949 bis heute</hi> (München:
                            Pantheon, 2009).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-32">One of the most important tools in ensuring the
                        functionality and control of a parliament are the rules of procedure. The
                        Volkskammer’s old rules of procedure from 1974 were totally inadequate for
                        modern, democratic parliamentary proceedings. They were modified out of
                        necessity in April, and then definitively replaced in July 1990 by a version
                        closely resembling that adopted by the German Bundestag. But the first
                        drafts of this new version existed even before the election in March 1990.
                        The Volkskammer’s administration had prepared a draft drawing on the
                        Volkskammer rules of procedure from 1949, those of the Weimar Reichstag and
                        those of the German Bundestag. The SPD also started off with an elaborate
                        draft inspired by the Bundestag’s rules of procedure.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-33">Despite this comprehensive help, a lot went wrong in
                        everyday parliamentary life – though this is not a huge surprise.
                        Parliaments are complex institutions which operate in accordance with
                        countless written and unwritten rules. Being able to work professionally
                        requires a well-honed mechanism, and, in the case of the Volkskammer, this
                        first had to be put in motion.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-34">It is not, for instance, enough to simply have rules of
                        procedure; you also need to be able to apply them. Only the deputy head of
                        parliament, Reinhard Höppner (SPD), actually knew how to use them to run a
                        parliamentary session, primarily thanks to his experience as president and
                        chair at Protestant Church synods, though he also had a gift for the task.
                        Not only was he truly familiar with the various version of the rules of
                        procedure, he was particularly able to anticipate situations and their
                        consequences, think in alternatives, and find solutions in challenging
                        scenarios. No other members of the steering committee, not even the
                        president Sabine Bergmann-Pohl or her six deputies were able to do this, and
                        often found themselves floundering. Other parliamentary processes also
                        required practice, whether it was an “Aktuelle Stunde”, correct composition
                        and lodging of a petition, or the formalities for applying for a procedural
                        motion. Or even just the knowledge that, according to information provided
                        by the specialists from the work groups and committees, party meetings are
                        there to discuss and establish the strategy for the plenum, and do not have
                        to act as the place of endless debates on principles, especially when under
                        time constraints.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-125-articel-sub04">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-125-head-10">The 10th Volkskammer and the media</head>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-35">The 10th Volkskammer was permanently monitored
                        throughout all of this. Its process of self-parliamentarisation played out
                        in the public eye, for the Deutscher Fernsehfunk (GDR state television)
                        broadcast the plenary meetings live and almost always in full right from the
                            start.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn22" n="21">This video
                            material, spanning more than 200 hours, is available to the public, cf.
                            the co-operative project run by the German Bundestag, the Bundesarchiv
                            (German Federal Archives) and the Deutsches Rundfunkarchiv (German
                            Broadcasting Archive) on the German Bundestag’s website: <hi
                                rend="italic">Deutscher Bundestag – Mediathek</hi>, <ref
                                target="http://www.bundestag.de/kulturundgeschichte/geschichte/parlamentarismus/10_volkskammer/mediathek"
                                >http://www.bundestag.de/kulturundgeschichte/geschichte/parlamentarismus/10_volkskammer/mediathek</ref>.
                            Cf. also Bettina Tüffers, “Die Volkskammer im Fernsehen. Strategien der
                            Selbstinszenierung in der 10. Volkskammer der DDR,” in <hi rend="italic"
                                >Lebenswelten von Abgeordneten in Europa 1860–1990</hi>, ed. Adéla
                            Gjuričová et al. (Düsseldorf: Droste 2014). </note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-36">The media’s interest in the Volkskammer had not just
                        surfaced with the election of 18 March 1990. A detailed GDR TV report from
                        the Chamber began as early as 24 October 1989, i.e. the final phase of the
                        9th Volkskammer. The TV covered the final eight meetings of this legislative
                        period live, broadcasting some 60 hours from the Palast der Republik between
                        24 October 1989 and 7 March 1990. The live coverage of the 10th Volkskammer
                        continued this practice. </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-37">All parties involved expected a lot from it, not least
                        the citizens, who naturally wanted to see how their representatives handled
                        their mandate. There was consequently great interest in the broadcasts at
                        this time, with people watching them regularly and, most importantly,
                        together in groups.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-38">The Volkskammer itself was, however, also convinced of
                        the importance of transparency, openness and information as conveyed by the
                        television. With this new understanding of the public sphere, enabling the
                        citizens to watch them perform their work, the MPs purposely wanted to break
                        away from the practices of their predecessor. “Watch” can also easily be
                        replaced with the word “monitor”, for that is what it boiled down to. This
                        became particularly apparent in the constitutive meeting to elect the
                        president and steering committee. What was unusual about it was the method
                        for counting the votes, which took place in front of everyone in the
                        Chamber, with the head of the Volkskammer administration, surrounded by the
                        parties’ secretaries, reading out each individual ballot paper.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn23" n="22">Cf. the video recordings of
                            the meeting dated April 5, 1990: <hi rend="italic">Deutscher Bundestag:
                                On-Demand Video</hi>, accessed October 12, 2015, <ref
                                target="http://webtv.bundestag.de/iptv/player/macros/_v_f_514_de/bttv/od_player.html?singleton=true&amp;content=526621"
                                >http://webtv.bundestag.de/iptv/player/macros/_v_f_514_de/bttv/od_player.html?singleton=true&amp;content=526621</ref>.</note>
                        As transparent and comprehensible as this process was for everyone, it was
                        also extremely tedious, and tested the patience of MPs, journalists and
                        viewers alike. The Volkskammer thus later did away with such laborious
                        procedures.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-39">The permanent television coverage did, however, have
                        unwanted and unexpected side effects. The Volkskammer did not have set
                        regulations regarding what was filmed and how it was filmed.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn24" n="23">Similar to the German
                            Bundestag and in complete contrast to institutions such as the British
                            parliament, cf. Tüffers, “Fernsehen”.</note> As a result, viewers not
                        only saw all the various parliamentary routines as they occurred, but also
                        chaotic meeting scenes; they saw MPs reading, eating or chatting, they saw
                        empty rows of seats, and they began to complain. The many letters received
                        by the Volkskammer attest to this.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn25"
                            n="24">BArch DA 1/16731.</note> Within a very short space of time, it
                        had developed a major image problem. In July, the steering committee felt
                        obliged to draft up a code of conduct, in which the MPs were asked to behave
                        in a manner respecting the dignity of the House, for the parliament’s image
                        was heavily defined by the television broadcasts.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-125-ftn26" n="25">BArch DA 1/16625, 65 f, Letter dated July
                            4, 1990.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-40">The MPs simply had not realised that, by adopting the
                        West German model of parliamentarianism, they had virtually automatically
                        also signed up to the associated by-products, i.e. the understanding of the
                        public sphere and the unique media situation. Just as they had to learn how
                        to handle the interaction between parliament, the media and the public in
                        general, they also had to learn that live television broadcasts did not
                        simply paint a neutral picture of the goings-on, but significantly
                        influenced viewer responses through camera work, editing or commentary.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-125-articel-sub05">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-125-head-11">The new states</head>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-41">The GDR was a centralist nation, while the Federal
                        Republic of Germany was and is, historically, a federal one.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn27" n="26">“The Federal Republic of
                            Germany is a democratic and social state,” Art. 20 (1) GG. The so-called
                            “eternity clause” in Art. 79 (3) GG further stipulates: “Amendments to
                            this Basic Law affecting the division of the Federation into Länder,
                            their participation on principle in the legislative process, or the
                            principles laid down in Articles 1 and 20 shall be inadmissible.”</note>
                        Within it, the execution of national authorisations and tasks is a state
                        matter, as per Article 30 of the Basic Law, unless otherwise stated or
                        permitted. </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-42">The GDR once also had states for a short time: The five
                        states of Mecklenburg, Saxony-Anhalt, Thuringia, Brandenburg and Saxony
                        established by the Soviet Military Administration in 1945, which were
                        replaced by 14 districts as part of the “Construction of Socialism” (“Aufbau
                        des Sozialismus”) announced at the 2nd SED party conference in July 1952.
                        The borders were primarily established based on economic interests, although
                        the restructuring also aimed for centralisation, control and the elimination
                        of self-administration (“democratic centralism”). The districts had no
                        political autonomy.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn28" n="27"
                            >“Measures to change the national structure in the German Democratic
                            Republic” dated April 29, 1952 and the “Law on further democratisation
                            of the structure and working methods of national bodies in the states of
                            the German Democratic Republic” dated 23 July 1952, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Gesetzblatt der Deutschen Demokratischen Republik</hi> 1: 613.
                            Henning Mielke, <hi rend="italic">Die Auflösung der Länder in der
                                SBZ/DDR. Von der deutschen Selbstverwaltung zum
                                sozialistisch-zentralistischen Einheitsstaat nach sowjetischem
                                Modell 1945–1952</hi> (Stuttgart: Steiner, 1995), 76–80.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-43">But it was not able to achieve what its leaders had
                        intended for these measures, namely a radical break with state traditions,
                        considered to be irrelevant remnants of Wilhelmine Germany, and the “final
                        elimination of federalism, parliamentarianism and the principle of
                        separating powers”,<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn29" n="28"
                            >Karl-Heinz Kajna, <hi rend="italic">Länder – Bezirke – Länder: Zur
                                Territorialstruktur im Osten Deutschlands 1945–1990</hi> (Frankfurt
                            am Main: Lang, 1995), 107.</note> as soon became patently clear in 1989.
                        The major demonstrations of autumn 1989 in the GDR saw the call for new
                        states to be formed become more vocal, with local citizens deeming it a
                        “guarantor for free democratic basic order”.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-125-ftn30" n="29">Michael Richter, “Die Entstehung der neuen
                            Bundesländer 1989/90,” in <hi rend="italic">Länder, Gaue und Bezirke.
                                Mitteldeutschland im 20. Jahrhundert</hi>, ed. Michael Richter et
                            al. (Dresden: Mitteldeutscher Verlag, 2008), 279.</note> The states
                        became a central moment of identification at a time where the superseded
                        social and political structures were rapidly dissolving.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-44">The Modrow government had established a “Commission to
                        prepare and perform an administrative reform” in the GDR in 1989, but left
                        other regulations to the subsequent Volkskammer. During the government
                        policy statement of 19 April 1990, Prime Minister de Maizière then labelled
                        the state structure “one of the basic conditions for German unity, a
                        fundamental structure for democracy, and a pre-requisite for successfully
                        restructuring our economy”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn31" n="30"
                            >3rd meeting on 19 April 1990, Protokolle, 49.</note> In late July 1990,
                        the Volkskammer finally decided to (re-)constitute the five states of
                        Mecklenburg-Vorpommern, Brandenburg, Thuringia, Saxony-Anhalt and Saxony on
                        14 October 1990, thereby re-establishing the federal structures which had
                        been dissolved by the GDR leaders in late 1952.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-125-ftn32" n="31">Law governing the establishment of states,
                            dated 22 July 1990, <hi rend="italic">Gesetzblatt der Deutschen
                                Demokratischen Republik</hi> 1: 955.</note> Apart from a few border
                        regions, the shape and layout of the new states matched those formerly
                        defined by the Soviet Military Administration in 1945. </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-45">However, the fact that it ended up being precisely
                        these five states, and no other options (such as forming just three or four
                        larger states) were seriously taken into consideration, was also a result of
                        the federal government and West German states having massive influence over
                        the decision, particularly financially. Bonn was not interested in extended
                        discussions with uncertain outcomes.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-125-ftn33" n="32">One suggestion stated, for example, that
                            only three states – Mecklenburg, Brandenburg and Saxony-Thuringia –
                            should be formed. ̶ Richter, “Entstehung,” 282–285.</note> This meant
                        that the adjustment of both countries’ national and administrative
                        structures which became necessary during the German reunification was
                        primarily the task of the GDR. It adopted the West German model to set up
                        the complex equalisation system and distribute skills among the individual
                        states, and between the states and the federal government. But this did not
                        meet with any criticism or even resistance in the GDR. On the contrary: it
                        was preaching to the converted. In fact, hardly any other issue appears to
                        have reached “such a broad consensus among all political powers”.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn34" n="33">Ibid., 280.</note> The
                        emerging parties and other organisations even anticipated the development by
                        “[establishing] regional associations geared around the state structures
                        which had existed until 1952 before the states themselves had actually been
                            formed”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn35" n="34">Ibid.</note>
                        And, as mentioned earlier, the CDU/DA party modelled its structure on that
                        of the CDU/CSU by combining MPs into state-based groups, once again before
                        the states even existed.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-46">The identity-boosting aspect of introducing the new
                        states was actually visible in the Volkskammer, with colours being shown in
                        more than just a figurative sense. Dresden-born DSU member Lothar Klein
                        appeared before his colleagues at the discussion relating to the “Prime
                        Minister’s report on the Moscow summit of foreign ministers regarding the
                        two-plus-four negotiations” on 20 September wearing an unusual tie bearing
                        the Saxon state coat of arms in the state colours green and white. He was
                        not the only one; at that same meeting, CDU/DA member Michael Albrecht, from
                        the Saxon town of Riesa, demonstrated his home ties in the same striking
                            manner,<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn36" n="35">36th meeting on
                            20 September 1990, Protokolle, 1767 f.</note> while Klein’s party
                        colleague Norbert Koch, the Saxon state leader of the DSU, had quoted the
                        first verse of Maximilian Hallbauer’s 1842 “Sachsenlied” in the plenum as
                        early as 21 June.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn37" n="36">16th
                            meeting on 21 June 1990, Protokolle, 583.</note> And as if to show that
                        the passion for all things Saxon really did extend across all parties,
                        Christine Ostrowski (PDS) from Dresden stepped up to the lectern on 6 July
                        dressed in black and yellow “as a sign of my bond with the future state
                        capital of Saxony”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn38" n="37">22nd
                            meeting on 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> July 1990, Protokolle, 936.
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-47">In retrospect, Volkskammer president Sabine
                        Bergmann-Pohl found it “remarkable that ‘state-conscious attitudes’ had
                        emerged so soon after the start of the political change”. […] I thought it
                        was a good starting point for completely normal, federative developments in
                        our new society and our nation”<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn39"
                            n="38">Sabine Bergmann-Pohl, “Die frei gewählte Volkskammer,” in <hi
                                rend="italic">Mandat für deutsche Einheit. Die 10. Volkskammer
                                zwischen DDR-Verfassung und Grundgesetz</hi>, ed. Richard Schröder
                            et. al (Opladen: Leske + Budrich, 2000), 61.</note> – a point which
                        Grüne member Bernd Reichelt also highlighted in the first reading of the
                        Ländereinführungsgesetz (the act establishing the new states). However, he
                        appeared far less surprised by it than Bergmann-Pohl, commenting that “The
                        GDR was not actually able to develop its own identity, despite 40 years of
                        efforts by the party leaders and government. The feeling of belonging to a
                        particular state in a historic and cultural context has largely endured, and
                        we can particularly notice this today in the emotional way people are
                        responding to the formation of the states. The House never reached an
                        agreement on how to surrender the GDR’s sovereignty, but I think there is a
                        consensus when it comes to establishing states. The states will be the
                        future reference framework for the people of the GDR when the GDR no longer
                            exists.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn40" n="39">17th meeting on
                            22 June 1990, Protokolle, 670. Cf. also Michael Richter,
                            “Föderalisierung als Ergebnis der friedlichen Revolution in der DDR
                            1989/90,” in <hi rend="italic">15 Jahre Deutsche Einheit. Was ist
                                geworden?,</hi> ed. Gerhard Besier et al. (Berlin: LIT 2007),
                            57.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-48">The behaviour of the Saxon members in particular –
                        Brandenburgers or Thuringians, for example, did not display their regional
                        allegiances as openly – must be viewed in the context of the imminent
                        elections; the first state parliamentary elections in the GDR were held on
                        14 October 1990, and the first pan-German Bundestag was elected in early
                        December. This demonstration of regional identity was thus a clear political
                        statement against the centralist GDR and in favour of the federal
                        restructuring. But it was also a sign of regional identification which had
                        never totally disappeared. Particularly in a time of political and economic
                        instability and rapid change, it provided cohesion and guidance.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-125-articel-sub06">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-125-head-12">Conclusion: Just a keen student or a parliament
                        with its own culture?</head>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-49">Immediately after the Volkskammer was dissolved in
                        October 1990, the members themselves became some of the harshest critics of
                        its work. Many felt heteronomous, driven and dominated by the events and
                        decisions of their own government and Bonn politics, sometimes simply
                        overwhelmed, working under permanent time constraints, without any
                        opportunity to make their own decisions or even work through drafts to the
                        point that people could vote on them in good faith.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ojs-125-ftn41" n="40">Cf. e.g. the interviews in the
                            Parliamentary Press Service of the GDR’s Volkskammer, No. 11, 1 October
                            1990 or the critical summaries by the party leaders at the last meeting
                            on October 2, 1990, Protokolle, 1863–1872. </note> By the time the
                        accession date had been set in the August for 3 October, and the Unification
                        treaty had been passed in the September, they had become redundant. The
                        feeling of powerlessness varied depending on which party the MPs belonged
                        to. It was most intense among the opposition parties. </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-50">The Stasi-Unterlagen-Gesetz (the act on the GDR’s state
                        security documents), which was only incorporated into the Unification Treaty
                        in this form at the urging of the parliament – against the intentions of the
                        government in Bonn –, was considered one of the few positive factors of
                        their work. The request for their own constitution, backed by the
                        opposition, however, was one of the many wishes left unfulfilled.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ojs-125-ftn42" n="41">Gunnar Peters,
                            “Verfassungsfragen in der 10. Volkskammer der DDR (1990),” <hi
                                rend="italic">Deutschland Archiv</hi> 37 (2004).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-51">Circumstances had admittedly made it difficult for the
                        10th democratically elected Volkskammer to develop its own profile as a
                        parliament. The task it had been assigned with the victory of the “Allianz
                        für Deutschland”, namely to arrange reunification with the Federal Republic
                        of Germany as quickly as possible, allowed very few alternatives or
                        independent solutions. Parliamentary structures first had to be established.
                        This affected institutional aspects just as much as it did the work methods
                        and everyday organisational matters of the MPs, including relations between
                        the parliament and the media and public.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-52">Neither the meeting venue nor the working conditions
                        were appropriate, the role of MP had to be defined and adapted to the new
                        requirements, and unknown parliamentary institutions and formalities had to
                        be introduced and tested. All this had to be borne by parliamentary novices,
                        making the need for assistance inevitable. This help, which came largely
                        from West German affiliate parties, as well as the German Bundestag, was
                        extensive, albeit not totally selfless, for it also pursued personal
                        interests in relation to future election successes. The help included
                        supplies of material and money, as well as immaterial support through
                        information, training and counselling.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-53">The 10th Volkskammer of the GDR differed from
                        established parliaments in many respects. In terms of its operating style,
                        it was generally considered more passionate, more spontaneous, more geared
                        around consensus, and more interested in fact-based, cross-party
                        problem-solving rather than fierce political discussions following rigid
                        party boundaries. But we must be cautious about construing this as a new,
                        fresher, more spontaneous, “more humane” form of parliamentary culture which
                        contrasts with the reputedly cold, aloof, professional Bonn/Berlin setup. As
                        time passed, the MPs’ harsh self-criticism gave way to a milder view of
                        things, which outweighed the enthusiasm over the experiences gained at the
                        time. Much of what was deemed negative and detrimental in 1990 was
                        reinterpreted as a positive: Chaos gave rise to improvisation, and a lack of
                        combativeness resulted in a preference for objective discussion and
                        consensual decision-making. This focus on consensus undoubtedly tied in with
                        the still-ambiguous differentiation between political parties, the
                        difficulty of the task, and the common goals despite all differences, but
                        also with the lack of parliamentary practice and uncertainty in dealings
                        with one another. Party discipline was, without question, also far less
                        intense than it is today, but conduct deviating from the party line during
                        votes can easily be tolerated when you have the comfortable majority the
                        coalition had in its first few months. A greater focus was also placed on
                        discipline within the parties in the Volkskammer once things became less
                        cut-and-dried for critical votes. There were also controversial
                        interjections, heated debates and personal attacks.</p>
                    <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-54">The “either/or” question raised in the title is thus
                        too strict. The 10th Volkskammer of the GDR was indeed a keen student; it
                        was capable of learning and incredibly diligent. But its work was never
                        completely heteronomous – both sides had identical intentions, not just in
                        the case of establishing the new states – nor was it a parliament with a
                        true culture of its own. The external circumstances, including considerable
                        time constraints, in which it operated required a pragmatic approach to the
                        extremely complex tasks. Well-honed rules and processes which had been tried
                        and tested elsewhere were used. While this left little room for its own
                        initiatives, it did enable things to run more or less smoothly.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr" xml:id="ojs-125-bibliogr">
                <head xml:id="ojs-125-head-13">Sources and references</head>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-125-bibliogr-sub01">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-125-head-14">Archive sources</head>
                    <list type="unordered" xml:id="ojs-125-list-1">
                        <item>BArch, Bundesarchiv DA 1:<list>
                                <item>Volkskammer der DDR: DA 1/16625 and DA 1/16731.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-125-bibliogr-sub02">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-125-head-15">Literature</head>
                    <listBibl xml:id="ojs-125-listBibl-1">
                        <bibl>Bergmann-Pohl, Sabine. “Die frei gewählte Volkskammer.” In <hi
                                rend="italic">Mandat für deutsche Einheit. Die 10. Volkskammer
                                zwischen DDR-Verfassung und Grundgesetz</hi>, edited by Richard
                            Schröder and Hans Misselwitz, 49–65. Opladen: Leske + Budrich,
                            2000.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Gutzeit, Martin. “Aufbau, Organisation und Arbeit der SPD-Fraktion der
                            Volkskammer.” In <hi rend="italic">ʻDie Handschrift der SPD muss
                                erkennbar seinʼ. Die Fraktion der SPD in der Volkskammer der
                                DDR</hi>, edited by SPD-Bundestagsfraktion, 23–36. Berlin:
                            2000.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hausmann, Christopher. <hi rend="italic">Biographisches Handbuch der
                                10. Volkskammer der DDR (1990).</hi> Köln, Weimar, Wien: Böhlau,
                            2000.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Kajna, Karl-Heinz. <hi rend="italic">Länder – Bezirke – Länder: Zur
                                Territorialstruktur im Osten Deutschlands 1945–1990</hi>. Frankfurt
                            am Main: Lang, 1995.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Kelle, Herbert and Tord Riemann. <hi rend="italic">Die Volkskammer –
                                wie sie arbeitet.</hi> Berlin: Staatsverlag der Deutschen
                            Demokratischen Republik, 1989.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Kloth, Hans Michael. <hi rend="italic">Vom ʻZettelfaltenʼ zum freien
                                Wählen. Die Demokratisierung der DDR 1989/90 und die
                                ʻWahlfrageʼ.</hi> Berlin: Links, 2000.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Kowalczuk, Ilko-Sascha. <hi rend="italic">Endspiel. Die Revolution von
                                1989 in der DDR.</hi> München: Beck, 2009.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Krüger, Paul. “Für einen geordneten Einigungsprozeß – zur Arbeit der
                            CDU/CDA-Fraktion.” In <hi rend="italic">Mandat für deutsche Einheit. Die
                                10. Volkskammer zwischen DDR-Verfassung und Grundgesetz,</hi> edited
                            by Richard Schröder and Hans Misselwitz, 153–162. Opladen: Leske +
                            Budrich, 2000.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Mielke, Henning. <hi rend="italic">Die Auflösung der Länder in der
                                SBZ/DDR. Von der deutschen Selbstverwaltung zum
                                sozialistisch-zentralistischen Einheitsstaat nach sowjetischem
                                Modell 1945–1952.</hi> Stuttgart: Steiner, 1995.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Müller-Enbergs, Helmut. “Welchen Charakter hatte die Volkskammer nach
                            den Wahlen am 18. März 1990?.” <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für
                                Parlamentsfragen</hi> 22 (1991): 450–467.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Patzelt, Werner J. and Roland Schirmer, ed. <hi rend="italic">Die
                                Volkskammer der DDR. Sozialistischer Parlamentarismus in Theorie und
                                Praxis.</hi> Wiesbaden: Westdeutscher Verlag, 2002.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Peters, Gunnar. “Verfassungsfragen in der 10. Volkskammer der DDR
                            (1990).” <hi rend="italic">Deutschland Archiv</hi> 37 (2004):
                            828–839.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Protokolle der Volkskammer der Deutschen Demokratischen Republik: 10.
                            Wahlperiode (vom 5. April bis 2. Oktober 1990), edited by Deutscher
                            Bundestag, Referat Öffentlichkeitsarbeit. Berlin: 2000</bibl>
                        <bibl>Richter, Michael. “Die Entstehung der neuen Bundesländer 1989/90.” In
                                <hi rend="italic">Länder, Gaue und Bezirke. Mitteldeutschland im 20.
                                Jahrhundert</hi>, edited by Michael Richter, Thomas Schaarschmidt
                            and Mike Schmeitzner, 279–306. Dresden: Mitteldeutscher Verlag,
                            2008.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Richter, Michael. “Föderalisierung als Ergebnis der friedlichen
                            Revolution in der DDR 1989/90.” In <hi rend="italic">15 Jahre Deutsche
                                Einheit. Was ist geworden?,</hi> edited by Gerhard Besier and
                            Katarzyna Stokłosa, 57–71. Berlin: LIT 2007.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Sabrow, Martin. “Der vergessene ‘Dritte Wegʼ.” <hi rend="italic">Aus
                                Politik und Zeitgeschichte</hi> 11 (2010): 6–13.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Schirmer, Roland. “Machtzerfall und Restabilisierung der Volkskammer
                            im Lauf der Friedlichen Revolution.” In <hi rend="italic">Parlamente und
                                ihre Macht. Kategorien und Fallbeispiele institutioneller
                                Analyse,</hi> edited by Werner J. Patzelt, 171–215. Baden-Baden:
                            Nomos, 2005.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Schug, Alexander, ed. <hi rend="italic">Palast der Republik.
                                Politischer Diskurs und private Erinnerung</hi>. Berlin: Berliner
                            Wissenschafts-Verlag, 2007.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Schwarz, Hans-Peter, ed. <hi rend="italic">Die Fraktion als
                                Machtfaktor. CDU/CSU im Deutschen Bundestag 1949 bis heute</hi>.
                            München: Pantheon, 2009.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Thaysen, Uwe. <hi rend="italic">Der Runde Tisch. Oder: Wo blieb das
                                Volk? Der Weg der DDR in die Demokratie</hi>. Opladen: Westdeutscher
                            Verlag, 1990.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Tüffers, Bettina. “Die Volkskammer im Fernsehen. Strategien der
                            Selbstinszenierung in der 10. Volkskammer der DDR.” In <hi rend="italic"
                                >Lebenswelten von Abgeordneten in Europa 1860–1990</hi>, edited by
                            Adéla Gjuričová, Andreas Schulz, Luboš Velek and Andreas Wirsching,
                            311–332. Düsseldorf: Droste 2014.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Volkskammer der Deutschen Demokratischen Republik, 9. Wahlperiode,
                            Protokolle von der 1. Tagung am 16. Juni 1986 bis zur 18. Tagung am 6.
                            und 7. März 1990, vol. 25. Berlin: 1990.</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="ojs-125-bibliogr-sub03">
                    <head xml:id="ojs-125-head-16">Other sources</head>
                    <listBibl xml:id="ojs-125-listBibl-2">
                        <bibl>
                            <hi rend="italic">Gesetzblatt der Deutschen Demokratischen Republik</hi>
                            1.</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl" xml:id="ojs-125-summary">
                <head xml:id="ojs-125-head-17">Povzetek</head>
                <head rend="subtitle" xml:id="ojs-125-head-18">10. skupščina NDR – Le zavzeta učenka
                    ali parlament z lastno kulturo?</head>
                <docAuthor xml:id="ojs-125-docAuthor-2">Bettina Tüffers</docAuthor>
                <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-55">10. sklic skupščine Nemške demokratične republike (NDR) je
                    gotovo bil nenavaden parlament. Obstajal je le šest mesecev – od konstituiranja
                    5. aprila 1990 do 2. oktobra 1990. V tem času je parlament na 38 plenarnih sejah
                    sprejel več kot 150 zakonov in 100 resolucij. Kot prvi in zadnji svobodno
                    izvoljeni demokratični parlament NDR je bil odgovoren za organizacijo
                    vzhodnonemškega dela pravno in ekonomsko zahtevne nemške združitve. Pri tem je
                    razpustil sebe in državo, katere državljane je predstavljal. Za nameček so
                    morali to nalogo opraviti poslanci, ki niso imeli skoraj nobenih izkušenj z
                    delovanjem parlamentarne demokracije ali parlamenta. Zgodovina te skupščine je
                    zanimiva tudi zato, ker se je (samo)parlamentarizacija odvila pred očmi javnosti
                    – ljudje so lahko opazovali novo izvoljene poslance, kako so se hitro učili
                    svojega “poklica”. Ker je šlo za 400 poslancev brez parlamentarnih izkušenj, je
                    bila potrebna pomoč iz Zahodne Nemčije.</p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-56">Pri tem se postavlja vprašanje, ali bi bila lahko v
                    tedanjih okoliščinah zadnja skupščina NDR več kot le zavzeta učenka
                    zahodnonemških učiteljev, ali ji je vseeno uspelo izoblikovati lasten
                    parlamentarni profil.</p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-57">Treba je priznati, da so dane razmere demokratično
                    izvoljeni skupščini oteževale, da bi se izoblikovala kot parlament. Naloga, ki
                    jo je dobila z zmago koalicije “Allianz für Deutschland”, in sicer da izvede čim
                    hitrejšo združitev z Zvezno republiko Nemčijo, ji ni omogočala veliko možnosti
                    ali neodvisnih rešitev.</p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-58">10. skupščina NDR se je v marsičem razlikovala od običajnih
                    parlamentov. Njeno delovanje bi lahko na splošno opredelili kot bolj čustveno in
                    spontano, bolj usmerjeno v doseganje konsenza in medstrankarsko reševanje težav
                    na podlagi dejstev namesto burnih političnih razprav v okviru strogih
                    strankarskih omejitev. Vendar moramo biti previdni, preden to opredelimo kot
                    novo, bolj svežo, spontano ali “človeško” obliko parlamentarne kulture, ki je
                    nasprotje domnevno hladne, vzvišene in profesionalne drže Bonna/Berlina. Sčasoma
                    je strogo samokritičnost poslancev nadomestil prizanesljivejši nazor, ki je
                    prevladal nad navdušenjem ob pridobljenih izkušnjah. Veliko zadev, ki so leta
                    1990 veljale za negativne in škodljive, je bilo prevrednotenih v pozitivnem
                    smislu. Kaos je vodil v improvizacijo in nepripravljenost za spopad je dala
                    prednost objektivnim razpravam ter sporazumnemu sprejemanju odločitev. Ta
                    osredotočenost na konsenz je nedvomno sovpadala s še vedno nejasnim
                    razlikovanjem med političnimi strankami, težavnostjo naloge in skupnimi cilji
                    kljub vsem razlikam, vendar pa tudi s pomanjkanjem parlamentarne prakse in
                    negotovimi medsebojnimi odnosi. Strankarska disciplina je bila vsekakor tudi
                    precej ohlapnejša od današnje, vendar je odstopanje od partijskih smernic med
                    glasovanjem mogoče dopustiti, kadar je zagotovljena zadostna večina, ki jo je
                    koalicija imela v prvih mesecih. Stranke v skupščini NDR so se bolj posvetile
                    uveljavljanju notranje discipline, ko odločilni glasovi niso bili več tako
                    samoumevni. Manj je bilo tudi kljubovalnih medklicev, razgretih razprav in
                    osebnih napadov.</p>
                <p xml:id="ojs-125-p-59">Vprašanje “ali/ali” iz naslova je torej prestrogo. 10.
                    skupščina NDR je bila vsekakor zavzeta učenka, ki se je bila sposobna učiti in
                    je bila nadvse prizadevna. Vendar njeno delovanje ni bilo nikoli povsem
                    podrejeno – obe strani sta imeli enake namene, ne le v primeru ustanovitve novih
                    držav – prav tako pa ni bila parlament z resnično lastno kulturo. Zunanje
                    okoliščine, vključno s precejšnjimi časovnimi omejitvami, v katerih je delovala,
                    so zahtevale pragmatičen pristop k izjemno zahtevnim nalogam. Uporabljena so
                    bila utečena pravila in postopki, ki so bili preizkušeni in preverjeni že
                    drugod. To sicer ni dopuščalo veliko prostora za lastne pobude, je pa omogočilo
                    sorazmerno nemoteno delovanje.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
